<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE eoh SYSTEM "eoh.dtd">

<eoh>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>a</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(the first letter of the Sanskrit alphabet)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Being the first manifest sound that emerged out of the ḍamaru (miniature drum) of Lord Śiva during his famous dance (tāṇḍavanṛtya), it is the first letter of the Sanskrit alphabet and the fundamental sound without which no other letter can be pronounced. Hence it is identified with God himself or used as his symbol. The Sanskrit lexicons give as many as 31 meanings and it is used in six different ways in grammar.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abādhita</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;not contradicted&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>In Indian philosophical systems, the word bādha and its derivatives are often used as technical terms, in the sense of objection or contradiction. Hence &#x2018;abādhita&#x2019; means that which is not contradicted, &#x2018;a&#x2019; representing the negative particle. For instance, truth or reality is defined as that which is abādhita, never contradicted. Obviously what is contradicted can never be considered true or real in the ultimate sense.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhaṅgas</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Lyrical poems, the compositions of the mystics of Maharashtra, are popularly known as &#x2018;abhaṅgas.&#x2019; &#x2018;Abhaṅga&#x2019; literally means &#x2018;unbroken or indivisible.&#x2019; The story goes that when Sant Tukārām, one of the greatest saints of Maharashtra, was compelled by his detractors to consign his poetical works to the river Indrāyaṇī, Lord Viṭṭhala (Viṣṇu) restored them to their author saying that the works were &#x2018;abhaṅga&#x2019; (&#x2018;indestructible&#x2019;). That apart, it is true that these poems and songs abound in philosophical, mystical and ethical teachings which are &#x2018;abhaṅga&#x2019; and hence true for all time. Besides Tukārām, several other saints like Jñāneśvar, Nāmdev, Eknāth and Rāmdās, including women saints like Janābāi and Kānhopātrā have composed these abhaṅgas. Importance of the divine name and its repetition in spiritual life, God-realisation as the <em>summum bonum</em> of life, the necessity of acquiring guru&#x2019;s grace, the harmony of worldly life and spiritual life, the need for inculcating moral values in day-to-day life are some of the oft-recurring themes of these compositions. If making the abstract spiritual truths intelligible and practicable to the common masses is the measure of success of religious reform movements, the Bhakti Movement of the saints of Maharashtra through their abhaṅgas has succeeded admirably. Even today these abhaṅgas are sung by the common folk.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ābhāsa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;appearance&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Literally the word means a &#x2018;reflection,&#x2019; an &#x2018;appearance,&#x2019; hence, a false phenomenon which shows itself as the real. For instance, the reflection of an object in a mirror is an &#x2018;ābhāsa.&#x2019; The word is widely used in Advaita Vedānta in the context of the relationship between the jīva (individual self) and Brahman (the Supreme Self). The jīva according to one of the schools of Advaita Vedānta, is only an &#x2018;ābhāsa&#x2019; of Brahman in and through the medium of the antaḥkaraṇa (mind).</p>
			<p>In Hindu logic, the word is used with regard to hetu or cause. Owing to several factors, a real hetu can get obscured and a false hetu, hetvābhāsa, can appear in its place leading to wrong conclusions. For more details see <ref>HETVĀBHĀSA</ref>.</p>
			<p>In temple architecture, the word stands for a particular type of vimāna (tower over the <em>sanctum sanctorum</em>).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhāva</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;non-existence&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The production of an effect is the sign of the existence of the cause. In the same way, the non-production of it is the sign of its non-existence. This is the line of argument adopted by the Vaiśeṣika system, one of the two dialectical schools of Hindu philosophy. According to it, the non-perception of a jar in the ground before us is the same as the perception of the non-existence, abhāva, of the jar. This is the only system which considers abhāva as a fundamental category of reality and describes four kinds of it:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>prāgabhāva—non-existence before coming into being, as for e.g., the non-existence of the jar before it is produced;</li>
				<li>pradhvaṁsābhāva—non-existence after destruction, as for e.g., the non-existence of the jar after it is destroyed;</li>
				<li>anyonyābhāva—mutual non-existence of two different objects, as for e.g., the non-existence of the cow in the horse and <em>vice versa</em>; and</li>
				<li>atyantā- bhāva—absolute non-existence, as for e.g., the non-existence of colour in air.</li>
			</ol>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhāva-yoga</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;yoga of negation&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Some of the Śaiva schools of philosophy describe yoga as being of five kinds, one of which is abhāva-yoga. In this state, the fourth yogic plane to be ascended, the yogi transcends the world appearance in its various forms. He is not concerned with the world. To him, the world has practically disappeared. Hence the name abhāva-yoga, the mystic experi-ence (yoga) in which the world has been negated (abhāva).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhayahasta</word>
			<alias>abhayamudrā</alias>
			<note>(&#x2018;hand [pose indicating] protection from fear&#x2019;)</note>
			<image>abhayahasta.png</image>
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The icons of gods and goddesses of the Hindu pantheon, whether they are of the aspects of the Supreme or of the minor deities presiding over various powers of the cosmos, often display this pose. Usually the right hand is shown raised, exhibiting the palm and with the fingers extended. It symbolises assurance of protection from fear and danger. It is but natural for mankind, with its fear of the unknown, to seek protection from the Divine and to believe in an appropriate response from It.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>MUDRĀS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhicāra</word>
			<alias>abhicārakarma</alias>
			<note>(&#x2018;black magic,&#x2019; &#x2018;exorcism,&#x2019; &#x2018;exorcistical act&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>In the eternal quest for happiness, peace and pleasure, man is often compelled to counteract the various forces and powers that thwart this quest. When common or natural remedies available to him fail to bring the desired result, he naturally turns towards uncommon and supernatural remedies. Attempts at enlisting the help of the supernatural, be it a fierce deity, a ghost or a disembodied spirit, are a common feature of all cultures. Hinduism seems to be no exception to this. The rites of abhicāra, though occasionally mentioned in the <em>Ṛgveda</em>, are found in abundance in the last of the Vedas, the <em>Atharvaveda</em> as also the subsidiary works based on it like the <em>Āṅgirasa Kalpasūtras</em> and the <em>Kauśika Kalpasūtras</em>. These rites pertain to a wide variety of subjects ranging from curing serious ailments, inflicting injury on enemies and rivals, winning the love of the beloved, to securing long life and prosperity. For instance, if a woman ties a particular root on her body with appropriate mantras, the mind of her husband is attracted only towards her and not towards her co-wives. A person harassed by enemies can perform certain rites by which spirits called kṛtyās will come to his help in overcoming them. Persons suffering from incurable diseases are advised to wear certain amulets like mūlamaṇi, duly consecrated.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ATHARVAVEDA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ābhicārika-mūrti</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;image pertaining to abhicāra&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>According to Hindu iconography certain categories of the images of Viṣṇu whose installation and consecration help in black magical rites for the destruction of enemies, are classed under the ābhicārika type. These images, whether in the standing, sitting or lying posture, are bereft of beauty or symmetry. Emaciated body, dark complexion, dark clothes and a shrunken countenance with the eyes turned upwards characterise such images. They are, as a rule, established in the outermost periphery of the village or town, known as the &#x2018;paiśācapada&#x2019; (the place where goblins live), in inaccessible places like mountain tops or thick jungles. Installation is done at inauspicious moments and worship conducted through magical formulae and sorcery.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ABHICĀRA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhihitānvaya-vāda</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;theory of words in relation&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The darśanas or Indian philosophical systems were very particular in working out their own theories about the meanings of words and sentences, because, upon these depended the development of their arguments to establish their schools <em>vis-a-vis</em> other schools.</p>
			<p>A word may have a direct meaning as also an implied meaning. When such words are put together to form a sentence, the total effect may be something more than the meanings indicated by the individual words. Different schools differ as regards the details.</p>
			<p>The above theory is propounded by the Nyāya school and accepted by Kumārila Bhaṭṭa (7th cent. A. D.) of the Mīmāṁsā school. According to this, the words forming a sentence, can have independent meanings also in addition to contributing to the total sense of the sentence. For instance, in the sentence &#x2018;gām ānaya,&#x2019; &#x2018;Bring the cow&#x2019;, the word &#x2018;gām&#x2019; is a noun in the accusative case and refers to a cow, an animal of the bovine class. The word &#x2018;ānaya&#x2019; is a verb in the imperative mood denoting the action of bringing. When related in a sentence thus, they give the total meaning that the person to whom they are addressed, is expected to bring the animal cow. However they do not lose their individual significance. The words when used independently continue to denote the animal cow and the act of bringing.</p>
			<p>This theory is not acceptable to Prabhākara Bhaṭṭa (a disciple of Kumā-rila), another teacher of Mīmāṁsā, forming a parallel school. According to him, words have no independent denotation and can denote something only when used in injunctive sentences (&#x2018;vidhi&#x2019;) in relation to other words. His theory is known as &#x2018;anvitābhidhāna-vāda.&#x2019;</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhijit</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;victorious&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Sins of omission and commission, when not intentional, can be atoned by certain expiatory rites known as prāyaścitta. Abhijit is one of such rites. It is actually a minor Vedic sacrifice similar in structure to the major sacrifice Soma, but requiring just a day to perform. It is specially recommended as an expiation for the sin of killing a brāhmaṇa.</p>
			<p>Abhijit is also the name of a nakṣatra (star or asterism) counted as the 28th, after uttarāṣāḍha. In mythological works, Abhijit is described as a daughter of Dakṣa-Brahmā and as a wife of Candra (the moon).</p>
			<p>The auspicious period that occurs at midnight is also called abhijit. Lord Kṛṣṇa is said to have been born at that time.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Abhimanyu</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>One of the greatest warriors of the second generation in the <em>Mahābhārata</em> and a legendary figure, Abhimanyu was the son of Arjuna and Subhadrā, and the husband of Uttarā. Trained in the martial arts by his father Arjuna and uncle Śrī Kṛṣṇa, he matured into a great warrior at an early age. During the Mahābhārata war, in the absence of Śrī Kṛṣṇa and Arjuna, Abhimanyu was obliged to break through the cakravyūha, the wheel-formation of the Kaurava army. Though he fought valiantly, he was surrounded by a multitude of Kaurava warriors and killed as he was ignorant of the technique of extricating himself out of that cakravyūha.</p>
			<p>However, before laying down his life, he fought bravely against the greatest of the warriors on the Kaurava side and displayed remarkable heroism.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>MAHĀBHĀRATA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Abhinavagupta</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>If what is known as &#x2018;Pratyabhijñā-darśana&#x2019; (Kashmir Śaivism) has attained a respectable status among the medieval philosophical systems, it is mainly due to Abhinavagupta, the encyclopaedic scholar and prolific writer of the middle ages. His ancestors hailed from the &#x2018;Antarvedī,&#x2019; the country between the Gaṅgā and the Yamunā rivers. He lived in Kashmir. His literary activities extended from about A. D. 980 to A. D. 1020. He was an authority on several subjects and at least forty works are attributed to him.</p>
			<p>His <em>Tantrasāra</em> is a voluminous treatise on Tantra. <em>Īśvara-pratyabhijñā-vimarśinī</em> is an authoritative work on the monistic Śaivism of the Pratyabhijñā school of Kashmir. Among his other works <em>Tantrāloka</em> and <em>Paramārthasāra</em> should also be mentioned.</p>
			<p>Abhinavagupta has carved out a niche for himself in the fields of poetics and dramaturgy also. His two superb commentaries, <em>Dhvanyāloka-locana</em> (also called <em>Locana</em>) and <em>Abhinavabhāratī</em> on Ānanda-vardhana&#x2019;s <em>Dhvanyāloka</em> and Bharata&#x2019;s <em>Nāṭyaśāstra</em> are considered as supreme authorities even now on those subjects.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhiniveśa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;excessive attachment [to life]&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>All living beings, starting from an insignificant worm right up to the highly evolved man, have a natural fear of death and a strong desire to live. According to the Yoga system of Patañjali, though this is understandable, it is not desirable! It is not desirable because it is born out of avidyā or ignorance of the true nature of the soul which is really immortal. This very ignorance is a great stumbling block on the path to perfection. Hence abhiniveśa which is technically termed as a kleśa, an affliction or a vicious tendency, preventing the rise of true knowledge, must be cast off by the seeker of perfection. Spiritual practices like kriyāyoga will help the seeker in this task.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>KLEŚA</ref>, <ref>KRIYĀYOGA</ref> and <ref>YOGA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Abhiplava</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The ṛṣis (men of knowledge and wisdom), who were the spiritual leaders of the Hindu society, kept before it the supreme ideal of mokṣa, liberation from the transmigratory existence. However, they never forgot that man has a constitutional inclination towards the enjoyment of pleasures got through artha (wealth) and kāma (desires of the flesh). While recognising this, they also stressed the need to confine them within limits through dharma (righteousness), and instituted the system of yajña or sacrifice through which man could achieve the desired ends. Abhiplava is one of the sacrifices included under the Soma group of sacrifices and forms part of a bigger one called Gavāmayana. It is spread over six days and includes four ukthyas (a small Soma sacrifice) and two Agniṣṭomas (another Soma sacrifice with hymns of praise on Agni, the fire-god) and the singing of some Sāma hymns.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ābhīras</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Caste has always been a dominant feature in the Hindu society. Division into groups based on vocation is a phenomenon common to all societies. But in India, such groups have often become fossilized and mutually exclusive, the membership of the group being acquired only by birth. Hence the appellation &#x2018;jāti&#x2019; (= birth). In spite of the vigorous attempts of its leaders to make the particular jāti a water-tight compartment, thanks to human nature, mixing has always taken place throughout history, giving rise to more castes, born out of the admixture of the prevalent ones. The ābhīras constitute such a mixed caste. They are regarded by Manu as the offspring of a brāhmaṇa by an aṁbaṣṭha (descended from a brāhmaṇa father and vaiśya mother) woman. Whether the ābhīras were a nomadic tribe which migrated into India by stages or were natives of this land, it is certain they lived a nomadic and predatory life. By the 2nd cent. A. D. some of them had attained high ranks and had even siezed political power, wielding it effectively till the 4th cent. A. D. Mention may be made of Ābhīra Īśvarasena, son of Śivadatta, supposed to be the founder of the Kalacuri-Cedi era (3rd cent. A. D.) who rose to the royal rank in northern Maharashtra.</p>
			<p>The common people among them lived by dairy farming. They have contributed much to the development of Indian music. The Apabhraṁśa dialect, a form of Prākṛt, is also their contribution. But their greatest contribution is towards the growth of pastoral legends centring round Śrī Kṛṣṇa. The modern āhīrs are considered to be the descendants of ābhīras and are scattered over the greater part of India.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhiṣava</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;to press out&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>This is a technical term used in Vedic liturgy to indicate the extracting of the soma juice from the soma stalks, by pressing them. There are two kinds of pressing: kṣullakābhiṣava (the little pressing) and mahābhiṣava (the great pressing). In the kṣullakābhiṣava, the Adhvaryu (one of the principal priests who does most of the ritual acts and recites the mantras from the <em>Yajurveda</em>) places a few soma stalks on one of the lower grinding stones (called upara), pours consecrated water (called nigrābhya) and beats the stalks in three turns consisting respectively of 8, 11 and 12 single beatings. The juice extracted is collected in a cup. In the mahābhiṣava, four priests sitting round the hide that holds the pressing stones (called adhiṣavaṇacarman) beat the stalks in three turns, after sprinkling them with consecrated water, using the crushing stones (called grāvan) for the operation. The whole act is a ceremonial ritual, forming part of Soma sacrifices.</p>
			<p>Abhiṣava is also the technical name given to the ceremonial bath taken before religious rites, especially sacrifices.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhiṣecanīya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;anointing rite&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The kṣattriya kings of olden days used to consider it a matter of prestige and pride to perform the Rājasūya-yāga, an elaborate and expensive ceremony of royal consecration. Abhiṣecanīya is the principal rite in the whole ceremony. The name is derived from &#x2018;abhiṣeka&#x2019; (sprinkling with holy water) which forms the most important part of the ritual. The Abhiṣecanīya rite which comes under the Soma group of sacrifices, is spread over five days, consisting of one dīkṣā (taking the vows), three upasad (a group of rites in which ghee is offered to Agni), and one sutyā (pressing of the soma stalks) days. The Dīkṣā lasts for a year. In the actual unction rite, the water drawn from various sources and places is kept in wooden vessels and sprinkled over the king by several people led by the priests including representatives of all groups.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>RĀJASŪYA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhiṣeka</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;pouring or sprinkling holy water&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>It is the unction rite in the Rājasūya sacrifice. See <ref>ABHIṢECANĪYA</ref>.</p>
			<p>The word is also used to indicate the ceremonial bath given to the duly consecrated images in temples. This part of the pūjā (ritualistic worship) is invariably accompanied by Vedic chants.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhiśravaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;to face and to cause to listen&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Performance of religious and semi- religious rites to propitiate one&#x2019;s ancestors is part and parcel of many cultures in the world. The Hindus do it through śrāddha (death anniversary rites of departed ancestors), though its forms may vary from caste to caste. Inviting and feeding the brāhmaṇas of learning and character is not only obligatory but also considered highly meritorious since the spirits of the departed souls are believed to be satisfied with it. When these brāhmaṇas are partaking of the food, the performer of the śrāddha or his representative is expected to stand respectfully in front of them (abhi) and chant certain Vedic and paurāṇic hymns prescribed as suitable for such occasions, in their hearing (śravaṇa). The idea is that this helps in creating a spiritual atmosphere soaked in which the brāhmaṇas eat the food and consequently the forefathers will feel immensely satisfied and happy.</p>
			<p>Some of the hymns recommended by the dharmaśāstras to be chanted during abhiśravaṇa are:</p>
			<p>Gāyatrī (<em>Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 3.62.10), Rakṣoghna Mantras (<em>Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 4.4.1-5), Pitrya Mantras (<em>Taittirīya Brāhmaṇa</em> 2.6.12.3), Apratiratha Mantras (<em>Taittirīya Saṁhitā</em> 4.6.4.1), <em>Puruṣasūkta</em> (<em>Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 10.90.1), <em>Śrīsūkta</em> (<em>Ṛgveda-khila</em>), <em>Pavamānasūkta</em> (<em>Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 9.1.1), Trisuparṇa Mantras (<em>Mahānārāyaṇopaniṣad</em> 38 to 40).</p>
			<p>While chanting the hymns, the sacred thread should be worn in the upavīta fashion (hanging from the left shoulder to below the right arm-pit). The chanting should be neither too loud nor too fast.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ŚRĀDDHA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhivādana</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;[causing the benediction to be] pronounced [by the elders while respectfully] facing [them]&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Honouring one&#x2019;s superiors is a basic dogma in Hindu religion and culture. As long as it was scrupulously followed, it contributed to the solidarity of the society. In the presence of a person worthy of honour, one is expected to rise from one&#x2019;s seat and salute him. The former is called pratyut-thāna and the latter abhivādana. After facing (= abhi) him, introducing himself and bowing down to him, the superior is expected to pronounce benediction (vādana). Hence the term. While offering abhivādana, it is necessary to repeat one&#x2019;s gotra (parental lineage) along with the name of the particular branch of the Veda traditionally studied in the family, and one&#x2019;s own name. During this repetition he should touch his ears and bend his head down. After this he can bow down touching or not touching the feet of the superior. In upasaṅgrahaṇa, another variety of abhivādana, clasping the feet of the superior at the time of saluting is obligatory.</p>
			<p>Elaborate details have been given in the dharmaśāstras with regard to abhi-vādana. For instance, it can be nitya (obligatory every day), naimittika (occasio-nal) or kāmya (done with certain rewards in view). Bowing down to one&#x2019;s teacher and parents everyday comes under the first category. Saluting the elders on special occasions like after returning from a journey, belongs to the second. If done at one&#x2019;s own will, seeking knowledge or long life or bliss in heaven it is classed under the third. Detailed rules have also been given as to whom abhivādana can be offered or should not be offered, the rules being based on caste, learning, status in society and age. It is noteworthy that salutation to women, except to one&#x2019;s mother, should be offered without touching their feet.</p>
			<p>The persons to whom abhivādana is offered should return it in a manner proper to their position and status.</p>
			<p>For details, see <ref>PRATYABHIVĀDA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhyaṅga</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>AVYAṄGA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhyāsa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;repetition&#x2019;, &#x2018;practice&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>&#x2018;Practice makes perfect&#x2019; as the saying goes. Practice is nothing but repetition of effort to achieve perfection. The word is used in a technical sense in the Yoga system of Patañjali. Repetition of effort put forth to keep the modifications of mind, called vṛttis, suppressed, is called abhyāsa. This abhyāsa when kept up over a long period, but in unbroken continuity, and with devoted faith, will become firmly established leading to yogic states (<em>vide Yogasūtras</em> 1.12, 13, 14).</p>
			<p>In Sanskrit grammar, the word is used to indicate the first part of the duplicated verbal root (<em>vide Aṣṭādhyāyī</em> of Pāṇini 6.1.4).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhyāsayoga</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;practice leading to yoga&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Controlling the vagaries of the mind and concentrating it on a chosen object or theme is a formidable task. Only those who have attempted it can vouch for its near impossibility. However, the great teachers of yoga assure us that it is not impossible, though difficult. With the right attitude and determined practice, this becomes possible. The path prescribed is abhyāsayoga. This term which seems to be the creation of the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> (8.8 and 12.9), a highly venerated scripture of Hinduism, has been interpreted in two slightly different but compatible ways:</p>
			<ul class="lower-alpha">
				<li>abhyāsa or practice leading to yoga or concentration;</li>
				<li>abhyāsa or practice which is itself yoga since it leads to yoga or concentration. Withdrawing the mind repeatedly from the various objects towards which it is naturally drawn and fixing it upon the desired goal is abhyāsa. When this fixing becomes steady and grows in intensity, it ripens into yoga or perfect concentration, also called samādhi. Hence abhyāsa and yoga form the preliminary and final stages of the same discipline. Retiring into solitude, choosing the right place conducive to yoga, observing moderation in all aspects of daily life, practising self-control—these are some of the disciplines recommended by the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> for abhyāsayoga (<em>vide</em> 6.10-28).</li>
			</ul>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>abhyudaya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;prosperity&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The Hindu scriptures, especially the dharmaśāstras, have always emphasised that a householder must strive for abhyu-daya (worldly prosperity) but not forgetting that niśśreyasa (mokṣa or liberation) is the ultimate goal of life. For a man of the world, it is certainly not wrong to entertain modest ambitions with regard to wealth, power, progeny or fame, to keep himself and his family happy and contented. On the other hand, he will be failing in his duty if he neglects his family and makes his dependents suffer. However, it is equally emphasised that while striving for abhyudaya, he should never forsake dharma (righteousness).</p>
			<p>See also <ref>NIŚŚREYASA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ābhyudayika-śrāddha</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;śrāddha for the sake of abhyudaya&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Belief in the continued existence of the forefathers (pitṛs) in a subtle body at a different plane (pitṛloka or the world of manes) is a common feature of mankind in general and the Hindus in particular. It is often believed that these forefathers when propitiated through appropriate rites can bestow on their descendants worldly prosperity, nay, even spiritual benefits. The propitiating rite is called śrāddha, since it is offered with śraddhā (faith). Of the several śrāddhas, ābhyudayika-śrāddha is particularly connected with abhyudaya (worldly well-being) and is performed on auspicious occasions like the birth of children, their marriage and so on. It can even be performed at the commencement of a charitable act such as the dedication of a well or tank or park to the public.</p>
			<p>Unlike the other śrāddhas which are solemn, this śrāddha is a joyous occasion. Hence certain changes have been effected in its performance. For instance: It is done in the morning and not in the afternoon. The yajñopavīta (sacred cord) is worn in the usual way and not from right to left. The mantra &#x2018;svadhā,&#x2019; which is a must in other śrāddhas is not used. Yava grains (barley) are used as the oblatory material instead of sesamum.</p>
			<p>This śrāddha is sometimes identified with Nāndīśrāddha or Vṛddhiśrāddha.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ŚRĀDDHA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Abu, Mt.</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Any spot of serenity and natural beauty can be made into either a place of picnic or pilgrimage. The choice depends upon the temperament. To the Hindu mind such spots reflect God&#x2019;s beauty and offer a congenial atmosphere for contemplation upon Him. One of such spots that nature has been bountiful in bestowing upon India is Mount Abu situated in southern Rajasthan and at a distance of 170 kms., (110 miles) from city of Ahmedabad. It is part of the Arāvalī range of mountains. The summit called Guruśikhara rises to a height of 1700 metres (5610 ft.) above the mean sea level. Referred to as Arbuda in the <em>Mahābhārata</em>, it is extolled as a tīrthakṣetra (a place of pilgrimage) on account of its association with the great sage Vasiṣṭha whose āśrama or hermitage was situated here. This is also supposed to be the place of origin of the Agnikula-kṣattriyas of Rajasthan like the Cauvhāns, Solaṅkis and Parmārs. Among the Hindu religious sites, the chief one is the Guru-śikhara itself, containing in a cavern the &#x2018;footprints&#x2019; of an ancient sage. The Acaleśvara temple campus has a cleft in the rock containing &#x2018;Śiva&#x2019;s toenail.&#x2019; The same campus contains a shrine for Arbuda Mātā, the consort of Śiva and the Mother-goddess of the hill. There are also shrines for the sages Vasiṣṭha and Gautama at Gomukha. The temples at Devāṅgaṇa are dedicated to Viṣṇu and Narasiṁha. Mount Abu is also famous for its Jain temples built in marble by the merchant prince Vimalśā (A. D. 1032) and the brothers Tejpāl and Vastupāl (A. D. 1197—1247). These temples are dedicated to Ṛṣabha-deva and Pārśvanātha, the 1st and the 23rd Tīrthaṅkaras.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>acalaliṅga</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the immovable liṅga&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Śiva, the third deity of the Hindu Trinity responsible for the dissolution of this universe is worshipped both in the anthropomorphic aspect and as the liṅga. The latter however is the rule, the former being an exception. Etymologically the word &#x2018;liṅga&#x2019; stands for that in which everything gets dissolved (<em>līyate asmin iti liṅgaḥ</em>). Liṅga also means an emblem. Hence the Śivaliṅga is an emblem of God Śiva into whom everything gets dissolved at the time of destruction of the created universe. Since God is beyond name and form and since we cannot conceive of an abstract principle like Him without the aid of concrete symbols, a rounded surface is perhaps the nearest approach to him.</p>
			<p>Śivaliṅgas may be cala (movable) or acala (immovable). The acala-liṅgas, also called sthāvara-liṅgas, are the stone liṅgas permanently fixed in the temples. There are several varieties of them classified under four or six or even nine groups. An acalaliṅga has three parts: Brahmabhāga (square in shape), Viṣṇubhāga (octagonal) and Rudrabhāga (round). The first two parts are embedded inside the pedestal, the third part alone being visible. This is the one to which pūjā or worship is offered. Hence it is called the &#x2018;pūjābhāga.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>See also <ref>CALALIṄGA</ref>, <ref>LIṄGA</ref>, and <ref>ŚIVALIṄGA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ācamana</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;[ceremonial] sipping [of water in rituals]&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Rituals are an important aspect of every religion. If philosophy explains the basic truths and mythology expounds the same through stories and analogies, rituals give them a concrete shape and lay down the practical disciplines to be followed which will ultimately lead to the realization of those truths. In Hinduism such rituals are legion. In fact, even the basic acts of our daily routine like cleaning the teeth or bathing have been elevated to the level of a religious ritual. The idea is that our whole life is a yajña (sacrifice) or sādhanā (spiritual practice).</p>
			<p>Practically all the rituals have to be preceded by ācamana or ceremonial sipping of water. A few drops of water, as much as can immerse a grain of blackgram, are taken in the palm of the right hand cupped like a cow&#x2019;s ear (gokarṇa) and sipped from the root of the thumb (called brahmatīrtha). After sipping three times, various parts of the body like the eyes, ears, nose, chest and head are touched with the wet hand in a specified order. Ācamana should always be done in the sitting posture.</p>
			<p>The process of ācamana is believed to cover the prāṇa (basic life-energy, considered as a deity) so that it protects the performer. Even the ancient Upaniṣads like the <em>Bṛhadāraṇyaka</em> (4.1.14) and the <em>Chāndogya</em> (5.2.2) seem to subscribe to this view.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>RITUALS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ācāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;conduct&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The smṛtis and dharmaśāstras, the law books that regulate the life of individuals, both at the personal and at the social level, usually deal with three important topics: ācāra (ceremonial duties), vyavahāra (civil and criminal laws) and prāyaścitta (penances and expi-atory rites). Of the three, ācāra usually gets the pride of place. Literally, ācāra means conduct. It is often identified with sadācāra, the conduct of good and great men, so much so that dharma (righteousness) itself is said to be born out of ācāra, &#x2018;ācāraprabhavo dharmaḥ&#x2019; (<em>Mahābhārata, Anuśāsanaparva</em> 161.172). Whenever one is in doubt with regard to one&#x2019;s duty or action in a particular situation in life, one is advised to seek the guidance of the wise elders of impeccable character. Their words should be implicitly obeyed.</p>
			<p>The ṣaṭkarmas, the six duties included under daily routine, are the most important aspects of ācāra at the personal level. They are: snāna (bath), sandhyā (the sandhyā ritual), japa (repetition of mantra), devapūjā (ritualistic worship of the family deity), homa (sacrifice), Vaiśvadeva (offerings of cooked food to all the gods) and ātithya (honouring the guests). Undergoing the various saṁskāras (purificatory rites) and performing the prescribed duties as per one&#x2019;s varṇa (caste) and āśrama (stage of life) are the other important aspects of ācāra.</p>
			<p>The word ācāra is also used in the sense of &#x2018;customs and tradition&#x2019; which is equally important. No doubt the Vedas are the supreme authority in all matters regulating the Hindu society. Since they do not deal with the details of various problems that arise in the day-to-day life and conduct of the individuals, one has to rely upon the smṛtis (recorded collections of great sages) and sadācāra (the conduct of great men). However, in matters of dispute, falling within the jurisdiction of jurisprudence, ācāra as custom and long-standing tradition or usage, is often the decisive factor, provided it is not against the spirit of the Vedas and smṛtis. Such ācāra can be deśācāra (pertaining to the particular region), jātyācāra (pertaining to the particular caste) or kulācāra (pertaining to the particular family). Even the judges or the king had to take cognizance of these ācāras before giving their verdict.</p>
			<p>See <ref>SMṚTIS</ref> and <ref>DHARMAŚĀSTRAS</ref> also.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ācāraliṅga</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the practical liṅga)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>ṢAṬSTHALA-SIDDHĀNTA</ref> and <ref>VĪRA-ŚAIVISM</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ācārya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;preceptor&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>In ancient India, education, the panacea for all maladies and problems of life, was imparted more by personal contact than by lectures and discourses. The student learnt more by observing the teacher&#x2019;s life than by hearing his teachings. Hence the teacher had to &#x2018;be&#x2019; that, which he wanted to &#x2018;make&#x2019; of his student. First &#x2018;be&#x2019; and then &#x2018;make.&#x2019; It is this philosophy of education that is reflected in this word &#x2018;ācārya.&#x2019; It is only he who successfully gathers (ācinoti) the essentials of dharma and wisdom from all sources and practises them (ācarati) in his own life, that deserves the appellation &#x2018;ācārya.&#x2019; In a more technical sense, the ācārya is one who performs the upanayana ceremony of the novice and imparts the Vedas to him, along with the accessories known as the Vedāṅgas.</p>
			<p>Great stress was laid on the quali-fications which the ācārya had to possess. Birth in a family known for its erudition and piety was always recognised as highly desirable. Deep erudition in the branch of the Veda he was required to teach was expected as a matter of course. A pure and sinless life, serenity and composure, active interest in imparting knowledge were the other qualifications looked for in the ācārya.</p>
			<p>The word is also frequently used as an honorific to men of great erudition and learning, especially if they are the initiators of new schools of thought or the revivers of old ones, like Śaṅkara, Rāmānuja, Madhva and others.</p>
			<p>The term is also applied to an adviser or preceptor guiding sacrificial rites.</p>
			<p>The wife of an ācārya is called &#x2018;ācāryāṇī&#x2019; whereas a woman preceptor is designated &#x2018;ācāryā.&#x2019; From this we can infer the existence of women preceptors also.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>acicchakti</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;non-sentient power [of Brahman]&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>If the solid world we perceive with our senses is a wonderful phenomenon, the unseen Power behind it is a deep mystery. The quest for the mode by which this unseen Power has evolved into this tangible world has resulted in several philosophical schools, often called &#x2018;darśanas,&#x2019; in the text-books of Hindu metaphysics. Of these, the Vedānta Darśana of Bādarāyaṇa has attracted the maximum number of commentators one of whom is Nimbārka (11th-12th cent. A. D.). According to him, Brahman, the highest Reality, is a personal God, identified with Kṛṣṇa or Hari. Brahman has two powers cit-śakti (sentient power, i.e., the indi- vidual souls) and acit-śakti (non-sentient power, i.e., nature). At the beginning of creation, He manifests these two powers. From acit-śakti or acicchakti, there is a gradual evolution of the entire material world.</p>
			<p>This acicchakti manifests itself in three different forms:</p> 
			<ol>
				<li>the prākṛta or what is derived from the prakṛti, primal matter, responsible for the material world;</li>
				<li>the aprākṛta, the non-material aspect, the stuff of the celestial bodies and objects as also the regions where the Lord and the freed souls live;</li>
				<li>kāla or time.</li>
			</ol>
			<p>See also <ref>NIMBĀRKA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Acintya-bhedābheda School</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>There have always been two major but parallel currents of thought—advocating jñāna (knowledge) and bhakti (devotion)—in the Hindu religious tradition, each getting the better of the other at certain periods of history. The school of jñāna or knowledge, based on the Upaniṣads and allied literature like the darśanas has always stressed that mukti (liberation from transmigratory existence) is possible only through ātmajñāna or knowledge of the Self. The school of bhakti or devotion, rooted in the <em>Ṛgveda</em>, but dependent mainly on the epics and the purāṇas (mythological lore) has emphasized that such liberation is possible only through the grace of God, bhakti or devotion to God being the only means of obtaining it. Each of these two schools, being unable to ignore the logical and psychological force of the other, has been obliged to find a place for some of the principles of the rival school though relegating them to an inferior status. More sober thinkers have attempted at reconciling, even harmonising, these two viewpoints with varying success. The best of such attempts which has succeeded remarkably is found in that classic scripture <em>Śrīmad Bhāgavatam,</em> which itself is based on an earlier work of a similar kind, <em>Śrī Viṣṇupurāṇa</em>. The philosophical schools of bhakti, based on these two and allied works (e.g., <em>Harivaṁśa</em> and <em>Brahmavaivartapurāṇa</em>) could not disregard the Upaniṣads or the <em>Brahmasūtras</em> (also called <em>Vedāntasūtras,</em> a work systematising the philosophical ref- lections scattered all over the Upaniṣads) which had attained a very high status among thinkers and religious leaders. Hence they ventured to interpret the <em>Brahmasūtras</em> and the Upaniṣads by superimposing their views—commonly known as the Bhāgavata school—on them. Though it is difficult to assess the degree of their success, there is no doubt that they have enriched the Hindu philosophical tradition. Among such Bhāgavata schools, those of Nimbārka (11th-12th cent. A.D.), Vallabha and Śrīkṛṣṇa Caitanya or Caitanya (both of the 15th cent. A. D.) have gained recognition and respectability. The religio-philosophical system propounded by Caitanya (A. D. 1485-1533), Jīva Gosvāmī (16th cent. A. D.) and other scholar-mystics of Bengal is known as the Bengal School of Vaiṣṇavism, also designated as the &#x2018;Acintya-bhedābheda&#x2019; school. This designation obtains from the fact that the relationship between Brahman (God) on the one hand and prakṛti (nature) and jīva (individual soul) on the other, is &#x2018;acintya&#x2019; (incomprehensible) since both &#x2018;bheda&#x2019; (difference) and &#x2018;abheda&#x2019; (non- difference) can be predicated of it.</p>
			<p>The teachings of this school can be summarised briefly as follows: The ultimate Reality is personal, (Brahman or) Śrī Kṛṣṇa, the God of love and grace. He is the same as the Brahman of the Upaniṣads. He is sat-cit-ānanda (existence-consciousness-bliss-absolute). He is infinite, omnipotent and omnipresent. He is the very embodiment of all blessed qualities that we can ever conceive of. In this sense, he is saguṇa (with attributes).</p>
			<p>He has three śaktis or powers: svarūpaśakti, māyā-śakti and jīva-śakti. By his svarūpa-śakti (also called cit-śakti) he upholds his own existence and that of others, knows and makes others know, enjoys and makes others enjoy bliss. These three characteristics of his svarūpa-śakti corresponding to sat, cit and ānanda aspects of his, are called sandhinī, saṁvit and hlādinī śaktis respectively.</p>
			<p>His māyāśakti (also called acit-śakti or jaḍa-śakti), has two aspects: guṇamāyā comprising the three guṇas of sattva, rajas and tamas; jīvamāyā, which makes the jīvas (individual souls) forget their true nature and hence get into the bondage of transmigration. God creates the universe by activating this māyāśakti. The created universe is real but transitory.</p>
			<p>All the living beings form his jīva-śakti (also called taṭasthaśakti).</p>
			<p>Creation proceeds out of him by the exercise of māyāśakti and jīvaśakti. Māyā-śakti evolves into the material universe and jīvaśakti involves the jīvas in it. The purpose of creation is to give more opportunities for the jīvas to get mukti by striving for it and by working out their karma.</p>
			<p>God who is the very personification of love and joy, assumes infinite forms including the avatāras or incarnations in this world. Of these, Śrī Kṛṣṇa is the chief. His supreme delight is in love, manifested through the Vṛndāvana-līlā. Rādhā, the doyen of the gopīs and the eternal divine consort of Kṛṣṇa is actually the personification of his hlādinīśakti.</p>
			<p>The jīvas who are infinite in number and different from God, are conscious entities atomic in size. They get into the bondage of saṁsāra (transmigration) due to the ignorance of their real nature, brought about by māyā. Mukti is gained by breaking the bondage of karma through bhakti or devotion to Śrī Kṛṣṇa. This bhakti can be like that of the servant towards his master (dāsya-bhakti), that of the friend towards his friend (sakhya-bhakti), that of the parents towards their child (vātsalya-bhakti) or that of the beloved towards the lover (kāntā-bhakti or madhura-bhakti).</p>
			<p>For practising the spiritual disciplines leading to bhakti, guidance from a competent guru (spiritual preceptor) is essential. Logic and reasoning are not to be trusted in the path of religion since they can undermine faith. Ethical virtues like compassion, tranquillity and equani-mity, humility and freedom from passions should be cultivated. Since all devotees are children of God, caste distinctions should be ignored.</p>
			<p>When bhakti matures into an abso-lutely pure and selfless state—called kevalā or śuddhā—the devotee aims exclusively at the loving service of Kṛṣṇa as the nearest and dearest one, for his happiness only and does not care even for mukti. This is posited as the fifth puruṣārtha. (See <ref>PURUṢĀRTHAS</ref>.)</p>
			<p>Though four kinds of mukti (See <ref>MOKṢA</ref>) like sālokya are recognised, the śuddha-bhakta is not interested in them.</p>
			<p>All this applies to the jīvas who are bound (baddha). There is another class of jīvas known as nityamuktas (ever-free), who have never been in bondage.</p>
			<p>The word &#x2018;acintya-bhedābheda&#x2019; itself needs some explanation. Hindu philosophers are broadly divided into two groups, one holding the view that in the ultimate analysis there is no difference (abheda) between Brahman and the jīva; and the other accepting difference (bheda). The Bengal school of Vaiṣṇavism differs from both and calls itself &#x2018;acintya-bhedābheda- vāda,&#x2019; since Brahman and jīva are identical (abhinna) in some respects and different (bhinna) in others, the very relationship being beyond our comprehension (acintya). Both being cit (consciousness) are identical in that respect. But Brahman is vibhu-cit (all-pervading consciousness) whereas the jīva is aṇu-cit (atomic consciousness). Again, the jīva is an aṁśa (part) of Brahman who is the aṁśin (the whole). Since the relation between the part and the whole is one of simultaneous bheda and abheda, the same subsists between Brahman and jīva also. How exactly this can be, is beyond human comprehension. Hence the appellation.</p>
			<p>On the side of dogma, this school accords Śrī Caitanya the same status as God since it believes that he is the combined incarnation of Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa.</p>
			<p>At the social level, the leaders of this school have contributed significantly by removing caste distinctions and encouraging the cultivation of primary moral and social values.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ŚRĪ KṚṢṆA CAITANYA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>acit</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the insentient&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Man is a &#x2018;thinking animal.&#x2019; Once his animal needs are satisfied and he obtains relative peace and stability in life, he starts thinking about the &#x2018;how,&#x2019; the &#x2018;why&#x2019; and the &#x2018;when&#x2019; of things perceived. This thinking about the origin and evolution of things has got to be in the form of conjectures and hypotheses before being advanced as theories. Such conjectures and hypotheses again, can start only from the seen and the known before progressing towards the unseen and the unknown. It is but natural that this world in which man lives, moves and has his being (as it were), is the first to catch his attention. Such attention and thinking often leads to a broad categorisation of the created world. Of such categorisations, what can be more simple, direct and obvious than the twofold one, viz., the living and the non-living, the sentient and the non- sentient? This is exactly what the Viśiṣṭādvaita Vedānta system—of which Rāmānuja (A. D. 1017-1137) is the chief exponent—has done.</p>
			<p>According to this system, the ultimate Reality is threefold: cit (the sentient), acit (the insentient) and Īśvara (God). The former two are dependent realities, subservient to the latter. (For details see <ref>VIŚIṢṬĀDVAITA VEDĀNTA DARŚANA</ref>.)</p>
			<p>The acit principle, as its very name indicates, is the matrix of all that is without life and consciousness. Also called prakṛti (nature), it is jaḍa (lifeless and insentient) but capable of vikāra (modi- fication or evolution). It is avidyā (ignorance) since it is opposed to true knowledge and also called māyā since it is the cause of all diverse creations. Being insentient it is incapable of evolving by itself but does so under the controlling will of God.</p>
			<p>According to one classification this acit has three aspects: the śuddha-sattva, the miśra-sattva and sattva-śūnya. The śuddha-sattva aspect has pure sattva guṇa (See <ref>GUṆAS</ref>.) capable of producing knowledge and bliss, and is the matrix out of which the world Vaikuṇṭha (See <ref>VAIKUṆṬHA</ref>.) has been made. It is un- affected by the karma of the individual souls and is directly under the control of God. The miśra-sattva aspect has the three guṇas of sattva, rajas and tamas. It is this which evolves as this world, contracts and obstructs the jñāna (knowledge) of the jīvas (individual selves) and sustains their bondage by producing viparīta-jñāna (knowledge opposed to their real nature). Kāla or time forms the third aspect viz., sattva-śūnya.</p>
			<p>Whether kāla should be deemed as an aspect of acit or considered as a special power inhering in God has been a point of debate among the thinkers of the Viśiṣṭādvaita school.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Acyuta Prekṣa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>It is often seen that some persons become known to history because of their association with the more brilliant one who makes history. Whether the former, though deserving better recognition, are overshadowed by the latter, or, become known only because of their association with the latter who are head and shoulders above them, is a matter of opinion. Acyuta Prekṣa, who gave saṁnyāsa to Madhvācārya belongs to this group. Not much is known of him. As per the scanty information available in the work <em>Maṇimañjarī</em> of Nārāyaṇācārya (14th cent. A.D.), he was the head of the &#x2018;Bhaṇḍāra-keri Maṭha.&#x2019; His preceptor belonged to &#x2018;Ānanda-bāla Maṭha&#x2019; and hailed from Nandigrāma. Since there are several Nandigrāmas in the country, it is difficult to decide which one it was. Acyuta Prekṣa was an advaitin and belonged to the Bhāgavata school. It was he who administered the monastic vows and gave the new names Pūrṇa- prajña, Ānandatīrtha and others to Madhvācārya. He had to accept defeat from his own disciple while teaching him. In course of time, he was himself converted into a dvaitin.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>MADHVĀCĀRYA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Adbhuta Brāhmaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Each of the four Vedas, the basic scriptures of the Hindus, is divided broadly into two sections: the Mantra and the Brāhmaṇa. The Mantra section contains prayers and hymns. The Brāhmaṇa section deals with the application of these mantras in rituals.</p>
			<p>The <em>Adbhuta Brāhmaṇa</em> forms the sixth (and the last) chapter of a bigger work called <em>Ṣaḍviṁśa Brāhmaṇa</em> which itself is the second of the nine Brāhmaṇas of the <em>Sāmaveda</em>, available to us now. Though the first five chapters of the <em>Ṣaḍviṁśa Brāhmaṇa</em> deal with the ceremonies and rituals connected with the Somayāgas, the sixth one makes a comp-lete departure and deals with strange phenomena like ill-omens and the expiatory rites that help offset their effects. It is perhaps due to this reason that this particular section is thus designated (adbhuta wonderful, strange).</p>
			<p>There are indications to prove that the <em>Ṣaḍviṁśa Brāhmaṇa</em> originally consisted of only five chapters and the sixth i.e., the <em>Adbhuta Brāhmaṇa</em> was appended to it later.</p>
			<p>The entire book deals with adbhuta-śāntis or appeasement of portents, and is divided into twelve khaṇḍas or sections. The various portents indicating imminent dangers are described as being connected with the gods like Indra, Yama, Varuṇa and Viṣṇu; and appropriate śāntis (rites of appeasement of the deities) are also given. The idea seems to be that when these gods are displeased, troubles start and when appeased through appropriate rites, they cease.</p>
			<p>The list of portents given is quite long but interesting. Starting from the breaking or damage of household articles for apparently no reason, right up to natural calamities like earthquakes, destruction of crops and the fall of meteors, the list mentions the happening of many unnatural and improbable phenomena also. Among such, it is curious to note that temples shake and the idols of gods laugh, weep, sing, dance or close their eyes! This is a clear indication that temples with idols installed, had already come into being by the time of this Brāhmaṇa.</p>
			<p>The śānti rites are usually sacrificial oblations with suitable mantras addressed to the deity that has been displeased.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ṢAḌVIṀŚA BRĀHMAṆA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Adbhuta Rāmāyaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>One of the two great epics of India, the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> of Vālmīki, has been the basic text for the story of Rāma. It has been the primary source of inspiration over the millennia, for many a poet who has retold the story in his own way, often adopting it to the philosophy of his life. One such work is the <em>Adbhuta Rāmāyaṇa</em> (&#x2018;the Wonder that is Rāmāyaṇa&#x2019;). Though attributed to Vālmīki, it is obviously a late work. Scholars are divided about its being earlier or later to another, more well-known work, the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> (A. D. 1400). The glorification of Kālī and identifying her with Sītā induce us to think that the work must have been written at a time when reconciling the Rāma cult of the Vaiṣṇavas and the Śākta cults had become a social necessity. Also, the words in the colophon as seen from a printed text—&#x2018;iti ārṣe śrīmad-rāmāyaṇe vālmīkīye ādikāvye adbhutottarakāṇḍe...&#x2019;—give rise to the suspicion that the writer might have attemp-ted to pass it off as an appendix to the <em>Uttarakāṇḍa</em> of Vālmīki&#x2019;s <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em>.</p>
			<p>The <em>Adbhuta Ramayaṇa</em> is a compa-ratively smaller work of 1355 verses spread over 27 sargas or chapters. Unlike the other Rāmāyaṇas it is not divided into kāṇḍas or books.</p>
			<p>The contents of the work may be summarized briefly as follows: The sage Bhāradvāja approaches the great sage Vālmīki and requests him to give the secret teaching that is hidden in his original <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> which is rather voluminous. Vālmīki replies that the real secret is that Rāma is the Highest Brahman and Sītā, the Highest Prakṛti, the power of Brahman. Then he goes on to narrate the reasons for the descent of Rāma (sargas 2 to 4) and Sītā (s. 5 to 7), which were apparently due to the curses of the sages Nārada and Parvata, but really to destroy the wicked and protect the good. This is followed by the story of the birth of Sītā as the daughter of Rāvaṇa, but abandoned by his wife Maṇḍodarī, and found by Janaka, the king of Mithilā, in his field. After this, the events move at a terrific speed: Rāma&#x2019;s marriage, Paraśurāma&#x2019;s humiliation at the hands of Rāma (s. 9), Rāma&#x2019;s entering the forest along with Sītā and Lakṣmaṇa (The entire episode of the <em>Ayodhyākāṇḍa</em> of Vālmīki&#x2019;s <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> leading to Rāma&#x2019;s banishment is glossed over here!), Sītā&#x2019;s abduction by Rāvaṇa and Rāma striking friendship with Sugrīva and Hanumān (s.10). In answer to the simple question that Hanumān asks, &#x2018;Who are you?&#x2019; (s.10) Rāma waxes eloquently to describe himself as the Ātman, Parameśvara, Māyāvī and Antaryāmin (s. 11 and 12). Most of the ideas and even the words are reminiscent of the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em>, and some of the Upaniṣads. This is followed by a short discourse on bhakti or devotion (s. 13) and a curious mixture of a variety of philosophical and mythological topics (s. 14). The next chapter contains a beautiful hymn of Hanumān on Rāma (s. 15). The sixteenth sarga disposes off very briefly (in 20 verses) the entire story of the <em>Yuddhakāṇḍa</em>. In the seventeenth, Sītā reveals the existence of a thousand-headed Rāvaṇa, the elder brother of the ten-headed demon, and describes him as she had heard from a brāhmaṇa in her younger days. Hearing this, Rāma starts on an invasion of the Puṣkara Dvīpa, the abode of the thousand-headed monster, in order to destroy him. In the terrific war that ensues, Rāma falls down unconscious (s. 18 to 22). Seeing this tragedy that had overtaken Rāma and his forces, Sītā assumes the terrible form of Kālī and destroys the demon along with all his forces. She is helped in this by her innumerable emanations (s. 23). Rāma wakes up and is surprised to see Kālī there (s. 24). He praises her with a long hymn containing 1008 names (s. 25). Though called <em>Sītā-sahasranāma</em> (&#x2018;thousand names of Sītā&#x2019;) almost all the names belong to the Śakti cult. Sītā dissolves the form of Kālī and reappears in her original form. After thus gaining victory, Rāma returns to Ayodhyā and resumes his rule (s. 26 and 27).</p>
			<p>Though this work might have served a specific purpose during the days of its composition and later, it fails to come up to the level of the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> and the <em>Ānanda Rāmāyaṇa</em>.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ADHYĀTMA RĀMĀYAṆA</ref>, <ref>ĀNANDA RĀMĀYAṆA</ref> and <ref>RĀMĀYAṆA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhāna</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;placing&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>AGNYĀDHĀNA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;support&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>One of the questions discussed frequently in Hindu metaphysical works is the relationship between God, the creator and the created world. Most of them subscribe to the view that God creates the world, sustains and supports it and dissolves it at the end of a cycle of creation. The created world cannot exist unless it is supported and sustained by him. He is thus the ādhāra (the ground and the support) and the world itself is ādheya (&#x2018;that which is supported&#x2019;). The relationship that subsists between them is called &#x2018;ādhara-ādheya-bhāva.&#x2019; The relationship that exists between the ground and a jar kept on it gives us some idea of this &#x2018;ādhāra-ādheya-bhāva.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>In the works on yoga, the word is used to indicate certain centres in the body like the navel, the heart or the middle of the eyebrows which act as supports for meditation or prāṇa (life-force).</p>
			<p>In Sanskrit grammar the word is used to indicate the sense of the locative case.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhāracakra</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>(&#x2018;supporting psychic centre&#x2019;)</p>
			<p>See <ref>CAKRAS</ref> and <ref>MŪLĀDHĀRA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhāraśilā</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;support-stone&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Belief in God and putting up structures to worship him or to pray to him seems to be a common trait of human beings irrespective of their geographical boundaries or differences of culture. There are evidences to show that the Hindu places of worship, called devālayas (temples, houses of God), have been existing since very ancient times. These devālayas are highly symbolic and attempt at unravelling this symbology, in concrete terms, have resulted in a regular science and art of temple construction. Apart from the usual foundation laid to support the superstructure of the temple, these works on temple construction insist on the laying of the ādhāraśilā or support-stone below the floor of the garbhagṛha (<em>sanctum sanctorum</em>).</p>
			<p>In the middle of the site for the garbhagṛha, where the idol will be installed, the ground is excavated to a pre-determined depth. A number of articles are ceremonially fixed therein, one after another, with appropriate mantras. (See <ref>ṢAḌĀDHĀRA-PRATIṢṬHĀ</ref>.) Of these, the ādhāraśilā is the first to be fixed, and at the lowest level, as the base or support. It is a square block of granite or any other hard stone, of specific dimensions. On it are placed the other articles like the pot called nidhikumbha and the lotuses of stone and metal.</p>
			<p>According to one of the interpretations of temple symbolism, the temple represents the body of the yogi (the spiritual aspirant practising yoga) with all the cakras (centres of psychic power). The ādhāra-śilā, then, stands for the mūlādhāra-cakra (the lowest centre).</p>
			<p>See also <ref>CAKRAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adharma</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;unrighteousness&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Among the pairs of words used often by the Hindu scriptures, the pair &#x2018;dharma-adharma&#x2019; is perhaps the most recurrent. Since the etymological definition of &#x2018;dharma&#x2019; is &#x2018;that which supports and sustains,&#x2019; all that attempts to destroy or oppose or reverse this process of supporting and sustaining comes within the purview of the word &#x2018;adharma.&#x2019; If dharma is the straight path that leads to abhyu-daya (well-being and prosperity) and niśśreyasa (spiritual perfection), adharma is the crooked path that leads away from both. If dharma indicates actions and duties, ritualistic or otherwise, which are in conformity with the teachings of the śāstras (holy scriptures) and ācāryas (spiritual and religious leaders), and not antagonistic to sampradāya (customs and traditions), adharma stands for all errors of omission and commission.</p>
			<p>In practice however, the word is more frequently used in the sense of unrighteous deeds and conduct resulting in sin. For instance, telling lies, stealing, cheating, adultery and committing such other forbidden acts and crimes are adharma. Dereliction of duties and not discharging the responsibilities one is entrusted with, are adharma. Performing such acts as are not prescribed for one—for e.g., a brāhmaṇa taking to arms or agriculture even though there is no urgency or emergency—is also considered adharma.</p>
			<p>The personified adharma, in the mythological lore, is said to have hiṁsā (violence) as his wife, anṛta (falsehood) as his son, and nikṛti (deceit) as his daughter. Māyā (delusion), bhaya (fear), vedanā (torment), naraka (hell), duḥkha (sorrow) and mṛtyu (death) are the other offsprings coming in that lineage (<em>vide Viṣṇupurāṇa</em> 1.7). Though the details of such lists may vary, the purport is clear: adharma is at the root of all our fears, troubles and sufferings.</p>
			<p>In Jaina metaphysics, adharma is considered to be a dravya (substance) responsible for restful state and immobility of things.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>DHARMA</ref> and <ref>PĀPA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhi</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;illness of the mind&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The ancient Hindu sages have recognised that the body and the mind form one unit and that this unit is of fundamental importance in achieving anything worthwhile in life. Hence each should be kept in a healthy condition and in harmony with the other. Vyādhi (illness of the body) and ādhi (illness of the mind) are both considered to be serious obstacles in the path of progress, whether temporal or spiritual.</p>
			<p>In most general terms, anything that disturbs the equilibrium of the body is a vyādhi and anything that upsets the equi- poise of the mind is an ādhi. The ariṣaḍ- vargas or six enemies viz., lust, anger, greed, delusion, pride and envy, as also worries and anxieties are examples of ādhi. Rāga (attachment) and dveṣa (aversion) are the root causes of all ādhis. Conquest of these will help in removing the ādhis.</p>
			<p>In the dharmaśāstras, the word is used in the sense of a pledge, deposit or article of mortgage.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhibhautika</word>
			<alias>ādhidaivika</alias>
			<alias>ādhyātmika</alias>
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The three words respectively mean: pertaining to</p>
			<ul class="lower-alpha">
				<li>the bhūta or living beings;</li>
				<li>the daiva or fate, unseen forces and gods;</li>
				<li>the ātma or the body (and the mind).</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Sorrow and suffering (duḥkha, tāpa) are inevitable in life. In fact, they are a part of life. A knowledge of their origin, causes and even categorisation helps one to minimise their effect if not eradicate them. The Hindu religious works usually call them &#x2018;tāpatraya,&#x2019; &#x2018;the three miseries.&#x2019; They are: ādhyātmika, ādhidaivika and ādhibhautika.</p>
			<p>The ādhyātmika duḥkha or tāpa is that which is caused by bodily suffering and mental anguish. Hereditary diseases like leprosy, disabilities like blindness or lameness and diseases caused by the violation of the rules of health and sanitation are classed under this. The mental agony caused by worries and anxieties, attachment and aversion, also comes under this group.</p>
			<p>The ādhidaivika duḥka or tāpa is that which is caused by daiva. The word daiva includes the power of time, nature and the unseen hand or fate. Diseases caused by the changing seasons, misery caused by the elemental forces like floods and fire, suffering caused by black magic or disembodied spirits or gods who are displeased, natural tribulations due to hunger, thirst and old-age belong to this group.</p>
			<p>The ādhibhautika duḥkha or tāpa is that which is caused by other bhūtas or living beings, like wild animals, snakes, or enemies.</p>
			<p>Some of these, like hereditary diseases or physical disabilities cannot be got rid of. Hence they must be endured. Some like the diseases caused by change of seasons or the machinations of enemies can be countered by taking appropriate precautions. However, raising the mind to the level of the spirit, thus transcending the limitations imposed by the body-mind complex, is the best solution to offset the effects of tāpatraya.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhidaivika</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>ĀDHIBHAUTIKA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhikamāsa</word>
			<alias>adhimāsa</alias>
			<note>(&#x2018;intercalary month&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>From the most ancient times, all religious activity of the Hindus was performed at times considered auspicious or suitable for them. Calculations were done based on the movements of the sun, the moon, the planets and the stars. This resulted in the growth of an entire science of Vedic Astronomy, &#x2018;Vedāṅga Jyotiṣa&#x2019;.</p>
			<p>The most fundamental periods of time, common to all the nations are the day, the month and the year. The day is due to the revolution of the earth round its axis. The month is mainly a lunar phenomenon based on the waxing and waning of the moon. The year is due to the apparent motion of the sun as seen from the earth. Hence the Hindus followed a luni-solar calendar from the ancient times, and being aware of the difference between the two ways of calculating, also provided for the necessary adjustments to be made to bring the two into consonance. The lunar year on which are based the religious activities, is less than the solar year by about eleven days. Hence two intercalary months are added in five years, one being a second āṣāḍha (the 4th lunar month) at the end of 2 years and a second pauṣa (the 10th lunar month) at the end of another 2 years. This is according to Vedāṅga Jyotiṣa. Later works give varying periods after which the intercalary month occurs. The general rule seems to be that the lunar month in which no saṅkrānti (apparent movement of the sun from one constellation to the next, as seen from the earth) occurs, is called an adhikamāsa and bears the same name of the next lunar month which is called śuddha or nija or prākṛta, to distinguish it from the former.</p>
			<p>Somehow, the adhikamāsa was considered even from the ancient times, inauspicious and hence named malamāsa (&#x2018;the dirty month&#x2019;), malimluca (&#x2018;a thief&#x2019;), aṁhaspati (&#x2018;the lord of sins&#x2019;) and so on. During this month one was advised to avoid acts like consecrating Vedic fires, installing images, offering gifts, observing vratas or religious vows, performing upanayana and other saṁskāras (puri- ficatory rites).</p>
			<p>However in some purāṇas like the <em>Padma</em> (6.64) the intercalary month is named &#x2018;puruṣottama-māsa&#x2019; (&#x2018;month of Lord Viṣṇu&#x2019;), probably with a view to reducing the opprobrium attached to it and considered, on the other hand, as holy.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhikāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;competence&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>All people are not endowed with equal ability. To perform an act properly and efficiently one must have at least the minimum capacity and competence in that field. Training can improve it but cannot create it. This patent fact has been recognised by the Hindu scriptures and propagated under the nomenclature &#x2018;adhikāra.&#x2019; For instance, it is the man who is endowed with physical strength and mental courage that has the adhikāra for joining the armed forces. Similarly it is the person who is endowed with more than average intelligence, a fair degree of scholarship and a capacity to speak well, that has the adhikāra to enter the teaching profession. Again, it is the person who has practised at least to a certain degree, purity and self-control, that has the adhikāra to become a monk.</p>
			<p>In most cases, adhikāra can be developed by assiduous cultivation. One who has adhikāra is called an &#x2018;adhikārin&#x2019; and the doctrine that advocates the need for adhikāra is called &#x2018;adhikāravāda.&#x2019; The differences among the adhikārins are termed &#x2018;adhikāribheda.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>In this creation there is nothing that is absolute. Everything is relative. Divergences and differences do exist. The &#x2018;Doctrine of Adhikāra or Adhikārabheda&#x2019; is just a recognition of this patent fact. It does not necessarily suggest a gradation, with its corollary of &#x2018;higher&#x2019; and &#x2018;lower&#x2019; status, implying pride or contempt. It is more an acceptance of a fact as it exists, helping one to understand where one stands and start one&#x2019;s progress from that base. Also it is designed to awaken one to one&#x2019;s duties rather than to one&#x2019;s rights and privileges.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhikaraṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;ground or support&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The word is generally used in the sense of a base, ground or support. For instance, when we say, &#x2018;This is a blue lotus with a sweet smell,&#x2019; the lotus flower forms the &#x2018;adhikaraṇa&#x2019; for the blue colour as also the sweet smell.</p>
			<p>In the Mīmāṁsā philosophy, it is used as a technical term and indicates the section of a work dealing with a particular topic. It consists of five parts: viṣaya (subject of discussion), viśaya or saṁśaya (doubt), pūrvapakṣa (<em>prima facie</em> view), uttara (answer) and siddhānta or nirṇaya (final conclusion).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Adhikāra Nandi</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Everyone that enters a Śiva temple cannot fail to see the image of Nandi, the reclining bull. In iconography, Nandi or Nandikeśvara is depicted in two forms as vṛṣabha or reclining bull and as Adhikāra Nandi, an image resembling that of Śiva. In this aspect , the two back hands hold the paraśu (battle axe) and the mṛga (antelope) and the two front hands are folded on the chest in the añjali (obeisance) pose. In all other respects, the characte-ristics of the image are identical with those of Śiva.</p>
			<p>Since he is the chief of the gaṇas (retinues) of Śiva, exercising his authority (adhikāra) over them, he is christened &#x2018;Adhikāra Nandi.&#x2019; He is also called Nandīśvara or Nandikeśvara.</p>
			<p>As regards the origin of this deity, there are three different accounts available in Hindu mythology. Desirous of a son, a sage Sālaṅkāyana by name, propitiated Viṣṇu, who granted his wish by producing a boy exactly resembling Śiva, from the right side of his body. He was named Nandikeśvara. According to another account, a sage called Nandi obtained the status of a god and the headship of the gaṇas of Śiva by propitiating him. A third account depicts him as emerging from the yāgaśālā (sacrificial shed) of the blind sage Śilāda, in the form of an young lad resembling Śiva, thus bringing &#x2018;nandi&#x2019; or joy to him. Śilāda adopted him as his son.</p>
			<p>Adhikāra Nandi took a prominent part in the destruction of Dakṣa&#x2019;s sacrifice.</p>
			<p>He is more often represented as a bull and also described as the vāhana (mount) of Śiva.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>NANDI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhiṣavaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;to press out&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The Vedic sages were fond of performing sacrifices to propitiate the various deities like Indra through whom they could fulfil their wishes. In one group of such sacrifices called Somayāgas, the libation of the juice of the soma creeper was the most important ceremony. The act of pressing out the juice from the creeper was no less important and even that had a ritualistic bearing. The word &#x2018;adhiṣavaṇa&#x2019; is used to indicate both this act of pressing the soma creeper and the wooden contrivance used in the process. More often, the latter which is in the form of a pair of semicircular wooden boards, is called &#x2018;adhiṣavaṇa-phalaka.&#x2019;</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhiṣṭhāna</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;base, support, substratum&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>While discussing the theory of illusory perception, this word is often used in Vedānta to denote the substratum wherein the illusion occurs. For instance, when a snake is perceived in a rope, or silver in nacre, the rope or the nacre forms the &#x2018;adhiṣṭhāna&#x2019; or substratum, for this illusory perception. Ignorance of this adhiṣṭhāna causes the illusion and its true knowledge dispels it.</p>
			<p>While enumerating the five causes responsible for the accomplishment of every action, the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> (18.14) puts &#x2018;adhiṣṭhāna&#x2019; as the first in the list. The word is interpreted there as the body, since the body is the primary basis necessary for all actions.</p>
			<p>In works on Hindu Architecture including Temple Architecture, the word denotes the basement of a building or even a column. Innumerable varieties of the same are detailed in those works.</p>
			<p>In Civics, the word was used to indicate a seat of administration like a city-council.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhivāsa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;to live in&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Temples form a very important part of the Hindu religious institutions and culture. Building of temples has developed, over the years, into a great art. Architecture and iconography have grown both vast and deep because of it. The images, though prepared strictly according to the standards of iconography, are unfit to be installed in them unless sanctified ceremonially by rites recommended in the āgamas (a class of religious works connected with temple worship). &#x2018;Adhivāsa&#x2019; is such a rite, making the image &#x2018;live in&#x2019; various substances like water and grains. The adhivāsas are three: jalādhivāsa, dhānyādhivāsa and śayyādhivāsa. The first is to remedy the effects of chiselling, the second for purifying the physical image and the last for inducing spiritual effulgence.</p>
			<p>In jalādhivāsa (&#x2018;living in water&#x2019;), the image is taken in a procession round the village, placed on level ground on the bank of a river or tank, sprinkled with the water of the same, wound round with kuśa grass and new cloth and ceremonially immersed in the water so that the head lies towards the east and mouth upwards. The duration of jalādhivāsa is from one night to nine nights, though three nights are more common. After taking it out of water, the image has to undergo physical and ceremonial cleansing once again.</p>
			<p>Dhānyādhivāsa (&#x2018;living in grains&#x2019;) and śayyādhivāsa (&#x2018;living in the bed&#x2019;) are actually one ritual in practice. On the vedi (special platform) a sthaṇḍila (an esoteric geometric design) is inscribed. Grains like wheat, rice, barley and black sesame are spread and a lotus of eight petals is inscribed on the grains. A bed is now prepared over this with five materials viz., wooden plank, skin of deer or tiger, a rug of animal hair, feathers of birds and cloth. In the absence of the first four materials, five layers of cloth can be used. The image is now made to lie for three nights on this bed, with kuśa grass underneath it, the head being towards the east and mouth upwards.</p>
			<p>The word &#x2018;adhivāsa&#x2019; is also used in the sense of &#x2018;perfuming&#x2019; or sanctifying with perfumes or other approved materials, any object or objects used in ceremonial worship.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PRATIṢṬHĀVIDHI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhonivīta</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;that which covers below&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The dharmaśāstras have made it obligatory for every man born in the brāhmaṇa, kṣattriya and vaiśya castes to undergo the sacrament of upanayana (See <ref>UPANAYANA</ref> for details.) after which alone he becomes eligible for the study of the Vedas and the performance of ordained rituals. A concrete part of this sacrament is the investiture with the sacred thread called &#x2018;upavīta&#x2019; or &#x2018;yajñopavīta&#x2019; which should be worn permanently on the body. One of the three modes of wearing this upavīta is &#x2018;adhonivīta&#x2019; or &#x2018;adhovīta&#x2019; or &#x2018;saṁvīta&#x2019;. In this mode, the sacred thread hangs from the neck like a garland, stretching below the navel. This mode of wearing is recommended at the time of performing secular activities. The relatives of a dead person—if he belongs to any of the first three castes—attending his funeral procession are also required to wear the sacred thread in this mode.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>NIVĪTA</ref>, <ref>UPAVĪTA</ref> and <ref>YAJÑOPAVĪTA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhvara</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;that which leads by a straight, therefore true, path&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Human beings by nature, are interested in getting the good things of life so that they can live in comfort, happiness and peace. Those of them that believe in an after-life, are also interested in perfor-ming those acts here, that assure them a happy life hereafter. If the religious and spiritual leaders do not show them the right way, in all likelihood, they will take to the wrong way, the way of selfishness, competition and even fighting among themselves. Hence the need to show them the right path, the straight path, the good path. This is exactly what &#x2018;adhvara&#x2019; is. Etymologically it means a path which is not crooked, which does not cause harm to others. But in usage, it means a Vedic sacrifice. Since the Vedic sacrifices point the straight and good path for the fulfilment of man&#x2019;s wishes, here and hereafter, it is but proper that they are designated &#x2018;adhvara.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>For details of sacrifices, see <ref>VEDIC SACRIFICES</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhvaryu</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;One who desires an adhvara or a sacrifice&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Man aspires after maximum happiness but with minimum effort, if he can help it. This aspiration can often tempt him to resort to shortcut methods which will entail a lot of suffering to other beings. The Vedic ṛṣis (sages) who had thoroughly understood human psychology, propounded and propagated a system of sacrifices by following which man could get his desires fulfilled, in a righteous way.</p>
			<p>Every such sacrifice must have a minimum of four priests: hotā, adhvaryu, udgātṛ and brahmā. Adhvaryu, the second priest who follows the <em>Yajurveda</em>, is by far the most active of the group. It is he who surveys the sacrificial ground, designs and builds the altars, prepares or secures the utensils, cooks the sacrificial oblations, fetches water and wood, kindles the fires, brings the animals and immolates them, all the while repeating the appropriate mantras from the <em>Yajurveda</em> at appropriate times. Being constantly on the move, he has no fixed seat. He is normally assisted by three priests: pratiprasthātṛ, neṣṭṛ and unnetṛ. Sometimes the number of such priests including him may be as large as 36.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>BRAHMĀ</ref>, <ref>HOTṚ</ref>, <ref>UDGĀTṚ</ref> and <ref>VEDIC SACRIFICES</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhyāropa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;superimposition&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The attempts at reconciling Brahman the Absolute with the world which is imperfect and limited have resulted in the &#x2018;doctrine of adhyāropa-apavāda.&#x2019; The problem is sought to be resolved by considering the world as an adhyāropa or adhyāsa, a superimposition (even as a snake is superimposed on a rope resulting in illusory perception) and denying it absolute reality. The process of desuperimposition called &#x2018;apavāda,&#x2019; consists of negating the illusory appearances by adopting the right means of knowledge and perceiving the truth as it is. Adhyāropa is practically the same as &#x2018;adhyāsa&#x2019; (See <ref>ADHYĀSA</ref>.) A slight shade of difference in meaning is perhaps, that adhyāropa refers to the process and adhyāsa is the result.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhyāsa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;superimposition&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The Advaita Vedānta philosophy, the chief exponent of which was Śaṅkara (A.D. 788-820), accepts Brahman (the Absolute), which is beyond names, forms, attributes, and hence, defies all description, as the Ultimate Reality. But the world that we perceive with its myriad names, forms and attributes, circumscribed by time, space and causation, cannot be easily brushed aside or wished away. Hence there is a great need to explain the relationship between Brahman the Absolute and this world of phenomena. &#x2018;Adhyāsa&#x2019; or &#x2018;adhyāropa&#x2019; is the explanation offered by Advaita Vedānta.</p>
			<p>Literally, the word means one thing &#x2018;sitting upon&#x2019; another, hiding its nature for the time being. It is defined as &#x2018;the appearance elsewhere, as in memory, of something perceived earlier.&#x2019; (<em>Adhyāsa-bhāṣya</em> of Śaṅkara, <em>Brahmasūtras</em> 1.1.1). Two oft-repeated analogies are the erroneous perception of a snake in a rope in insufficient light and of silver in nacre shining in light. In both cases, the impressions of a snake and silver from an earlier idea of the same are superimposed on the rope and the nacre under conditions conducive to the erroneous perception. These erroneous perceptions have been caused by the &#x2018;adhyāsa&#x2019; of the snake on the rope and the silver on the nacre. This again is due to ajñāna or avidyā (ignorance) of the real nature of the adhiṣṭhāna (substratum—here, the rope and the nacre). This ajñāna is anādi (without beginning) since it has no ascertainable beginning. Once this ajñāna is removed by right perception, the error disappears automatically.</p>
			<p>Using the doctrine of adhyāsa and the two analogies already mentioned, Advaita metaphysics tries to explain that the world palpably perceived by the senses is only an erroneous perception caused by adhyāsa on Brahman. Once the real nature of Brahman is realised, the world appearance ceases. At the subjective level, this adhyāsa causes the erroneous perception of the body-mind complex on the ātman (the immanent aspect of Brahman at the individual level). Once the real nature of the ātman is realised, its identification with the body-mind complex will disappear.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ADHYĀROPA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhyātma</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;pertaining to the ātman&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>In the Upaniṣads as well as in the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> the three words adhibhūta, adhidaiva and adhyātma are frequently met with. The indeclinable &#x2018;adhi&#x2019; has the sense of &#x2018;ruling over,&#x2019; &#x2018;pertaining to&#x2019;. The word &#x2018;ātman&#x2019; is often used in the sense of the body. Hence &#x2018;adhyātma&#x2019; generally indicates the Self within the body which resides in it and rules over it. It is also used to indicate Brahman or the Supreme Self.</p>
			<p>The word is also used as an adjective and in combination with other words. For instance: adhyātmavidyā (knowledge of the Self), adhyātmayoga (yoga or meditation on the Self).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhyātma-prasāda</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;peace of the mind within&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Mind is the basic instrument for gaining knowledge and wisdom. Controlling its vagaries and making it flow in a concentrated manner is the best means of attaining knowledge in any field. This however is easier said than done. By a long and arduous process of yogic discipline which includes the practice of ethical principles like ahiṁsā (non-violence), satya (truth) and brahmacarya (continence) and the practice of concentration by stages, the mind loses all its dross and impurities and becomes placid and pellucid. Such a state of mind is called &#x2018;adhyātma-prasāda&#x2019; (<em>vide Yogasūtras</em> 1.47). In this state the mind, being rid of all impurities that distract and disturb it, has become like a pure crystal capable of reflecting the consciousness of the puruṣa (the Self), in full measure. Such a mind can produce instant knowledge of any object towards which it is directed.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Hindu life will lose all its meaning and charm without Rāma and Kṛṣṇa, the two colossuses that have strode the Hindu heart for the last few millennia. If the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> of Vālmikī has been the basis on which the Rāma personality has been built up, no less important are its numerous imitations and adoptions that have kept alive the Rāma cult and the Rāma community leading to the development of Rāmālogy. Perhaps, one of the most important Sanskrit works of this type is the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> which is very popular in North India, not only among the devotees of Rāma but also among the Vedāntins. In fact, it is this work that provided Tulasīdāsa with the inspiration to compose his immortal work, the <em>Rāmacaritmānasa</em>.</p>
			<p>Though depicted as a part of the <em>Brahmāṇḍa Purāṇa</em>, respected as a canonical work of the Vaiṣṇavas and begun in the Tantra style of conversation between Śiva Mahādeva and Pārvatī, scholars ascribe it to the period 14th-15th cent. A.D. Nothing is known of the author, though the Rāma tradition believes it to be Vedavyāsa since it is said to be an integral part of the <em>Brahmāṇḍa Purāṇa</em>.</p>
			<p>Like its original source, the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> also has seven kāṇḍas or books, named in the same manner, except for the sixth, the <em>Yuddhakāṇḍa</em>, which is sometimes designated <em>Laṅkākāṇḍa</em>. The total number of verses is 4200 spread over 65 sargas or chapters. Written in mellifluous Sanskrit, the work admirably sums up the main events of the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> of Vālmīki omitting only the minor details, or descriptions of war and nature. On the other hand new material pertaining to Vedānta philo-sophy, the cult of bhakti in general and Rāma-bhakti in particular and several hymns in praise of Rāma have been liberally added.</p>
			<p>A few of the changes and innovations made, departing from the original may be noted here: The major alteration in the facts of the story is the introduction of a shadow Sītā throughout the period of her abduction, the real Sītā having disappeared into the fire just before the golden deer episode. She re-emerges from the fire at the end of the war when the shadow Sītā enters into it. The whole drama is preplanned and enacted at the bidding of Rāma himself (<em>vide</em> 3.7). Other alterations though minor in nature, are: the earth accompanies the gods in the form of a cow (1.2); Sumitrā gets more of the sacred pudding than Kausalyā and Kaikeyī (1.3); Ahalyā after being cursed by her husband, the sage Gautama, becomes a stone (1.5); Rāvaṇa treats Sītā with the respect due to a mother (3.7.65); Rāma establishes a Śivaliṅga at the site of the bridge to Laṅkā (6.4.1-2).</p>
			<p>Coming to the additions to Vālmikī&#x2019;s story, five paurāṇic episodes need be mentioned: the stories about Vālmīki himself (2.6), Śuka (6.5) and Kālanemi (6.6) who warn Rāvaṇa about Rāma&#x2019;s divinity and the need to propitiate him, Vālī and Sugrīva (7.3). The dialogue between Rāvaṇa and Sanatkumāra is another addition (7.3).</p>
			<p>But the major contribution of the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> lies in its casting of Rāma in the role of a spiritual teacher and in the several exquisite hymns sung in praise of Rāma. There are four occasions when Rāma assumes the role of the teacher and gives philosophic disquisitions. In response to Lakṣmaṇa&#x2019;s questions on three different occasions he teaches know-ledge, devotion, detachment (<em>vide</em> 3.4), methods of worship (4.4) and the way of emancipation (7.5). In reply to Kausalyā&#x2019;s query, he teaches the three yogas of karma, jñāna and bhakti (7.7).</p>
			<p>The well-known <em>Rāmagītā</em> is part of the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> and is the teaching given to Lakṣmaṇa on the last occasion already referred to (7.5). It contains a rather strong dose of Advaita Vedānta though couched in beautiful poetry. In fact some scholars feel that this <em>Rāmagītā</em> and<em> Rāmahṛdaya</em> (1.1) were independent works incorporated later into this <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em>.</p>
			<p>As regards the laudatory hymns, we find quite a good number of them: by Brahmā (1.2; 6.13), Kausalyā (1.3), Nārada (2.1), Vālmīki (2.6), Jaṭāyu (3.8), Vibhīṣaṇa (6.6) and all the gods (6.15).</p>
			<p>However the real contribution of this work is in its repeatedly propounding the doctrine that Rāma is Brahman the Absolute and that Sītā is his Māyāśakti or Prakṛti, thereby raising the personality of Rāma to the highest level and providing a firm base to the cult of Rāma. No occasion that gives a chance to do this is missed. Not only sages, gods and devotees, but even the enemies of Rāma—not excepting Rāvaṇa himself !—recognise his divinity and divine mission. Their only duty is to cooperate in the cosmic play of the Divine and be blessed. This task has been admirably fulfilled by the book.</p>
			<p>In the orthodox circles of Rāma devotees, the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em>, is considered to be a mantraśāstra, a sacred book, each stanza of which is revered as a &#x2018;mantra&#x2019; (mystic syllable) and devoutly repeated in a ceremonial way.</p>
			<p>It is worthwhile noting that the well-known Hindi work, <em>Rāmcaritamānas</em> of Tulsīdas (A. D. 1532-1623), is based almost entirely on the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em>.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>RĀMAGĪTĀ</ref>, <ref>RĀMAHṚDAYA</ref> and <ref>RĀMĀYAṆA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Adhyātma Upaniṣad</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Upaniṣads are the treasurehouse of the spiritual knowledge of India. They have been accepted and venerated as basic scriptures by most of the religio-philosophical schools of India. Every philo-sopher or religious reformer has taken pains to show that his views are rooted in the Upaniṣadic traditions, or at least, do not go against them. Even the non-Hindu and non-Indian savants have heaped praises on their enlightened views.</p>
			<p>The ten Upaniṣads on which Śaṅkara (A. D. 788-820) wrote commentaries have universally been accepted as the more ancient, more authentic and authoritative. The <em>Adhyātma Upaniṣad</em>, though outside this list, still, breathes the spirit of the more ancient and the major Upaniṣads.</p>
			<p>Since the printed texts give the śāntimantra as &#x2018;pūrṇamadaḥ ...&#x2019; it is to be surmised that it belongs to the <em>Śukla Yajurveda</em>. The last verse of the Upaniṣad declares that it was first revealed to the sage Apāntaratamas who taught it to Brahmā. Brahmā gave it to Ghora Aṅgiras who in turn transmitted the same to Raikva. Raikva passed it on to Rāma and Rāma revealed it to all the living beings.</p>
			<p>The teaching itself has been designated as &#x2018;nirvāṇānuśāsanam&#x2019; (&#x2018;command concerning final emancipation&#x2019;).</p>
			<p>The text consists of 70 verses, all in the śloka metre, and has not been divided into sub-sections. But there is a method and order in the dealing of the subject matter. It starts with the description of the antarātman, the Innermost Self, the same as Adhyātman, (hence the name <em>Adhyātma Upaniṣad</em>) who exists in all things and beings controlling them from within, but whom none of them knows. He has also been called &#x2018;Nārāyaṇa&#x2019; here (verse 1). After declaring that the sense of &#x2018;I&#x2019; and &#x2018;mine&#x2019; with regard to the body and the senses which are anātman or non-Self, arises due to adhyāsa or superimposition by ignorance, the Upaniṣad exhorts us to get rid of this adhyāsa by being devoted to Brahman and through discrimination. The line of arguments to be pursued in this is practically the same as in Advaita Vedānta (v. 2-11). This is followed by a description of the ātman-Brahman principle as the one without a second, and without internal distinctions. The disciple is asked to see It as his own Self (v. 12-27). Renunciation leads to intuitive knowledge which results in the withdrawal of the mind into itself. Resting it on the ātman, one attains infinite peace and joy or realization. This is the next topic (v. 28 and 29). Then, the identity between the jīva (individual soul) and Brahman (the Cosmic Soul) is shown by negating the accidental characteristics like association with the mind and the māyā-power (v.30-32) followed by a delineation of the three sādhanās or practices, śravaṇa (hearing), manana (reflection) and nididhyāsana (meditation) resulting in samādhi (superconscious experience) (v. 33-35). Then, there is the description of &#x2018;dharma-megha-samādhi,&#x2019; &#x2018;the samādhi which results in kaivalya or liberation&#x2019; (v. 36-43). This is followed by a nice pen-picture of the jīvanmukta, one who is liberated even while living in the body (v. 44-47). He is never affected by the vicissitudes of life and is ever in equipoise. Then the Upaniṣad says that the knowledge of the ātman destroys all the previously accumulated karmas, except the prārabdha-karma which has already begun to fructify. It can be exhausted only through experience. However, the liberated soul is unaffected by it (v. 48-60). It ends with a poetic description of the personal experience of the jīvanmukta (v. 61-69).</p>
			<p>This Upaniṣad is sometimes called <em>Turīyātīta Avadhūta Upaniṣad</em> also.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>UPANIṢADS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhyātmavidyā</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;science pertaining to the Self within&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The Hindu sages have always advocated mokṣa (liberation from transmi- gration) as the parama-puruṣārtha (the highest goal to be achieved by man) and have recommended adhyātmavidyā as the means of achieving it. Adhyātmavidyā is the science that leads one to the realization of the Self within. It is the knowledge and wisdom taught in the Upaniṣads, the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> and other works which follow them. A study of these books under enlightened teachers will lead to a clear understanding of the ātman or the Self and meditation on this understanding will ultimately lead to realization. Parā-vidyā and brahmavidyā are other words often used as synonyms for this. It is the highest knowledge and the only one worth seeking in life. Hence in the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em>, Lord Kṛṣṇa goes to the extent of identifying himself with it (<em>vide</em> 10.31).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ādhyātmika</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;pertaining to the Self &#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>ĀDHIBHAUTIKA</ref> and <ref>ADHYĀTMA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adhyayana</word>
			<alias>adhyāpana</alias>
			<note>(&#x2018;studying and teaching&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Study of the Vedas, technically termed &#x2018;adhyayana,&#x2019; was considered not only as part of education but as part of religious life as well. Since a change of svara (intonation) would often entail a change of meaning as well, great care was exercised in preserving the oral musical tradition of the Vedas.</p>
			<p>The student desirous of learning the Vedas had to live in the house of the guru, after first completing the sacrament of upanayana. Avoiding the days known as &#x2018;anadhyayana&#x2019; (or anadhyāya) (See <ref>ANADHYĀYA</ref>.) on all other permissible days he could approach the guru for Vedic studies after finishing the daily religious chores like the sandhyā. He had to sit facing north. The guru would recite the Vedic mantras pāda by pāda (i.e., a quarter of a stanza) and the student had to repeat them at least twice. Once he learnt the correct pronunciation and intonation and also committed it to memory, the guru would proceed with the next part. The student had to revise the lessons by himself or with the help of senior students the same day. The study would cover the Saṁhitā, the Brāhmaṇa and the Upaniṣad parts of the particular śākhā (branch) of the Veda to which the student belonged. It would normally take twelve years to master one&#x2019;s śākhā.</p>
			<p>Along with the Vedic studies, a study of the Vedāṅgas (subsidiaries like grammar) dharmaśāstras, itihāsas and purāṇas as also some secular sciences would also be pursued.</p>
			<p>As for teaching (adhyāpana), it was expected that the teacher (adhyāpaka or ācārya) should be well-versed and competent and of a sinless life. He could teach anyone eligible for Vedic studies, on any of the following three conditions:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>as dharma, as part of his duties;</li>
				<li>for artha or wealth, if the student promised it beforehand;</li>
				<li>as a reward for śuśrūṣā or personal service. He was not expected to teach if none of these conditions was fulfilled.</li>
			</ol>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādimūrti</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the Original form&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Viṣṇu, the central deity of the Hindu Trinity, manifests himself in several forms. &#x2018;Ādimūrti&#x2019; is one of them. Considered as a minor manifestation, he is described in iconographical works as sitting upon the serpent Ādiśeṣa, with the right leg hanging and the left as folded and resting upon the seat. Of the four hands, the two back hands hold as usual, the śaṅkha (conch) and cakra (discus). The front right hand rests upon the seat whereas the front left is supported on the folded left knee. The colour of the figure is coral red and it is richly decorated with ornaments. The other two gods of the Trinity, Brahmā and Śiva, as also the sages Bhṛgu and Mārkaṇḍeya are also shown, in a reveren-tial aspect.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādinātha</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the Primeval Lord&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The esoteric Nātha cult which originated in Bengal and the followers of which are found in some parts of North India considers the Supreme Being as elusive and intangible, and as manifested in the universe created out of him. It designates him as &#x2018;Ādinātha.&#x2019; Following in the footsteps of the <em>Ṛgveda</em> (10.129) and the opening verse of <em>Manusaṁhitā</em>, the Nātha cult describes the beginning of creation as starting from a bubble or an egg which appeared as a result of the impulse for creation in the infinite void and all- encompassing darkness. The egg hatched and out of it emerged &#x2018;Ādinātha&#x2019; the primeval God. From his sweat was produced his spouse Ketakā or Manasā who in turn created Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Śiva. Further creation proceeded out of them.</p>
			<p>The first of the nine Nātha gurus is also Ādinātha.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>NĀTHA-CULT</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādiparva</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p><em>Mahābhārata</em>, the great epic of Hinduism and the biggest didactic work of poetry in world literature, is divided into eighteen books, each of which is known as a &#x2018;parvan.&#x2019; <em>Ādiparva</em> forms the very first book. For details see under <ref>MAHĀBHĀRATA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādipurāṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the original mythology&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Every religion has three aspects: philosophy, mythology and rituals. While philosophy tries to find solutions to the ultimate questions and problems of life, mythology tries to explain the truths discovered by it, through stories, allegories and examples. The Hindu mythological lore, designated &#x2018;purāṇa,&#x2019; does this and much more. It gives whole systems of knowledge in various fields whether allied to or even remotely connected with philo-sophy, or not. The <em>Ādipurāṇa</em> is one of the purāṇas often included in the lists.</p>
			<p>According to one tradition, it is the original purāṇa, as its very name implies, composed by Brahmā the Creator himself.</p>
			<p>Comprising four hundred thousand verses, it is the source book for all the other purāṇas written by Vyāsa. The book however is not available now.</p>
			<p>Among the extant purāṇas, the <em>Brahmapurāṇa</em> is occasionally designated as <em>Ādipurāṇa</em> also. One <em>Ādipurāṇa</em> is sometimes listed among the minor purāṇas known as upapurāṇas. This book, now available in print is obviously a much later work. It is mainly the story of Kṛṣṇa.</p>
			<p>The Jaina tradition (digambara sect) also has an <em>Ādipurāṇa</em>, an incomplete work by one Jinasena, a part of which was added on later by another author Guṇabhadra. It describes the stories of Ṛṣabhadeva and Bharata, the first two Tīrthaṅkaras.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PURĀṆAS</ref> and <ref>UPAPURĀṆAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādiśakti</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;Primeval Power&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The source and sustenance of all creation whether at the level of matter, mind or life, is one. It is called Śakti (power or energy). Hinduism posits a cyclic theory of creation (sṛṣṭi), preservation (sthiti) and destruction (pralaya) and this goes on eternally. It is the Śakti of God that is responsible for this. This Śakti is usually conceived as a female deity, as the Consort of God. Since she is the original source, she is often called &#x2018;Ādiśakti,&#x2019; the Primeval Power.</p>
			<p>It is the Śaiva and Śākta Āgama works that propound this theory of Śakti, and She is fully identified with Pārvatī, Śiva&#x2019;s Consort. Māyā (the illusory power of God) of Vedānta and Durgā of the purāṇas are also called Ādiśakti since they also are identified with Pārvatī.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ŚAKTI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādiśeṣa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>In the Hindu mythological literature, Ādiśeṣa is described as a mighty serpent of a thousand hoods on which he is supporting the world. He forms the bed on which Lord Nārāyaṇa is reclining. Ananta, Anantanāga, Śeṣa and Śeṣanāga are his other names. Born as the son of Kadru and Kaśyapa he later on dropped out of the company of his brother-serpents since they illtreated his step-mother Vinatā who was a good and noble woman. He pleased Brahmā, the Creator, by severe austerities and obtained the boon of the power to support the world on his hoods. Lord Nārāyaṇa was pleased to make him his couch. Lakṣmaṇa and Balarāma, the brothers of Rāma and Kṛṣṇa, are said to be the incarnations of Ādiśeṣa. So also Patañjali, the promulgator of the Yoga system of philosophy.</p>
			<p>It is obvious that this is a highly allegorical and symbolical picture. Ādiśeṣa really stands for cosmic time and space which are &#x2018;ananta,&#x2019; endless or infinite. Hence, the myth of Ādiśeṣa supporting the world on his thousand hoods signifies that the created world comes into being in the infinite time and space and is sustained by them. The thousand hoods stand for the innumerable divisions of time and space.</p>
			<p>The word &#x2018;śeṣa&#x2019; means &#x2018;what is left over&#x2019;, &#x2018;the remainder&#x2019;. Since creation cannot proceed out of nothing, it is to be assumed that &#x2018;something&#x2019; is left over (śeṣa) from the previous cycle of creation. So Śeṣa represents the totality of jīvas or individual souls in their subtle forms left over from the previous cycle and needing more opportunities for redemption.</p>
			<p>The serpent usually stands for kāma or desire, which is always left over (śeṣa) even after acquiring and enjoying the desired object. Hence in a cosmic sense it can stand for the desire of the Lord to proceed with the next cycle of creation after rest.</p>
			<p>Lord Nārāyaṇa reclining upon the serpent couch can mean that desire for creation as also time and space form the basis, resting on which he proceeds with creation.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>NĀRĀYAṆA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Aditi</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the boundless&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Aditi, the &#x2018;devamātā&#x2019; (mother of the gods) is one of the few goddesses mentioned in the <em>Ṛgveda</em> and other Vedic literature. She is often associated with Diti, her sister, and mother of the daityas (demons). She is eulogised as the boundless and identified with practically everything in the created world. She is the sky and the air. The three aspects of time are also she. She has become all the human beings, nay, even the gods. She is the mother and she is the father too. That is why supplications are made to her to confer her blessings on children and cattle as also for the removal of sins (<em>vide Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 1.89.10).</p>
			<p>In the mythological lore of the Vedas she is usually described as one of the daughters of Dakṣa, though sometimes she is said to be his mother. There are also passages which mention her as the wife of Viṣṇu instead of Kaśyapa. However according to most of the accounts she was married to the sage Kaśyapa for whom she bore several sons. The gods being her sons are called Āditeyas. Sometimes the eight Ādityas are described as her sons. Out of these eight, she is said to have cast out the last son Mārttaṇḍa.</p>
			<p>Coming to the Upaniṣads, the word &#x2018;Aditi&#x2019; is used to denote death, the devourer (ad to devour) (<em>Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad</em> 1.2.5), and the deity presiding over the earth (<em>Mahānārayaṇa Upaniṣad</em> 28.1) as also the jīvātman or the individual soul (<em>Kaṭha Upaniṣad</em> 4.7).</p>
			<p>In the epics and the purāṇas she is always depicted as the daughter of Dakṣa, wife of Kaśyapa and mother of gods including the Vāmana incarnation of Viṣṇu. Indra is said to have picked up a pair of divine kuṇḍalas (ear-rings) as they were thrown up by the churning of the primeval ocean (See <ref>SAMUDRAMATHANA</ref>) and presented them to Aditi. But the demon Narakāsura Bhauma (the son of Bhūmi or earth) stole them from her. It was Kṛṣṇa who recovered and restored them to her.</p>
			<p>Aditi is also the name of a place of pilgrimage on the bank of the river Gaṅgā.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Āditya</word>
			<alias>Ādityas</alias>
			<note>(&#x2018;son/sons of Aditi&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Āditya is one of the well-known epithets of the sun.</p>
			<p>The Ādityas, the sons of Aditi, repre-sent a group of deities. They are six in the <em>Ṛgveda</em>, eight in most of the Brāhmaṇas (except the <em>Śatapatha</em>) and twelve in the later mythological lore. They can be described as the personifications of the laws that rule the universe and the human society. They regulate the relationships of human beings among themselves and with the forces of nature.</p>
			<p>Since Āditya is one of the names of the sun, the Ādityas can be considered as imperishable beings, the gods of light, by whom all kinds of luminous life are manifested and sustained in this universe.</p>
			<p>The twelve Ādityas are: Mitra (the friend), Varuṇa (one who encompasses and binds), Aryaman (the destroyer of foes), Dakṣa (the skilful), Bhaga (the giver), Aṁśa (the liberal), Tvaṣṭṛ (the shaper), Savitṛ (the vivifier), Pūṣan (the nourisher), Śakra (the mighty), Vivasvat (the resplendent) and Viṣṇu (the pervader).</p>
			<p>Sometimes, these twelve are linked with the twelve aspects of the sun spread over the twelve months and hence des-cribed as the twelve spokes of the wheel of time.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>SŪRYA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āditya-darśana</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;seeing the sun&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Every Hindu has to undergo certain saṁskāras or sacraments—religious rites conducive to inner evolution—at various stages of his life. The dharmaśāstras list them as sixteen; hence the name &#x2018;ṣodaśa-saṁskāras&#x2019; (ṣodaśa 16). One such ṣaṁskāra called &#x2018;niṣkramaṇa&#x2019; (lit., &#x2018;going out&#x2019;) consists of taking the baby outside the lying-in chamber for the first time, to see the sun. This is &#x2018;āditya-darśana.&#x2019; For details see <ref>NIṢKRAMAṆA</ref>.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>SAṀSKĀRAS</ref> and <ref>ṢODAŚA-SAṀSKĀRAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Āditya-hṛdaya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the heart or the essence of Āditya&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Hindu hymnal literature is as vast as it is deep. Quite a few of these hymns, whether they contain praises of the Lord or expound some philosophical doctrines, are often used for ceremonial chanting, considering them as mantras (esoteric words and sentences) capable of fulfilling one&#x2019;s desires. The <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> of Vālmīki, though a voluminuous work, strangely enough, contains only one such hymn; strangely enough because, the <em>Mahā-bhārata</em>, the other epic, as also the purāṇas contain scores of them. This hymn known as the &#x2018;Ādityahṛdaya&#x2019; occurs in the <em>Yuddhakāṇḍa</em> (sarga 105).</p>
			<p>After the first round of battle with Rāvaṇa, Rāma was rather tired and anxious as to how he could vanquish his formidable enemy. Just at that time, Agastya the sage of the Vindhya fame, who was among those that had gathered to witness the battle, came forward to reveal a secret with the help of which Rāma could conquer Rāvaṇa and fulfil the mission of his life. The secret was the <em>Ādityahṛdaya</em> hymn by reciting which he could get enough power to destroy his foe. Being initiated into its mysteries by Agastya, Rāma recited it thrice, became imbued with energy and enthusiasm and achieved victory with ease.</p>
			<p>Whether the <em>Ādityahṛdaya</em> comprises the entire chapter or part of it only (e.g., verses 6 to 21) is a point on which there are differences of opinion. Verses 1 to 5 form the introduction and eulogise the hymn. Verses 6 to 21 describe Āditya or the Sun-god, his various names and attributes. Verses 22 to 25 describe his power and give the phalaśruti (the benefits of recitation). Verse 26 gives the viniyoga (the method and purpose of recitation). Verses 27 to 31 complete the narration of the story.</p>
			<p>Here are a few of the epithets which the hymn uses to describe and eulogise Āditya: He is so effulgent that even the gods adore him. In fact he is the very personification of all gods including the Trinity. It is he that is manifested as the leaders of the eight quarters. He is the creator and sustainer of the world. It is again he that destroys the world at the end of the cycle of creation. He is manifested in everything that is created.</p>
			<p>The proper recitation of the hymn will free a man from all troubles and tribulations and fulfil the wishes of his heart.</p>
			<p>Every mantra has a ṛṣi (the seer to whom it was revealed), a chandas (the poetical metre) and a devatā (the deity to whom it is addressed), who are to be adored at the beginning of a ceremonial recitation. In the case of this hymn (which is considered as a mantra), Agastya is the ṛṣi and anuṣṭubh is the chandas. As regards the devatā, some state that Brahmā residing in the sun is the deity whereas others consider Rāma the Supreme God, the internal ruler of the sun, is himself the deity. The viniyoga or purpose is to obtain supreme knowledge or victory in all walks of life.</p>
			<p>Any Sunday on which there is a saṅkrānti (movement of the sun from one zodiacal sign to the next) is believed to be very holy and suitable for the recitation of this hymn. Repeating it 108 times in a Sun-temple and observing a fast in the night are considered to be highly meritorious.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādityapurāṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;purāṇa concerning  Āditya or Sun-god&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Purāṇas or the mythological lore of the Hindus are a vast body of literature dealing with not only philosophical and religious subjects but also cultural and even mundane subjects. They are divided into two broad groups: The Mahāpurāṇas (the great, big or main purāṇas) and the Upapurāṇas (small or subsidiary purāṇas). <em>Ādityapurāṇa</em>, a purāṇa dealing with the deity Āditya (Sun-god), is often mentioned in the latter group. The book itself is not available now, except for some quotations incorporated by the dharmaśāstra literature. These quotations concern the following subjects: rājadharma (duties of the king), dāna (gifts), śrāddha (obsequial offerings), vrata (religious vows and obser- vances) and śauca (ceremonial purity).</p>
			<p>The <em>Matsyapurāṇa</em> (53.62) as also Al Beruni (A. D. 1030) mention this purāṇa.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PURĀṆAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Āditya-śānti-vrata</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;religious vow to appease Āditya or Sun-god&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Vratas or religious vows and observances are a common form of practical religion in Hinduism. These vratas are undertaken either for fulfilling a desire with divine intervention or for expiating sin or even as observing a spiritual discipline.</p>
			<p>The Ādityaśāntivrata can be observed on any Sunday associated with the Hastā-nakṣatra. Worshipping the image of the Sun with 28 or 108 fuel sticks of the arka plant (<em>Calatropis gigantea</em>) is the main part of the ritual. These fuel sticks are to be offered with honey and ghee (or ghee and curds) in homa (fire sacrifice). The vrata can be repeated seven times.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>VRATAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādityatīrtha</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>(&#x2018;place of pilgrimage connec- ted with Āditya or Sun-god&#x2019;)</p>
			<p>Places of pilgrimage have always played a very important part in the life of a devout Hindu. Endowed with natural beauty and conducive to peace and blessed-ness these places have been attracting millions of pious pilgrims since millennia.</p>
			<p>Ādityatīrtha is one of the less known places of pilgrimage mentioned in some of the Hindu scriptures (<em>vide Śalyaparva</em>, ch. 49 of <em>Mahābhārata</em>). Situated on the bank of the now invisible Sarasvatī river, the place got its name on account of its association with Āditya (Sun) who performed a sacrifice there and obtained lordship over all bright objects. It was here that Lord Viṣṇu killed the demons Madhu and Kaiṭabha.</p>
			<p>Again it was in this sacred place that great sages like Vyāsa, Kṛṣṇa and Śuka performed austerities and gained perfection.</p>
			<p>The <em>Padmapurāṇa</em> locates it at the confluence of the river Sābhramatī with the sea.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>TĪRTHAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādityavrata</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;vrata to please Āditya&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>A brahmacārin (celibate student) living in the house of the ācārya (preceptor) had to observe several vratas (religious observances) as part of the student-life. Whenever the study of new sections of the Vedas had to be commenced he had to prepare himself physically and mentally for the same. For instance the followers of <em>Sāmaveda</em> were required to perform five vratas before studying its several sections: godānika, vrātika, āditya, aupaniṣada and jyeṣṭhasāma vratas.</p>
			<p>Ādityavrata was considered as optional by some authorities, whereas the other vratas were compulsory. It had to be performed before beginning the study of the śukriya section (last part of the Āraṇyaka) of the Sāmaveda.</p>
			<p>Before beginning the vrata nāndī-mukha-śrāddha (See <ref>ĀBHYUDAYIKA ŚRĀDDHA</ref>.) had to be performed and upanayana saṁskāra had to be undergone once again, followed by ājyahoma (offering ghee into the fire) with Āditya mantras. During the period of the vrata which lasted for a year, the brahmacārin had to wear only one cloth and avoid taking protection against the sun&#x2019;s rays by contrivances like umbrella. Of course, taking shelter in the house or under trees was allowed. Also, he was prohibited from entering into more than knee-deep water, for bath. The vrata had to be concluded with offering caru (porridge of unpounded rice) to Indra, repeating the ājyahoma and gifting a cow to the ācārya (preceptor).</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādivarāha</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>BHŪVARĀHA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ādivāsīs</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;Original inhabitants&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The population of the Ādivāsīs, the original inhabitants of India or aboriginals —that is what the name signifies—exceeds thirty million. They are primarily to be found in north-east India, Bihar, Orissa, Madhya Pradesh and parts of Maharashtra, Deccan and South India. How many of them are really the &#x2018;original&#x2019; inhabitants and how many have come as migrants is anybody&#x2019;s guess. The various tribes of Ādivāsīs largely inhabiting the mountain and jungle areas differ widely from one another with regard to racial characteristics, language, food habits, modes of dress, means of occupation as also their cult and culture. By and large they are treated as belonging to Hindu culture.</p>
			<p>Their religious beliefs and observances include the worship of nature and totems as also their ancestors and spirits. Taboos are many. Bloody sacrifices are common. Priests are sorcerers too and have a tight grip over the community. Modern education, wherever it has percolated, is fast changing the complexion of their life style.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adoption</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>DATTAKA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adravya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;non-substance&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The Indian systems of metaphysics known as &#x2018;darśanas&#x2019; invariably deal with three topics: Pramā (valid knowledge), pramāṇa (means of valid knowledge) and prameya (objects of valid knowledge)</p>
			<p>The Viśiṣṭādvaita Darśana, one of the important schools of Vedānta, whose chief exponent was Rāmānuja (A. D. 1017-1137) categorises prameya into two broad groups of &#x2018;dravya&#x2019; (substance) and &#x2018;adravya&#x2019; (nonsubstance).</p>
			<p>If dravya acts as a substratum or locus of change, adravya is an attribute or quality always necessarily dependent on dravya. Neither dravya nor adravya can be thought of apart from the other.</p>
			<p>The adravyas are ten: sattva, rajas and tamas (the three guṇas or qualities of prakṛti or insentient nature); śabda (sound), sparśa (touch), rūpa (colour or form), rasa (taste) and gandha (odour) being the five characteristic qualities of the five bhūtas like ākāśa (ether); saṁyoga (conjunction or external relation between substances) and śakti (potency or the effecting agency in all causal substances as for instance, plasticity in clay or the power of attraction in a magnet).</p>
			<p>According to Viśiṣṭādvaita, instances can be given where an adravya can be viewed both as a substance and as an attribute. For example, though light is an attribute of an effulgent object, it serves also as a substance, since it is subject to contraction and diffusion, and possesses colour as an attribute. Dharmabhūtajñāna is another example.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>DHARMABHŪTAJÑĀNA</ref> and <ref>VIŚIṢṬĀDVAITA VEDĀNTA DARŚANA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adṛṣṭa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the unseen&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Human efforts, however great, often end in failure or only in partial success. The reason is that there is an unseen (adṛṣṭa) power that is guiding human destinies. Success or failure depends on the consonance or otherwise of this power with our efforts. This belief in an unseen power is common to almost all the religious groups.</p>
			<p>Most of the Hindu religious works use this word in the sense of &#x2018;karma&#x2019; or fate (the consequence of actions, good or bad, done in the previous lives). The word is sometimes used to indicate only merit, accruing to the performer of good deeds. Some schools use it in the sense of blind destiny also.</p>
			<p>The Pūrva-mīmāṁsā system however employs it in a technical sense as equivalent to &#x2018;apūrva,&#x2019; the unseen effect of sacrificial rites producing the desired results for the performer in his future life.</p>
			<p>Adṛṣṭa resides in the subtle body of the soul unfolding its results at the appropriate time in future or in future life. Its power is irresistible and incompre- hensible by ordinary consciousness.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>APŪRVA</ref> and <ref>KARMA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>adultery</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>VYABHICĀRA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Advaitācārya</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>At a time when the common masses of India were oppressed by the fanatical Muslim rulers on one side and the tyranny of the caste system on the other, the Bhakti Movement (the Hindu spiritual renaissance through bhakti or devotion to God) started and sustained by a galaxy of great spiritual leaders from Rāmānuja to Caitanya (11th to 16th centuries A. D.) came as a great saviour. One of the important predecessors and a senior contemporary of Caitanya was Advaitācārya (16th Century A. D.) also known as Advaita or Advaita Prabhu. Not much is known of him. He was a resident of Śāntipur and a disciple of Mādhavendra Purī. It was in his house that Caitanya met his mother Śacī Devī for the first time after taking to the monastic life, and decided to stay at Purī (Orissa) for the rest of his life in deference to her wish.</p>
			<p>Even before Viśvambhar—that is how Caitanya was known in his premonastic days—was acclaimed as a great devotee of Kṛṣṇa by the contemporary Vaiṣṇava leaders, Advaitācārya had had visions of him as an incarnation of Kṛṣṇa himself.</p>
			<p>According to the theology developed by the later Caitanya school, Advaitācārya was an aspect of Viṣṇu.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Advaita-siddhi</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;fulfilment of Advaita&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>If Hindu philosophical systems have grown both in width and depth revealing power and energy, it is not a little due to the freedom of thought enjoyed by the various writers. It was perhaps Śaṅkara (A. D. 788-820) the doyen of Advaita Vedānta who initiated and also gave a fillip to voluminous writing on abstruse philosophical subjects. Criticism, defence and counter-criticism of his views by sub- sequent writers gave rise to a phenomenal growth of Vedānta literature. When Vyāsa Tīrtha, a pontiff of the Mādhva school (15th-16th cent. A. D.) caused a jolt to Advaita metaphysics by his well-known polemical work <em>Nyāyāmṛta</em>, the Advaita tradition met his challenge through the <em>Advaitasiddhi</em>, the most celebrated work of Madhusūdana Sarasvatī (16th cent. A. D.).</p>
			<p>The point of dispute between the two works is the definition of what is true (satya) and what is false (mithyā). Any object is considered as satya (true, real) only as long as it is not bādhita (contradicted or negated) by subsequent experience. All the criticisms of <em>Nyāyāmṛta</em> against the five definitions of falsity given by the previous writers on Advaita have been met by the <em>Advaitasiddhi</em>. The book also discusses and supports many of the conflicting theories regarding the unity or plurality of the selves, unity or plurality of avidyā (nescience), Brahman or the jīva as the locus of avidyā thereby implying that any of the theories can be resorted to in explaining the indeterminable false world since the main interest of the advaitin is the one absolute Brahman. The different theories of Advaita can be adopted by the different aspirants according to their fitness (adhikāra).</p>
			<p>The work has three Sanskrit commen- taries of which <em>Laghucandrikā</em> of Brahmā-nanda Sarasvatī is popular among the scholars.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ADVAITA VEDĀNTA DARŚANA</ref>, <ref>MADHUSŪDANA SARASVATĪ</ref>, <ref>NYĀYĀMṚTA</ref> and <ref>VYĀSATĪRTHA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Advaita Vedānta Darśana</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;Non-dual Vedānta System&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<subhead>PREAMBLE</subhead>
			<p>Man is often described as a rational animal. Once the animal in him is reasonably satisfied by the provision of basic biological and some psychological needs, the rational part gets an opportunity to evolve to higher levels. Philosophy including metaphysics is one of the highest aspects of this evolution.</p>
			<subhead>DARŚANAS</subhead>
			<p>The Indian philosophical systems have developed not only as a result of intellectual speculation but also of mystical intuition. Hence the name &#x2018;darśana&#x2019; (lit., &#x2018;seeing&#x2019;), usually applied to them. The topics most commonly discussed by these darśanas are generally four:</p>
			<ul class="lower-alpha">
				<li>nature of the physical world, its origin and evolution;</li>
				<li>nature of man and other living beings;</li>
				<li>existence of God, his nature and attributes;</li>
				<li>the goal of human life and the way of attaining it.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Different standpoints and differing views of these topics of discussion have naturally led to a variety of schools. These schools are broadly divided into two classes: the āstika and the nāstika. The former accept the authority of the Vedas whereas the latter do not.</p>
			<subhead>VEDĀNTA DARŚANA</subhead>
			<p>The Vedānta Darśana is the last of the former schools but has gained the most important place among them. A judicious combination of reasoning and acceptance of the authority of the Vedas as also a long unbroken tradition are responsible for its gaining the pre-eminent place.</p>
			<p>Though the &#x2018;prasthānatraya&#x2019; (&#x2018;the three great paths&#x2019;) viz., the Upaniṣads, the <em>Brahmasūtras</em> and the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em>, are the basis of the Vedānta Darśana, it is the <em>Brahmasūtras</em> (also called <em>Vedānta-sūtras</em> and <em>Śārīrakasūtras</em>) of Bādarāyaṇa-Vyāsa that occupies the key position. The sūtras (aphorisms) being quite terse and often ambiguous have naturally led to widely differing interpretations, resulting in the three well-known systems of Vedānta viz., Advaita, Viśiṣṭādvaita and Dvaita.</p>
			<p>The word &#x2018;Vedānta&#x2019; itself means the &#x2018;end or the essence of the Vedas.&#x2019; It is the Upaniṣads that mainly comprise the Vedānta since they normally form the last part of the Vedic literature and contain the quintessence of their teachings.</p>
			<subhead>ADVAITA VEDĀNTA</subhead>
			<p>The Advaita Vedānta Darśana owes its systematisation as a formidable doctrine, to Gauḍapāda (7th-8th cent. A.D.) who wrote his famous Kārikās on the <em>Māṇḍūkyopaniṣad</em> and Śaṅkara (A. D. 788-820). Śaṅkara&#x2019;s commentaries on the prasthānatraya as also a few independent treatises form the bedrock on which the later Advaitins built their edifices.</p>
			<p>&#x2018;Advaita&#x2019; means &#x2018;non-dual&#x2019;, &#x2018;one without a second&#x2019;. The system derives this nomenclature from the fact that it recognises Brahman (the Absolute) as the only reality and denies permanent reality to the world as also to the individual souls.</p>
			<p>The entire edifice of Advaita metaphysics is built upon the foundation that Brahman is the only reality, &#x2018;brahma satyam&#x2019;. This premise is based firmly on the famous Upaniṣadic statement &#x2018;sadeva somya idamagra āsīt, ekamevādvitīyam.&#x2019; &#x2018;Dear (Śvetaketu), in the beginning (before creation) Reality (or Brahman) alone existed, the one without a second&#x2019; (<em>Chāndogya Upaniṣad</em> 6.2.1). However, the world of multiplicity is a matter of our day-to-day experience. Hence it becomes necessary to offer an explanation as to how Brahman, the one without a second, appears as this world of multiple names and forms. The explanation offered by Advaita is &#x2018;Anirvacanīyakhyāti,&#x2019; its theory of erroneous cognition, which defies logic. (For other theories about erroneous cognition see <ref>KHYĀTIS</ref>.) Perceiving silver in nacre in moonlight or snake in rope in insufficient light are stock examples given by the Advaitins. In both cases there is an erroneous perception brought about by the impressions of silver and snake from an earlier idea of the same, now superimposed upon nacre and rope under conditions favourable to the error. This superimposition called &#x2018;adhyāsa&#x2019; or &#x2018;adhyāropa&#x2019;, is responsible for the mithyājñāna (false knowledge) that the object perceived is silver or snake.</p>
			<p>The silver or the snake perceived is neither &#x2018;sat&#x2019; (real) nor &#x2018;asat&#x2019; (unreal). It is not asat or unreal like &#x2018;the son of a barren woman&#x2019; since it is actually perceived. Neither is it sat or real since it disappears as soon as the substratum (the nacre and the rope) is perceived as it is. To explain such a peculiar phenomenon Śaṅkara creates, out of logical necessity, a third type of perceived objects which is &#x2018;sad-asad-vilakṣaṇa&#x2019; (different from both the real and the unreal). The &#x2018;khyāti&#x2019; or the cognition itself is described as &#x2018;anirvacanīya,&#x2019; incapable of any precise definition or description.</p>
			<p>The basic cause of this erroneous perception is termed &#x2018;ajñāna&#x2019; or &#x2018;avidyā&#x2019; (ignorance) which is said to be bhāvarūpa (existent) and is endowed with two śaktis or powers viz., &#x2018;āvaraṇaśakti&#x2019; (veiling power) and &#x2018;vikṣepaśakti&#x2019; (transforming power). It veils the true nature of nacre and rope and shows up silver and snake in their place by apparently transforming them. Such an apparently transformed object is called a &#x2018;vivarta&#x2019; of the original and the theory that propounds this is known as &#x2018;Vivartavāda.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>Since this avidyā does not make the nacre and the rope completely disappear from view, but only makes them appear as something else, it is described as bhāvarūpa or existent.</p>
			<p>An attempt may now be made to explain how this world of duality has evolved out of the non-dual Reality called Brahman in the Upaniṣads. The world of duality can be broadly divided into &#x2018;dṛk&#x2019; (the seer) and &#x2018;dṛśya&#x2019; (the seen). Both these again are divided into the innumerable living beings (jīvās) and the countless objects of creation. How does Brahman the Absolute, the One without a second, the indivisible Reality, appear divided into innumerable beings on the one side and countless objects on the other? It is avidyā that causes the one Ātman (the Self)—incidentally, the Upaniṣads use both words, Ātman and Brahman, to indicate the same Reality—appear as many jīvas and it is māyā that causes the world of phenomena. Māyā is avidyā at the cosmic level.</p>
			<p>Śaṅkara accepts three degrees of reality. The first, known as &#x2018;prātibhāsika-satya&#x2019; (apparent truth, illusory appearance) is illustrated in the wrong perception of silver in nacre or snake in rope. The second, called &#x2018;vyāvahārika-satya&#x2019; is illustrated by this world of our day-to-day experience. This world-appearance has a much higher degree of reality and lasts till one gets ātmajñāna or brahmajñāna, realization of the Truth, Ātman-Brahman. It is satya or true for all purposes of vyavahāra i.e., day-to-day existence or practical life. The third, designated as &#x2018;pāramārthika-satya,&#x2019; is the highest Truth and the only truth that really exists. It is Brahman or Ātman, which is nirguṇa (without attributes) and nirākāra (without forms), hence incapable of being described except in a negative way (&#x2018;neti,&#x2019; &#x2018;neti&#x2019;—&#x2018;not this, not this&#x2019;).</p>
			<p>Brahman associated with māyā is Saguṇa Brahman (Brahman with attri-butes) or Īśvara (Lord of creation, God). It is this aspect of Brahman that is responsible for creation, preservation and destruction of the world. As for the actual order of evolution of the created world, the descriptions given in the Upaniṣads are accepted.</p>
			<p>For Śaṅkara who holds that the world process is only a &#x2018;vivarta&#x2019; (illusory appearance) due to adhyāsa (superimposition) on Brahman, the very attempt to describe the various steps of evolution is a futile exercise. However, since the śruti (revealed scripture, the Upaniṣads) has done so, a place of honour must somehow be accorded to it. Hence he characterises such descriptions as giving the &#x2018;taṭastha-lakṣaṇa&#x2019; (accidental or casual charac- teristics) of Brahman helping us to be directed towards it, even as the branch of a tree helps us to locate the crescent in the sky. On the other hand Brahman as it is, can be comprehended only through its &#x2018;svarūpalakṣaṇa&#x2019; (integral or essential characteristics), which is &#x2018;sat-cit-ānanda.&#x2019; &#x2018;Sat&#x2019; (eternal reality), &#x2018;cit&#x2019; (pure consciousness), and &#x2018;ānanda&#x2019; (unalloyed bliss) are not really its characteristics but its very essence.</p>
			<p>This Brahman or Ātman which is sat-cit-ānanda, has inexplicably got itself involved in the body-mind complex, the involvement being due to avidyā. Since the origin of this involvement can never be logically or satisfactorily explained, avidyā is stated to be anādi or beginningless. The involved ātman is designated as &#x2018;jīva.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>This jīva, the ātman in bondage, has five kośas or sheaths (For details see <ref>PAÑCAKOŚAS</ref>.), three śarīras or bodies (See <ref>STHŪLAŚARĪRA</ref>, <ref>SŪKṢMAŚARĪRA</ref> and <ref>KĀRAṆA-ŚARĪRA</ref>.), performs actions motivated by desires, experiences pleasure and pain due to karma and undergoes transmigration (See <ref>KARMA</ref> and <ref>PUNARJANMA</ref>.) until libera- tion. Śaṅkara declares that this jīva, when shorn of its upādhis or limiting adjuncts like the body and the mind, is identical with Brahman, since its essential nature also is sat-cit-ānanda.</p>
			<p>The main trouble with the ātman become jīva is the tādātmya or false identification with the mind and the body brought about by adhyāropa or adhyāsa (superimposition). Hence the only way of remedying it is by apavāda or desuper-imposition, denying this identification. For this, one has first to prepare oneself by the preliminary fourfold discipline or sādhana-catuṣṭaya viz., viveka (discrimination between the eternal and the non-eternal), vairāgya (dispassion), śamādi-ṣaṭka (cultivation of the six virtues like self-control) and mumukṣutva (desire for liberation). (For details see <ref>SĀDHANA-CATUṢṬAYA</ref>.) Then one has to approach a competent guru (spiritual preceptor) and learn the truth from him by śravaṇa (hearing), manana (reflection) and nidi-dhyāsana (contemplation). The most important part of the guru&#x2019;s teaching will be in the form of &#x2018;mahāvākyas&#x2019; (great sentences) like &#x2018;tat tvam asi&#x2019; (That thou art&#x2019;) or &#x2018;ahaṁ brahmāsmi&#x2019; (&#x2018;I am Brahman&#x2019;). (See <ref>MAHĀVĀKYAS</ref> for details.) Śravaṇa and manana produce the deep-rooted conviction that one is the spirit. Hence in nididhyāsana, desuperimposition in the form of &#x2018;I am not the body, nor the sense-organs, nor the mind, nor even the ego&#x2019; and so on, can be practised leading ultimately to the realization that one is the ātman. This realization resulting in mukti or liberation can be had even while one is living in this body. It is known as &#x2018;jīvanmukti.&#x2019; He will attain &#x2018;videhamukti&#x2019; after the body falls off, the continuance of the body between the two states being due to prārabdha-karma. (See <ref>PRĀRABDHA KARMA</ref>.)</p>
			<p>Mukti or liberation from transmigration is not the gaining of a new state but recognising the already existing original state.</p>
			<p>Two kinds of mukti—jīvanmukti and videhamukti—are envisaged in the Advaitic works. The Vivaraṇa school upholds the theory that mukti is simultaneous with jñāna. Hence jīvanmukti is not only possible, but the only mukti that can be recognised. Continuance of the body for some more time, due to prārabdha karma, has no effect upon jñāna. On the other hand, the Bhāmatī school holds that even after jñāna, if the body continues due to prārabdha karma, this imposes a limitation thereby implying the existence of a trace of avidyā. The death of the body puts an end even to this trace of avidyā, and real mukti is obtained then. Since this comes after the death of the body, it is called &#x2018;videhamukti.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>A favourite topic of discussion that frequently crops up in Advaita metaphysical works is the locus of avidyā. Since Brahman is the only reality that exists, it alone is the āśraya (locus) as also the viṣaya (object) of avidyā. This is one school. Sureśvara and Padmapāda are the main protagonists of this school. According to them avidyā is one only.</p>
			<p>Since Brahman is pure consciousness, avidyā can never exist in it nor act on it. This is the opposing school propagated by Vācaspati Miśra. For him, the jīvas are the loci of avidyā and there is one avidyā for every jīva.</p>
			<subhead>POST-ŚAṄKARA ADVAITA</subhead>
			<p>Though Śaṅkara wrote profusely, clearly enunciating the main doctrines of his school, there are certain places in his writings wherein the important aspects of certain doctrines are either vague or are capable of more than one interpretation. This has naturally, resulted in the growth of quite a voluminous post-Śaṅkara Advaita literature leading to different prasthānas or schools of thought. The &#x2018;Vārttika-prasthāna&#x2019; of Sureśvara (9th cent. A. D.) comes first in the series. This school gets its designation from the exposition contained in the &#x2018;vārttikās&#x2019; or commentaries in verse of Sureśvara on Śaṅkara&#x2019;s bhāṣyas on the <em>Bṛhadāraṇyaka</em> and the <em>Taittirīya</em> Upaniṣads. According to this school, Brahman is the material cause of this world, and not māyā. The locus of avidyā is Brahman and not the jīvas. Avidyā is one only and not many. The mahāvākyas or the great Vedic dictums are capable of producing immediate cognition of the Self as Brahman. Hence dhyānābhyāsa or practice of meditation on the meaning of those dictums is not necessary. The jīvas are but ābhāsas or appearances of Brahman in the individual minds. (This has earned the theory, the designation of &#x2018;ābhāsavāda&#x2019; as opposed to &#x2018;pratibimbavāda&#x2019; and &#x2018;avaccheda-vāda&#x2019; of other schools.)</p>
			<p>The &#x2018;Vivaraṇaprasthāna&#x2019; of Padma-pāda (9th cent. A. D.) and Prakāśātman (A. D. 1220) comes next. The name is derived from the work <em>Pañcapādikā- vivaraṇa</em> of the latter, it being a voluminous commentary on the <em>Pañcapādikā</em> of Padmapāda, which itself is a commentary on Śaṇkara&#x2019;s Brahmasūtra-bhāsya. Though this name suggests that it covers five pādas or sections of the <em>Brahmasūtras</em>, only the commentary on the first four sūtras is now available. The chief doctrines of this school are: Avidyā is a jaḍātmikā śakti (a force of material nature) and is the material cause of this world. It is bhāvarūpa, a positive entity but not real. Māyā, prakṛti, avyakta, avyākṛta, tamas, śakti etc., are all its synonyms. It is called avidyā when āvaraṇa power is predominant and māyā when vikṣepa power becomes dominant. Alternatively, it is māyā at the cosmic level and avidyā at the individual level. Avidyā rests on Brahman but acts on the jīvas. The jīvās are pratibimbas or reflections of Brahman in the antaḥkaraṇa (mind). The reflected images have no reality other than that of the original (bimba) brahman. This theory is called &#x2018;pratibimbavāda&#x2019; and contrasted with &#x2018;ābhāsavāda&#x2019;.</p>
			<p>The &#x2018;Bhāmatīprasthāna&#x2019; of Vācaspati Miśra (A. D. 840) is the third and the last of these major schools. <em>Bhāmatī</em> is his celebrated commentary on the Śāṅkara-bhāṣya of <em>Brahmasūtras</em>. This school is built round the <em>Bhāmatī</em> along with its subsidiary commentaries <em>Kalpataru</em> of Amalānanda (13th cent A. D.). and <em>Parimalā</em> of Appayya Dīkṣita (16th cent A. D.) The views of this school can be briefly summarised as follows: Brahman is the material cause of the world, not as the locus of avidyā but as the object of avidyās supported by the jīvas. Māyā is only an accessory cause. Avidyā cannot abide in Brahman. It abides in the jīvas and is plural since the jīvas are plural. Vācaspati advocates two varieties of avidyā: the mūlāvidyā or kāraṇāvidyā (primal nescience); the tūlāvidyā or kāryāvidyā (derivative nescience). It is the latter that is responsible for bhrama-saṁskāras or error impressions. Also, Vācaspati appears more inclined towards the &#x2018;avacchedavāda&#x2019; or the theory of limitation with regard to the appearance of the jīvas. Just as a pot limits the infinite sky in itself, avidyā of the individual limits Brahman and makes it appear like a jīva. Another point of importance in this school is that the mahāvākyas do not produce anubhava (immediate cognition). It is the mind seasoned by meditation that gives such experience.</p>
			<p>Mention may also be made here of &#x2018;dṛṣṭisṛṣṭi-vāda&#x2019; which advocates that the world is created simultaneously with its perceptions, and, &#x2018;ekajīvavāda,&#x2019; which propounds that there is only one jīva which is in bondage and when it gets liberation, everything else disappears. Prakāśānanda (15th-16th cent. A. D.) is the chief exponent of these schools.</p>
			<p>Advaita was subjected to continuous criticism by other Vedāntic schools as also the Buddhists and hence the growth of polemical literature became inevitable. Mention must be made of two most important works of this type: The <em>Khaṇḍana-khaṇḍa-khādya</em> of Śrīharṣa (12th cent. A.D.) and the <em>Advaitasiddhi</em> of Madhusūdana Sarasvatī (16th cent. A. D.).</p>
			<subhead>CONCLUSION</subhead>
			<p>It should be said to the credit of Advaita Vedānta that even now it is attracting the respectful attention from scholars of the highest calibre, both Eastern and Western.</p>
			<subhead>NOTE :</subhead>
			<p>The number of connected topics is too large to be mentioned separately for cross reference. The reader can look for them under the respective titles as he comes across them in this essay.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Advayatāraka Upaniṣad</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>It is a minor Upaniṣad belonging to the <em>Śukla Yajurveda</em> and classed among the &#x2018;Yoga-Upaniṣads,&#x2019; Upaniṣads that deal with yogic meditations and other processes. Except for the last part which is in verses (14 to 18), the whole Upaniṣad is in elegant prose.</p>
			<p>It has been called &#x2018;Advayatāraka&#x2019; since it deals with Brahman, the one without a second (&#x2018;advaya&#x2019;), which takes us beyond (&#x2018;tāraka&#x2019;) saṁsāra or transmigratory existence.</p>
			<p>The Upaniṣad begins with the statement that it has to be taught to one who is struggling to meditate upon Brahman, the Absolute, (&#x2018;yati,&#x2019; &#x2018;one who struggles&#x2019;) who has practised self-control (&#x2018;jitendriya&#x2019;) and who has cultivated the six virtues like peace (&#x2018;śamādiṣaṭka&#x2019;). Then it describes that one who meditates upon light in between the eyebrows as Brahman attains to It. After negating the difference between the jīvātman (individual self) and Īśvara (Supreme Soul) as brought about by the limiting adjuncts like māyā, it goes on to describe a yogic meditation for attaining Brahman, the Absolute.</p>
			<p>The suṣumnā-nāḍī (a tube-like structure meant for the passage of the kuṇḍalinī) (See <ref>KUṆḌALINĪ</ref>.) is situated in the middle of the body, stretching from the mulādhāra plexus at the root of the spinal column, up to the brahmarandhra or the aperture in the crown of the head. It shines like the sun or the moon. The Kuṇḍalinī which is fine like the thread in the lotus stalk, is inside this suṣumnā and is shining like millions of lightnings. By closing the ears and meditating on the sound within and the blue light within, between the eyes, and witnessing it, one gets infinite happiness. This is meditation on the &#x2018;inside.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>The Upaniṣad then proceeds to describe the process of meditation on two points, &#x2018;outside&#x2019; and &#x2018;in between&#x2019; the &#x2018;inside&#x2019; and the &#x2018;outside.&#x2019; The first consists in fixing the gaze and the mind at any point in front of the nose, 4, 6, 8, 10 or 12 aṅgulas (an aṅgula is roughly about an inch) in distance, seeing it as of blue-yellow colour. The latter consists of meditating on the &#x2018;ākāśa&#x2019; or ether/space, near the tip of the nose but beyond it, and as being bright like the full sun of the morning or fire with leaping tongues. In both cases this light becomes a symbol for Brahman.</p>
			<p>Then comes the description of &#x2018;tārakayoga,&#x2019; meditation on the light in the head, by reversing the mental light into the area between the eye brows, inside the head but towards the crown. Such meditation can give the supernatural &#x2018;aṣṭasiddhis&#x2019; or &#x2018;eight powers.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>Last comes the Śāmbhavīmudrā. It is the same as meditation already described, but, with the eyes without being closed or opened.</p>
			<p>The Upaniṣad ends with a description of the qualifications of the guru fit to teach such yoga.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ŚĀMBHAVĪMUDRĀ</ref> and <ref>UPA-NIṢADS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Āgamanī</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;welcome&#x2019; [songs])</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Śrī Durgāpūjā is one of the major festivals of the Hindus celebrated on a grand scale in Bengal, Orissa, Bihar and Assam. Beautiful clay images are ceremonially installed during the period of nine days (1st to 9th in the month of Āśvina, śuklapakṣa or bright half) (October) and elaborate worship performed. &#x2018;Āgamanī&#x2019; is the name given to a particular type of songs generally sung on this occasion as part of the &#x2018;Kālīkīrtan&#x2019; programmes.</p>
			<p>Śrī Durgā is actually Pārvatī or Umā, the beloved daughter of queen Menā and king Girirāja (the king of Himālayas), given in marriage to Lord Śiva. It is long since the daughter has visited the house of her parents. The parents, especially the mother Menā, are anxious about her welfare since rumours have reached their ears that their daughter is languishing in her husband&#x2019;s house owing to his poverty and queer ways of life. The Āgamanī songs depict their concern and anxiety for their daughter and anger towards their son-in-law. They are full of tenderness of the mother&#x2019;s love for the daughter. Solicitude for the welfare of Umā, disgust with Śiva&#x2019;s way of life—especially his living in the cremation grounds, besmearing his body with ashes and begging his food—consequent anger expressing itself in a resolve not to send her back to her husband&#x2019;s house and even a grim determination to fight a wordy duel with him if he presses for her return—these are some of the sentiments frequently found in these songs. Rāmprasād, Kamalākānta and Dāśarathi are some of the well-known mystic poets who have composed these songs.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Āgamānta Śaivism</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>PĀŚUPATA DARŚANA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āgamas</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;sacred books which teach the Truth from all aspects&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Āgamas are a certain class of Hindu religious literature which practically form the basis of Hindu religious practices of the post-Vedic era. Literally, the word means &#x2018;that which teaches Truth from all aspects,&#x2019; <em>ā samantāt gamayati</em>, and hence can denote the Vedas, or for that matter, any sacred book. But in practice it is used in a more restricted sense to indicate the above-mentioned class of literature.</p>
			<p>Though the āgamas are definitely post-Vedic since they deal elaborately with the deities Śiva, Śakti and Viṣṇu, their temples and rituals, it is rather difficult to fix their chronological origin and development. It can be definitely stated that some of the āgamas devoted to the cult of Viṣṇu were already in existence by the time of the <em>Mahābhārata.</em> The development of various āgamas might have continued till the 8th cent. A. D.</p>
			<p>A typical āgama is generally divided into four parts known as &#x2018;pādas.&#x2019; In the Vidyāpāda or Jñānapāda philosophical and metaphysical subjects are discussed. In the Yogapāda details of yogic practices required to purify the body and mind are given. In the Kriyāpāda, which is usually voluminous, temple architecture and iconography are dealt with. In the Caryāpāda, the details of spiritual sacraments as also the code of conduct expected of a novice are delineated.</p>
			<p>According to the deity propitiated, the āgamas are divided into three broad groups: Śaivāgamas, Śāktāgamas and Vaiṣṇavāgamas. The twenty eight Āgamas starting with <em>Kāmikāgama</em> and ending with <em>Vātulāgama</em> comprise the Śaivā- gamas. According to them, Śiva the Supreme God is &#x2018;pati&#x2019; (the Lord), the jīvas or individual souls are &#x2018;paśu&#x2019; (animal in bondage) and the three kinds of malas or impurities (āṇavamala, kārmikamala and māyāmala) comprise the &#x2018;pāśa&#x2019; (rope) by which the jīvas are bound. It is by the grace of Śiva, the Paśupati, that the paśus are able to get rid of their pāśas and get mokṣa or liberation.</p>
			<p>The Śāktāgamas, also known as tantras, are legion in number. They follow the Śaivāgamas very closely, the only exception being that Śakti or Devī (Power or consort of Śiva) gets the supreme place. The tāntric discipline has become divided into dakṣiṇācāra (the right-hand path), also known as &#x2018;samaya,&#x2019; and vāmācāra (the left-hand path), also called &#x2018;kaula.&#x2019; The former conforms to the decent and accepted norms of spiritual practice whereas the latter seems to advocate the theory that even aberrations can be sublimated to the level of the spiritual practice resulting in the experience of the same supreme Truth.</p>
			<p>The Vaiṣṇavāgamas, also called Saṁhitās, are divided into the <em>Vaikhānasa</em> and the <em>Pāñcarātra</em> schools. Both teach that Viṣṇu is the highest Truth and stress the importance of worship in temples.</p>
			<p>Jainism also has its āgamas written in the Ardhamāgadhi language, and is divided into two: Śrutāṅgas and Upāṅgas.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>DAKṢIṆĀCĀRA</ref>, <ref>KAULA-MĀRGA</ref>, <ref>PĀÑCARĀTRĀGAMAS</ref>, <ref>ŚAIVĀGAMAS</ref>, <ref>ŚĀKTĀ- GAMAS</ref>, <ref>SAMAYAMATA</ref>, <ref>TANTRAS</ref>, <ref>VAIKHĀ-NASĀGAMA</ref> and <ref>VĀMĀCĀRA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āgāmī-karma</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the future karma&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Belief in karma and punarjanma (reincarnation) is one of the fundamental dogmas of Hinduism, Jainism, Buddhism and Sikhism. Karma or action, good or bad, must have its effect. Āgāmī-karma is the karma that is being done now or that will be done in future (before death) which will produce its results later.</p>
			<p>For details see <ref>KARMA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Agastya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;One who stunted the growth of the mountain Vindhya&#x2019;)</note>
			<image>Agastya.png</image>
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Agastya is one of the most famous ṛṣis (sages or seers) frequently met with in Hindu religious lore. He is the seer of several Ṛgvedic mantras (<em>Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 1.166 to 191). He is a brahmarṣi, the son of Pulastya and Havirbhuk. Sage Agniveśya is his disciple.</p>
			<p>According to another version he was the son of Mitra and Varuṇa, and was born in a kumbha or jar. Hence the names Kumbhaja, Kumbhodbhava, Kalaśīsuta and so on. Vasiṣṭha was his brother. He married Lopāmudrā (also known as Kāverī), the princess of Vidarbha and begot a son Dṛḍhāsya, also known as Idhmavāha. A man of vast knowledge and severe austerity he is said to have destroyed the demons Ilvala and Vātāpi, stunted the growth of the Vindhya mountain which was growing recklessly, obstructing the light of the sun, drunk the waters of the ocean to expose the demons Kālakeyas who were killed by the gods, to have been honoured by Rāma when he was living in the Daṇḍakāraṇya and to whom he gave divine weapons and also taught the <em>Ādityahṛdaya</em>-hymn later and brought about reconciliation between Indra and the Maruts.</p>
			<p>Though Agastya is not enumerated among the Saptarṣis (the seven great sages), he is included among the progenitors of &#x2018;gotra&#x2019; geneology. He has been accorded a stellar status and identified with Canopus, the brightest star in the sky of southern India.</p>
			<p>In the annals of Tamil religious lore and literature, Agastya is the accredited originator of the Tamil language, the author of the maiden grammar of that language and the first president of the first organization of Tamil litterateurs. He is also credited with the authorship of several works on medicine, mysticism and magic. One work called <em>Agastya Saṁhitā</em> which deals with ritualistic worship is available. It is part of Pāñcarātra literature. He is said to have visited several South East Asian countries like Borneo, Siam and Cambodia.</p>
			<p>The word &#x2018;Agastya&#x2019; might have been a title. Several Agastyas may have been involved in these stories, syncretised into one.</p>
			<p>An Agastyāśrama, a hermitage of Agastya, has been mentioned in the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em>. This has been sometimes identified with Agastyapurī, east of Nasik in Maharashtra state.</p>
			<p>The <em>Vanaparva</em> of <em>Mahābhārata</em> (88.13) mentions an Agastyatīrtha in the Pāṇḍya country as an important place of pilgrimage.</p>
			<p>Seeing the star Agastya or Canopus when the sun is in the middle of Kanyā or Virgo and worshipping him at night is mentioned as a vrata (religious rite).</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ĀDITYAHṚDAYA</ref>, <ref>GOTRA</ref> and <ref>LOPĀMUDRĀ</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>aghamarṣaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;destroyer of sins&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Every religion has its rituals. We have plenty of them in Hinduism. Sandhyā or sandhyākarma or sandhyāvandana is a fundamental Vedic ritual obligatory on all the dvijas (the &#x2018;twice born,&#x2019; viz., the brāhmaṇas, the kṣattriyas and the vaiśyas). It is essentially an upāsanā (meditation, spiritual practice) and has several steps designed to elevate the mind to levels of meditation and mysticism. Aghamarṣaṇa is one such step in the process. It consists of taking a few drops of water in the right hand shaped like the gokarṇa (the ear of a cow), holding it near the nose and breathing out from the nose on the water (with the idea of driving away sin from oneself) to the accompaniment of the three Ṛgvedic verses beginning with &#x2018;ṛtaṁ ca&#x2019; (<em>vide</em> <em>Ṛgveda Saṁhitā</em> 10.190. 1-3), and throwing away the water to one&#x2019;s left on the ground. Though the subject matter of these mantras is creation and the Creator, the mantras themselves are reputed to be &#x2018;aghamarṣana&#x2019; or sin-effacing. These mantras can also be repeated during bath and as an expiation of sins.</p>
			<p>The mantras beginning with &#x2018;hiraṇya-śṛṅgaṁ varuṇaṁ prapadye&#x2019; and ending with &#x2018;ākrāntsamudraḥ&#x2019; which form part of the <em>Mahānārāyaṇa Upaniṣad</em> (55-70) are known as <em>Aghamarṣaṇasūkta</em>. The three ṛks of the aghamarṣaṇa ritual (&#x2018;ṛtaṁ ca&#x2019;) are also included in this. This <em>Aghamarṣaṇasūkta</em> is normally recited while taking bath in ponds or rivers. It is accredited with the power of destroying all sins, whether ordinary ones like the one incurred by eating the food given by evil ones or heinous ones like committing adultery and murder of the embryo.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Aghamarṣaṇasūkta</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the hymn that destroys sins&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>It is natural for human beings to commit sins, either knowingly or unknowingly. Very often they realise their mistakes and even repent for them. As knowers of human psychology, the ṛṣis (sages) of yore have prescribed certain religio-spiritual rituals that help in the eradication of sins.</p>
			<p>The <em>Aghamarṣaṇasūkta</em> is one such Vedic hymn (of prayer) prescribed for this purpose.</p>
			<p>It forms an integral part of the <em>Mahānārāyaṇa Upaniṣad</em> (Anuvāka 1, mantras 55-70).</p>
			<p>Water is a great purifying agent and should therefore be considered as an aspect of the Divine. Varuṇa is the presiding deity of water.</p>
			<p>This sūkta has to be chanted before taking bath in a river or lake or tank.</p>
			<p>The gist of the whole sūkta can be stated as follows:</p>
			<p>I take refuge in Varuṇa. Pardon me for having accepted gifts from unworthy persons.</p>
			<p>May Indra, Varuṇa, Bṛhaspati and Savitā destroy the sins committed by me. My salutations to them.</p>
			<p>Through the power of this mantra, let all the impurities in this water (where I am to bathe now) be destroyed. May Varuṇa purify me.</p>
			<p>I invite the seven sacred rivers—Gaṅgā, Yamunā, Sarasvatī, Godāvarī, Narmadā, Sindhū and Kaverī—to be present here in this water.</p>
			<p>May Varuṇa, capable of effacing all sins, purify all the beings dwelling on the earth, in the atmospheric region and in heaven. Similarly may the Vasus also purify us.</p>
			<p>I am the Supreme Light which projected itself as the universe. I am the same light that shines as the inmost essence of all that exists.</p>
			<p>Varuṇa, the regent of waters and effacer of sins, absolves the sinners of all types.</p>
			<p>Though I am the ground of sins and am made to weep, wise men can favour me by destroying my sins.</p>
			<p>The Supreme Lord is infinite like the limitless ocean. He dwells in the hearts of devotees. He delights the individual souls by guiding them and offering the fruits of their action.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Aghamarṣaṇa-vrata</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;a religious rite [prescribed for] destroying sins&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>No man, however careful, can avoid sins of omission and commission in life. Recognizing this fact, the Hindu dharma-śāstras have provided for prāyaścittas (expiations) by performing which, these sins can be obviated, or at least, their effects can be minimised. Aghamarṣaṇa-vrata is such a prāyaścitta prescribed by even the most ancient dharmaśāstra works like those of Gautama, Baudhāyana, Manu and Yājñavalkya, as an omnibus penance for all types of sins.</p>
			<p>The person performing it must fast for three days, recite the <em>Aghamarṣaṇa-sūkta</em> three times every day at the time of bath, standing in the water of a river or tank or pond, spend the days standing and nights, sitting. At the end of the vrata he should gift a milch-cow. This penance is said to be equal in sanctification to the avabhṛthasnāna (ceremonial bath) taken at the end of an Aśvamedha sacrifice.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>AGHAMARṢAṆASŪKTA</ref> (under <ref>AGHAMARṢAṆA</ref>), <ref>PĀPA</ref> and <ref>PRĀYAŚCITTA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>aghodaka</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;water libation during the period of impurity&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Belief in the survival of the soul after death and the need to bring peace to the soul in a spirit body through appropriate obsequial rites are common to many religions. Hinduism goes to the extent of considering antyeṣṭi or death-rites to be performed immediately after the death of a person, a &#x2018;saṁskāra,&#x2019; a rite that purifies and uplifts the soul. As part of this ceremony, water libation (udaka) is offered for the benefit of the deceased during the period of ceremonial impurity (agha). There are differences of opinion among the dharmaśāstra writers with regard to the number and duration of these water libations.</p>
			<p>A near relative (called sapiṇḍa) of the deceased, should take water mixed with sesame in the añjali (joined palms) and offer it facing south, with appropriate mantras. It should be offered thrice a day for eleven days from the day of death.</p>
			<p>&#x2018;Udakakriyā&#x2019; and &#x2018;udakadāna&#x2019; are the other names used for this rite.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ANTYEṢṬI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Aghora</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;not terrible&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Śiva is a deity of the Hindu Trinity and is responsible for the laya or pralaya, dissolution, of the universe. One of the names, by which he is well-known, is Pañcānana or Pañcamukha, &#x2018;the five faced one&#x2019;. These five faces are actually five aspects of his manifestation. &#x2018;Aghora&#x2019; is one of these five. Facing south and ruling over the element agni (fire), Aghora stands for the power that absorbs and renovates the universe.</p>
			<p>Iconographically, he is shown with a terrific face and eight hands holding śūla (spear), ḍamaru (drum), pāśa (noose), kapāla (skull-cup), daṇḍa (staff), cāpa (bow), bāṇa (arrow) and asi (sword). The neck is blue and the rest of the body is black. The body is either naked or clad in the hides of elephant and lion. Snakes and scorpions form the ornaments.</p>
			<p>Since his terrible form frightens away all the sufferings of his devotees, who have taken refuge in him, he is &#x2018;Aghora,&#x2019; the &#x2018;not terrible&#x2019; to them.</p>
			<p>The mantra beginning with the words &#x2018;aghorebhyo&#x2019; in the <em>Mahānārāyaṇa Upaniṣad</em> (19.1) is known as &#x2018;aghora- mantra&#x2019; and is one of the five mantras well-known as &#x2018;pañcabrahma-mantras&#x2019; employed in the worship and meditation of Mahādeva Śiva visualised as having five faces.</p>
			<p>These mantras are normally prescribed for japa to a person who desires divine illumination.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Aghora-panthī</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;a follower of Aghori school [of Śaivism]&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Aghorapanthis are the ascetics of a queer Śaiva order, who worship Śiva as &#x2018;aghora&#x2019; (&#x2018;the non-terrible&#x2019;). The origin of this sect which revels in abominable practices like cannibalism, eating from a human skull, besmearing with ashes from funeral pyres and a generous helping of spirituous liquors, is rather obscure. May be, they represent the remnants of some aboriginal non-Āryan religious cults which were absorbed into Hinduism in course of time. The few surviving members of the sect are to be found mostly in Bihar, Bengal, Rajasthan and Assam. Owing to the natural abhorrence of people towards such sects, their number has fast dwindled.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>KĀPĀLIKAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Aghora Śivācārya</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Śaivism is a very ancient branch of Hindu religion. Rooted in the Vedas and āgamas, it has been developed into a formidable religio-philosophical system by a galaxy of mystics and writers. An important teacher often quoted especially by the Vīraśaiva writers is Aghora Śivācārya, a pontiff of the Āmardaka monastery at Cidambaram (Tamil Nadu) who probably lived in the 11th-12th cent. A. D. <em>Tattva-prakāśa</em> of king Bhoja of Dhārā is said to be a fundamental work on Śaivism. Aghora Śivācārya is reputed to have written a detailed commentary on this work, refuting the highly monistic interpretations of an earlier commentator Śrīkumāra. Another work usually attribu-ted to him is <em>Mṛgendrāgama-vṛtti-dipikā</em>, a commentary on the famous Śaivāgama, <em>Mṛgendrāgama</em>. He is credited with the authorship of several other works also like <em>Aghora-śivapaddhati, Tattvasaṅgraha, Mahotsavanidhi</em> and so on.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnaukaraṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;making one with fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Pārvaṇaśrāddha is an important rite performed during &#x2018;parvans&#x2019; i.e., amāvāsyās or new moon days with a view to propitiating the departed forefathers, up to the third generation. On such days, worthy brāhmaṇas are invited for dinner. A portion of the food prepared for the same is taken out in a vessel and seven āhutis or libations are cast into the homa fire with seven appropriate mantras. Two offerings each are made for the father, the grand-father and the great-grand- father and one for all the other pitṛs (forefathers) combined. This rite is known as agnaukaraṇa.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PĀRVAṆAŚRĀDDHA</ref> and <ref>ŚRĀDDHA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āgneya-kṛcchra</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>(&#x2018;kṛcchra connected with Agni&#x2019;)</p>
			<p>Sins of omission and commission are inevitable in the life of a man however careful he may be. The law of karma being inexorable he is obliged to suffer their consequences. But none wants to suffer, and if given the chance to escape, will try for the same. With the full understanding of human nature and with a view to giving a chance for redemption to those who genuinely repent, the Hindu dharma-śāstras have devised elaborate prāyaścittas or expiations for sins. Kṛcchra—literally &#x2018;that which causes suffering&#x2019;—is a general word used for several penances out of which āgneya-kṛcchra is a variety. The main part of the discipline in this expiation is that the person performing it should subsist only on sesame (tila) for twelve days. Agni will be pleased by it and all the difficulties of the performer will be removed.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āgneyī-dhāraṇā</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;fixing the mind on the fire principle&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Conquest of self gives mastery over the whole world. Conquest of the mind leads to the conquest of the self. Works on yoga portray the various age-old techniques for controlling the mind. Pañca-dhāraṇās, five kinds of fixing the mind on prescribed subtle principles, is one such method described in a well-known work on Haṭhayoga viz., <em>Gheraṇḍa Saṁhitā</em>.</p>
			<p>The fire principle is situated at the navel, in the form of a red effulgent triangle. Its presiding deity is Rudra. Fixing the prāṇa along with the mind on this fire principle at the navel for a period of five ghaṭis (i.e., 2 hours) is known as &#x2018;āgneyī-dhāraṇā.&#x2019; Destruction of the fear of death is the result achieved.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Agni</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image>Agni.png</image>
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>According to the Hindu scriptures, every elemental force is presided over by a deity. The presiding deity of tejas, fire and heat, is Agni.</p>
			<p>The religion of the Vedas being mainly centred round sacrificial rites, Agni the god of fire naturally gets the pride of place in the Vedic hymns. A large number of them are devoted to describing and praising him. He is often eulogised as the Supreme God, the creator, the sustainer and the all-pervading cosmic spirit. All the other gods are his different manifestations. He manifests himself as fire (agni) on this earth, as lightning and air (Indra and Vāyu) in the sky and as the sun (Sūrya) in the heavens. He acts as a mediator between men and gods by carrying the sacrificial offerings of men to gods. He is all-knowing and all-powerful. He is all-merciful too. Though an immortal he lives among the mortals, in every house. He protects them by dispelling their difficulties and fulfils their wishes. Without him, the world can never sustain itself.</p>
			<p>In the epics and the purāṇas he is said to have been born out of the face of the Virāṭ Puruṣa (Cosmic Being), married Svāhā, the daughter of Dakṣa, consumed the Khāṇḍava forest with the help of Arjuna whom he rewarded with gifts of divine weapons like the bow Gāṇḍīva, helped Indra to be relieved of a part of his sin of brahmahatyā (killing a brāhmaṇa) and restored Sītā to Rāma after she had entered the fire to prove her chastity.</p>
			<p>Iconographically, Agni is represented as an old man with a red body. He has two heads, a big belly and six eyes, seven arms in which he holds objects like the spoon, ladle, fan etc., seven tongues, four horns and three legs. He has braided hair, wears red garments as also the yajñopa-vīta (sacred thread). He is attended on either side by his two consorts, Svāhā and Svadhā. The smoke is his banner and the ram his mount. Obviously this is an anthropomorphic representation of the sacrificial fire.</p>
			<p>As sacrificial fire, Agni has five aspects known as Pañcāgni: gārhapatya, āhavanīya, dakṣiṇā (or anvāhāryapacana), sabhya and āvasathya.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PAÑCĀGNI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnicayana</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;piling the fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>According to the ancient Hindu reli-gious texts like the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> (3.10, 11) Prajāpati (the Creator) gave the yajña (system of sacrifices) as the link between the human beings and the deities (devas) of the cosmic regions. Human beings were advised to propitiate these deities through various yajñas and the deities in turn would respond by bestowing upon them their needs.</p>
			<p>Vedic sacrifices which were simple fire rituals during the Saṁhitā period were gradually developed, by the period of the Brāhmaṇas, into a bewildering variety of rites and ceremonies with a labyrinth of details. One of the complicated sacrifices is the Somayāga of which agnicayana forms an integral part. However this rite is not compulsory even in Somayāga. Literally the word means &#x2018;piling the fire&#x2019; but in practice it refers to the rite of building up the altar on which the sacrificial fire (āhavanīya) will be lighted.</p>
			<p>The <em>Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa</em> (kāṇḍas 6 to 10) of the <em>Śukla Yajurveda</em>, which is the basic authority on this rite, represents it as a human imitation of the construction of the cosmic world of Prajāpati.</p>
			<p>Detailed instructions are given for the manufacture of the various kinds of bricks, of different shapes and sizes, and for the building up of the altar in several layers and of prescribed shapes. The most common shapes are those of suparṇa (eagle), śyena (hawk) and droṇa (trough). As many as 10,800 bricks are needed to complete the construction of the altar. A thorough knowledge of geometry is necessary on the part of the priests who guide and direct the construction. The bricks are usually laid in five layers, the 1st, the 3rd and the 5th being of the same pattern while the 2nd and 4th are different.</p>
			<p>Measuring the ground on which the altar is built, ploughing and sowing it with several seeds, interring the heads of five animals or their golden images and the golden image of the sacrificer as also a living tortoise into the altar that is being built are some of the details mentioned in the liturgical works.</p>
			<p>The piling of the altar could be completed in one year (8 months for the first four layers and 4 months for the last) or only in five consecutive days.</p>
			<p>The &#x2018;Agnicit,&#x2019; i.e., the person who performs agnicayana, is expected to observe certain vows during this period. He is permitted to do &#x2018;punaściti&#x2019; (doing agnicayana once again) if he does not prosper in the year after performing it.</p>
			<p>To obviate the effects of the sins of omission and commission during the agnicayana rite, several prāyaścittas (expiations) are prescribed.</p>
			<p>The esoteric doctrine of agnicayana is said to have originated with Prajāpati himself and come down through a succession of teachers from Tura Kāvaṣeya to Śāṇḍilya.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>SOMAYĀGA</ref> and <ref>VEDIC SACRIFICES</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āgnīdhra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;one who kindles the fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>No Vedic sacrifice can be conducted without the help and guidance of priests. Liturgical works on sacrifices enumerate four chief priests—hotṛ, adhvaryu, udgātṛ and brahmā—each of whom is assisted by a maximum of three more. Āgnīdhra, also called āgnīdh, is an important priest who is the assistant of brahmā but has much to do with the adhvaryu also. As the very name indicates, he is the person who lights the sacrificial fire and tends it. It is also his responsibility to ensure its proper distribution among the various vedis (altars). Apart from this, his chief function is to respond to the āśravaṇa-call of the adhvaryu with words such as &#x2018;astu śrauṣaṭ.&#x2019; He is also given the duty of seeing that everything is in order before invoking the deities. As an insignia of this authority, he holds the wooden sword called sphya.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>ṚTVIKS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Agnihotra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;in which libations are poured into agni&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Yajña or sacrifice links the human beings with divine beings. When these divinities or devatās are propitiated through yajñas, they reward the performers with whatever they desire for (<em>vide Bhagavadgītā</em> 3.10-12).</p>
			<p>These yajñas may be nitya (obligatory, performed daily), naimittika (occasional) or kāmya (motivated). Again, depending upon the materials used they may be classified as pāka-yajña, havir- yajña and somayāga. If cooked food is offered in pākayajña and soma juice in somayāgas, milk and ghee are the materials normally used in haviryajña.</p>
			<p>Agnihotra is one of the most common and important sacrifices which is classed among the haviryajñas and considered to be nitya.</p>
			<p>It is performed more as a daily worship than for the fulfilment of any specific desire. It should be started from the very evening of the day on which agnyādhāna (establishing the Vedic fire ceremonially) is done. It is obligatory to perform it daily till death or old-age or saṁnyāsa. All the dvijas (the &#x2018;twice-born,&#x2019; the men of the first three varṇas) are entitled to its performance. It must be done twice daily at dawn and dusk, along with the wife. Wife, son or pupil can perform it on his behalf in emergencies.</p>
			<p>The main part of the rite consists in heating and offering cow&#x2019;s milk in a ladle into the gārhapatya fire with appropriate mantras. Sūrya (sun) and Prajāpati are the deities to whom offerings are made in morning and Agni and Prajāpati, in the evening.</p>
			<p>Instead of with milk, the rite may be performed with gruel, cooked rice, ghee or curds when specific fruits or results are desired for.</p>
			<p>The performer of Agnihotra is obliged to rear a cow. The milk vessel which must be an earthen pot with a straight brim is called &#x2018;agnihotra-sthālī&#x2019; and the ladle &#x2018;agnihotrahavaṇī.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>If and when the yajamāna (performer of the sacrifice) goes on a pilgrimage along with his wife, he can carry the gārhapatya fire with him or can ceremonially put it out and perform punarādhāna (re-establishing the fire) on his return.</p>
			<p>When he dies, the various wooden implements used by him for Agnihotra should be kept on various parts of his body as prescribed and the body cremated with the gārhapatya fire.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>HAVIRYAJÑA</ref> and <ref>YAJÑA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnikṣetra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;site of fire)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>In Vedic sacrifices called Somayāga the adhvaryu (the chief and active priest) builds a &#x2018;mahāvedi&#x2019; (&#x2018;the great altar&#x2019;) on the eastern side of which the agnikṣetra, the site of fire, is constructed in the form of a śyena (hawk). Taking the sacrificer&#x2019;s height as the measuring unit, the agnikṣetra is to be 4 units in length and 3 units in breadth. However, in certain cases like the Aśvamedha sacrifice, this size can be doubled or even trebled.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>MAHĀVEDI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agniprākāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;wall of fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Ritualistic worship gives a concrete shape to abstract philosophical principles and basic convictions born out of them. Also, it elevates the mind of the worshipper to higher levels of spiritual experience and provides emotional satisfaction.</p>
			<p>Several steps are prescribed in the process of worship. Some of these are just preliminaries which help in preparing the mind of the worshipper. &#x2018;Agniprākāra&#x2019; is one such in which an imaginary wall of fire is erected round the worshipper by drawing three lines in the air about him with the right index finger or by sprinkling water all round. This is done with the recital of mantras like &#x2018;raṁ&#x2019; or &#x2018;sahasrāra huṁ phaṭ.&#x2019; This wall of fire is believed to act like a fort preventing evil spirits or passions from attacking the worshipper.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PŪJĀ</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Agnipurāṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Popular Hinduism is firmly based on the purāṇas. They have played an un- enviable part in preserving Hindu religion and culture, especially among the masses. The original stuff of the purāṇas is as old as the Vedas though the extant purāṇas are later productions showing unmistakable signs of compilation, evolution or even manipulation. Some scholars feel that the purāṇas contain much historical material also.</p>
			<p>Purāṇas are narratives of ancient events, &#x2018;purā bhavaṁ purāṇam&#x2019;. Though a purāṇa is said to have pañcalakṣaṇas (five characteristics) like the accounts of creation, dissolution, and geneology of kings, rarely do the purāṇas conform to this pattern. They are practically encyclopaedic in character dealing with every topic under the sun.</p>
			<p>Tradition ascribes the authorship of all the purāṇas to Vedavyāsa and divides them into two groups of Mahāpurāṇas (the great or the major ones) and the Upapurāṇas, (the small or the minor ones) each containing 18 works. <em>Agnipurāṇa</em> is usually classed as the eighth among the Mahāpurāṇas.</p>
			<p>Whether the extant <em>Agnipurāṇa</em>, now available in print, is the original or a purāṇa by name <em>Vahnipurāṇa</em> (vahni agni) whose manuscript has been discovered, is the original, has been a subject of scholarly disputation. Though scholars like Prof. R. C. Hazra are inclined to accord the latter, the status of the genuine or original purāṇa, it has gone into oblivion for the obvious reason that the former has met the needs of the people to a much greater extent.</p>
			<p>This <em>Agnipurāṇa</em> might have taken the present shape during the period A. D. 700-1100. It contains nearly 12,000 verses spread over 383 chapters. It is obviously a Vaiṣṇava work of an all comprehensive character containing almost everything of general interest.</p>
			<p>The following are some of the topics dealt with in this work: incarnations of God, creation, worship of Lord Viṣṇu and Agni, initiation, methods of building a temple, characteristics of śālagrāma stones and their worship, consecration of the deity in a newly built temple, greatness of places of pilgrimage and holy rivers like Gaṅgā, descriptions of the various worlds, amulets, mystic formulae, medicines, duties of men of the various āśramas (stages of life), expiations for sins, descriptions of hells, sandhyā ritual and Gāyatrī, consecration of a king and his duties, characteristics of precious stones, the science of archery, prosody, literature and greatness of this purāṇa.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PURĀṆAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnisāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;the essence of fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Works on Haṭhayoga like <em>Gheraṇḍa Saṁhitā</em> describe &#x2018;Ṣaṭkarmas&#x2019; or six purifi- catory techniques for cleansing the body. &#x2018;Dhauti&#x2019; the first of these is of four kinds: antardhauti, dantadhauti, hṛd-dhauti and mūlaśodhana. Antardhauti, the first of these is again of four varieties, viz., vātasāra, vārisāra, vāhnisāra or agnisāra, and bahiṣkṛta.</p>
			<p>Agni or vahni represents the &#x2018;fire&#x2019; of the digestive system (often called jāṭharāgni or vaiśvānarāgni), the capacity of digestion and assimilation. The health and strength of the body depends on the proper functioning of the digestive system. Agnisāra-dhauti is prescribed for the removal of functional disorders and even organic defects of this system.</p>
			<p>The process consists in &#x2018;pressing the navel knot a hundred times against the spinal cord&#x2019; by breathing out and contracting the abdominal muscles. This is said to result in the body acquiring a divine lustre and vital energy.</p>
			<p>As in all other Haṭhayogic exercises, this also should be practised under the direct guidance of a guru.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>DHAUTI</ref> and <ref>ṢAṬKARMAS</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnīṣoma-praṇayana</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;leading agni and soma&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Of all the Vedic sacrifices, Somayāga is, perhaps, one of the most complicated. A separate altar called mahāvedi is to be erected for the conduct of the Soma group of sacrifices. Since the yajamāna or sacrificer has already a vihāra (an old and permanent shed containing the three fires gārhapatya, āhavanīya and dakṣiṇāgni), the fire for the new sacrifices has to be carried from the vihāra to the mahāvedi. This is done as a part of the whole ritual.</p>
			<p>Taking out the agni (fire) from the old āhavanīya in the vihāra, as also the soma stalks from which soma juice is to be extracted for the Somayāga in a ceremonial procession is called &#x2018;agnīṣoma-praṇayana.&#x2019; This is done on the day before the sutyā (day of extraction of soma juice). The adhvaryu carries the fire on clay, the yajamāna and patnī along with their sons and grandsons following him, one behind the other, in a long procession. Soma stalks as also all the vessels needed in the sacrifice are brought in a cart and deposited in their respective places. The fire is deposited and kindled in his pit by the āgnīdhra priest.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>AGNIṢṬOMA</ref> and <ref>SOMAYĀGA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Agniṣṭoma</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;praise of Agni&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The system of sacrifices (yajñas and yāgas) forms the link between men and gods. Men propitiate gods through them and gods respond by bestowing upon men what they want. This is the doctrine propounded in the Hindu scriptures like the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> (3.10-12).</p>
			<p>Somayāga is a general name for those sacrifices in which libations of the soma juice are offered in the duly consecrated fire. Agniṣṭoma is a typical Somayāga, forming the prakṛti or model for other Soma sacrifices. It is such an integral part of another well-known sacrifice, Jyoti-ṣṭoma, that these two are often identified. Literally the word &#x2018;Agniṣṭoma&#x2019; means &#x2018;praise of Agni&#x2019; and the rite derives its name from the hymns called stoma (a group of three ṛks) which are chanted in praise of Agni towards the end of the rite.</p>
			<p>On the first day, somapravākas or heralds of Soma sacrifice are sent out to invite priests. Choosing the priests, dīkṣā (initiatory rites) of the sacrificer including another small sacrifice called Dīkṣaṇīyā-iṣṭi and construction of bamboo sheds are the other rites to be performed.</p>
			<p>On the second day apart from purchasing the soma creepers and &#x2018;welcoming&#x2019; them ceremonially, two more rites called pravargya and upasad are performed. (For details see <ref>PRAVARGYA</ref> and <ref>UPASAD</ref>.)</p>
			<p>On the third day, pravargya and upasad rites are repeated followed by the construction of mahāvedi and uttaravedi (altars for performing the sacrifices).</p>
			<p>On the fourth day, after once again performing pravargya and upasad rites, fire is ceremonially transferred from the old and permanent sacrificial shed to the new. This is known as agnīṣoma-praṇayana. (See <ref>AGNĪṢOMA-PRAṆAYANA</ref> for details.) An animal sacrifice (paśu-bandha) is also performed.</p>
			<p>On the fifth and the last day called &#x2018;sutyā,&#x2019; the soma juice is extracted cere- monially three times and offered. The first called prātassavana is done in the morning. The second, mādhyandina-savana is done at noon. At the end of this, sacrificial fees are distributed. Soon after this, begins the third pressing called tṛtīyā. At the end of the sacrifice, all those directly involved in it have avabhṛtha-snāna (ceremonial bath marking the conclusion of the sacrifice).</p>
			<p>See also <ref>JYOTIṢṬOMA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Agniveśa</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>ĀYURVEDA</ref> and <ref>CARAKA-SAṀHITĀ</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnyādhāna</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;producing the fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>During the Vedic period, the perfor-mance of sacrifices was very common. It was believed that one could get whatever one desired through the appropriate sacrifices. Only men belonging to the first three castes, viz., the brāhmaṇas, the kṣattriyas and the vaiśyas, were eligible for establishing the Vedic fires and performing these sacrifices. Certain classes of śūdras like the rathakāras (carpenters) were also considered eligible. Even such persons had to establish the fires in a ceremonial way following the prescribed procedure. One who established the fires came to be known as an āhitāgni.</p>
			<p>Agnyādhāna, also known as agnyā-dheya (or simply ādhāna or ādheya) was this prescribed rite. Literally it means placing of burning coals for the generation of the gārhapatya fire.</p>
			<p>Only a married adult could establish the Vedic fires. He could do it on any day he felt the desire or had to do it only in certain seasons and on certain astronomically suitable days, nakṣatras or stars or asterisms being the determining factor.</p>
			<p>The actual rite was spread over two days though preparation of the araṇis (pieces of wood used in producing fire by attrition) and other implements would start much earlier.</p>
			<p>The first day known as upavasatha is devoted by the yajamāna (sacrificer) to preliminaries like choosing the priests (ṛtvigvaraṇa), offering them madhuparka (For details see <ref>MADHUPARKA</ref>.), preparing the sacrificial ground, having a shave and so on. Preparation and consumption of the brahmaudana (cooked rice meant for the priests) is another rite, performed by the adhvaryu. (See <ref>ADHVARYU</ref>.)</p>
			<p>After the first night and just before dawn the next day, fire is produced by the attrition of the two araṇis by the adhvaryu. Singing of sāmans at this time by the udgātṛ (priest of <em>Sāmaveda</em>) is a special feature. Gārhapatya fire in the hearth meant for it is the first to be set up. The āhavanīya fire is produced from the gārhapatya by the adhvaryu. The dakṣiṇāgni is set up by the priest āgnīdhra (one of the assistant priests) (See <ref>ĀGNĪDHRA</ref> for details.) either directly by the attrition of the araṇis or from the gārhapatya.</p>
			<p>Establishing of the other two fires, sabhya and āvasathya, is optional.</p>
			<p>After setting up the fires, various kinds of grains and fuel sticks are offered to them.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>PAÑCĀGNI</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agnyādheya</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;producing the fire&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>See <ref>AGNYĀDHĀNA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>agrahāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;grant given to brāhmaṇas&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Since the most ancient times brāhmaṇas—men of learning, austerity and character—have commanded the respect of the Hindu society. Kings used to vie with one another in granting land, cows and wealth to them for their personal use. Villages or lands (parts of villages) given to them for their maintenance have been known as &#x2018;agrahāra.&#x2019; People living in such agrahāras were called &#x2018;mahājanas.&#x2019; They were exempted by the kings from payment of taxes and also punishment for lapses in behaviour unless they were of a serious nature like treason, murder etc. The mahājanas themselves regulated the conduct of the inhabitants of the agrahāra.</p>
			<p>Agrahāras were intended to be centres of learning and the mahājanas were expected to be models of conduct.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āgrahāyaṇī</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;related to agrahāyaṇa&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>The month Mārgaśīrṣa, the 9th month of the Hindu calendar year (corres- ponding to November-December) is called Agrahāyaṇa (&#x2018;beginning of the year&#x2019;). According to the writings of the foreign travellers visiting this country like Al Beruni (A. D. 1030) and borne out by the internal evidence in the <em>Mahābhārata (Anuśāsanaparva</em> 106.17-30) the year began with Mārgaśīrṣa. Hence the name Agrahāyaṇa. The rite performed on the full-moon day of this month is called &#x2018;āgrahāyaṇī.&#x2019;</p>
			<p>An important part of this rite is pratyavarohaṇa (&#x2018;descending again&#x2019;) signifying the ceremonial descent of the entire family from a high cot or, couch which was being used from the month of Śrāvaṇa (corresponding to July-August) for fear of snakes. Hence this is sometimes considered a part of the snake rite.</p>
			<p>After uttering the prescribed mantras (which contain prayers to snakes not to harm the family) and offering pāyasam (milk-rice pudding) to them, the entire family comes down the high cot and sleeps on the bed of straw or grass newly prepared.</p>
			<p>On this occasion the house is usually replastered and painted, if not renovated.</p>
			<p>In some works pratyavarohaṇa is mentioned as a separate rite to be performed at the beginning of each of the six seasons.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Āgrayaṇa</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;offering of first fruits&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>It was a custom among the ancient Hindus to offer newly harvested grains to the Vedic deities before consuming them. Āgrayaṇa is an agricultural rite of the iṣṭi type (See <ref>IṢṬI</ref> for details.) which an āhitāgni (one who has ceremonially established the Vedic fires) should perform, before making use of the newly harvested grains. The rite was considered necessary only with regard to vrīhi (rice), yava (barley) and śyāmāka (a kind of yellow grain, <em>Panicum frumentaceum</em>) and not for other grains, vegetables or fruits. Oblations of cooked food are offered to the deities like Indra and Agni. A lump of the cooked food should be thrown on the top of the dwelling house. The sacrificer should also eat a mouthful of the grain.</p>
			<p>Even those who have not established the Vedic fires can perform Āgrayaṇa in the aupāsanāgni (domestic fire lighted at the time of marriage) with an extra oblation to Agni-sviṣṭakṛt.</p>
			<p>This rite is also called Navayajña or Navasasyeṣṭi.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ahalyā</word>
			<alias />
			<note />
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Ahalyā, the wife of the sage Gautama and mother of another sage Śatānanda, is a well-known character in Hindu mythology. She is said to have been born out of creator Brahmā&#x2019;s mind as the very personification of feminine grace and beauty and given in marriage to the maharṣi Gautama. Infatuated by her beauty, Indra the king of gods impersonated Gautama and seduced her. Consequently she was cursed by the sage Gautama to remain invisible for a thousand years sustaining herself only on air and wallowing in ash. She was redeemed by Rāma, the son of Daśaratha and restored to Gautama.</p>
			<p>Some works like the <em>Adhyātma Rāmāyaṇa</em> say that she was converted into a stone. This version seems to be more popular.</p>
			<p>When Uttaṅka (or Udaṅka), a disciple of Gautama, offered to fulfil any of her desires as his gurudakṣiṇā (fees due to the preceptor) she asked for the kuṇḍalas (ear-ornaments) of queen Madayantī (wife of the king Saudāsa). Uttaṅka secured them successfully, though with great difficulty.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>GAUTAMA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>Ahalyābāī Hoḷkar</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(A. D. 1735-1795)</note>
			<image>Ahalyabal_Hoḷkar.png</image>
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>One of the few Hindu rulers of the medieval period, who did much for the protection of Hinduism and preservation of Hindu temples was Ahalyābāī Hoḷkar, the queen of Indore.</p>
			<p>Though born in a poor family of farmers, she was married to Khaṇḍe Rāo, the son of Mallhār Rāo Hoḷkar of Indore. When her husband died in a battle, she boldly took over the administration in A.D. 1765 and ruled with great efficiency till her demise in A. D. 1795. She was responsible for the protection of the original Śivaliṅgas of Somanātha and Kāśī temples by building separate temples for the same. She improved or renovated many temples in North India and also built rest-houses for pilgrims in the places of pilgrimage. The modern city of Indore owes its development mainly to her.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>ahaṅkāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;egoism&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Ahaṅkāra is that which produces abhimāna, the sense of &#x2018;I&#x2019; and &#x2018;mine.&#x2019; According to Sāṅkhyan metaphysics, a large part of which is accepted by Vedānta, ahaṅkāra is the principle of individuation that arises after mahat or buddhi in the process of evolution from prakṛti (nature). It is regarded as a substance since it is the material cause of other substances like the mind or the sense-organs. Through its action the different puruṣas (individual selves) become endowed each with a separate mental background. These puruṣas identify themselves with the acts of prakṛti through ahaṅkāra.</p>
			<p>At the individual level it makes the puruṣa feel that he is receiving the sensations through the senses and the mind, and deciding about appropriate action, through the intellect.</p>
			<p>At the cosmic level, the five senses of cognition (jñānendriyas), the five organs of action (karmendriyas), the mind (manas) and the five subtle elements like the earth (tanmātras) are produced out of ahaṅkāra.</p>
			<p>In some works of Vedānta, ahaṅkāra is considered as a function of antaḥkaraṇa (internal instrument or mind), responsible for ego-sense and possessiveness.</p>
			<p>Ahaṅkāra as egoism or self-conceit is considered as a great obstacle in spiritual life and the cultivation of humility is prescribed as its antidote.</p>
			<p>See also <ref>SĀṄKHYA DARŚANA</ref>.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āhāra</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;What is taken in,&#x2019; &#x2018;food&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description />
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<head>
			<word>āhāraśuddhi</word>
			<alias />
			<note>(&#x2018;purity of food&#x2019;)</note>
			<image />
		</head>
		<description>
			<p>Hindu scriptural works declare that there is a close relationship between the body and the mind. In fact it is the mind, as the repository of karma, that creates the future body since it survives the death of the physical bodies till the attainment of mokṣa (liberation). Hence the body and the mind act and react on each other. In this context āhāra or food assumes great importance. The quality of food affects the quality of mind. In fact the <em>Chāndogya Upaniṣad</em> (7.26.2) goes to the extent of declaring that purity of food leads to purity of mind which results in the excellent retention in memory of all that is heard and studied from the preceptor. The resultant wisdom leads to freedom from all bonds. This is because the subtle part of the food that is eaten sustains the mind whereas the gross part of it nourishes the body.</p>
			<p>Āhāra is classified into three groups:</p>
			<p>sāttvika, rājasika and tāmasika (<em>vide Bhagavadgītā</em> 17.7-10). Sāttvika food contributes to longevity, health, strength and happiness. Rājasika food generates passion leading to sorrow and suffering. Tāmasika food produces dullness, indolence and drownsiness.</p>
			<p>The various scriptural works mention long lists of food articles coming under these three categories.</p>
			<p>There are regulations with regard to the quantity of food to be eaten and elaborate rules regarding the time, place and also company in which it should be taken.</p>
			<p>Moderation in eating is always the rule. Hindu medical works recommend that half the stomach should be filled with solid food and a quarter with water leaving the rest of the space for the movement of air.</p>
			<p>One is advised to avoid partaking of food before performing spiritual practices. Solar and lunar eclipses are believed to have very adverse effects on food and hence one should not eat during eclipses.</p>
			<p>Places to be avoided for eating include temples, public places, moving animals and vehicles.</p>
			<p>Impurity (doṣa) can accrue to food on three counts: jātidoṣa, nimittadoṣa and āśrayadoṣa. Garlic or cabbage for instance, is impure by its very species (jāti) and hence must be avoided. Nimittadoṣa comes by external impurities like dust or hair as also an insanitary handling of food. This can be obviated by strictly observing the rules of health and sanitation. Foods cooked, touched or handled by persons of questionable character become contaminated by their evil psychic vibrations which can be transmitted to those who consume them. This type of impurity is called āśrayadoṣa, doṣa or defect arising as a result of āśraya or repository. Offering the food to God before eating destroys this impurity.</p>
		</description>
	</entry>
</eoh>
