<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE eoh SYSTEM "eoh.dtd">

<eoh>
	<volume vnum="004">
		<entry>
			<head>
				<word>Hindu Culture</word>
				<note />
			</head>
			<description>
				<h3>1. Introduction</h3>
				<p>It is an undeniable fact of history that the destiny of the world has very often been shaped by great persons of sterling character, rather than the mediocre mortals who were a hapless part of history. Man&#x2019;s innate spirit—the personification of life, energy and consciousness—has always been goading him to rise above nature by struggling <em>against</em> it and <em>not</em> by being in conformity with it. It is this struggle that results in his progress.</p>
				<p>This progress can be in two directions: external and internal. External progress leads to a better standard of living, i.e., civilization. Internal progress on the other hand, results in greater refinement of the whole personality, i.e., culture.</p>
				<p>Civilization and culture do not necessarily go together. Nor are they mutually exclusive. They can be elegantly harmonized, provided one knows the relative proportions in combining them. This is exactly what the ancient ṛṣis or sages of India—whether the rājarṣis like Janaka and Śrī Rāma or the brahmarṣis like Vasiṣṭha and Vyāsa—did when they administered or guided the great kingdoms of their times.</p>
				<p>World-history, whether of the ancient times or of the recent past, is replete with conflicts and wars. In general, one can adduce the following reasons for such conflicts:</p>
				<ul class="lower alpha">
					<li>Imperialism or dictatorship versus democracy.</li>
					<li>The rich versus the poor.</li>
					<li>Patriotism and nationalism versus humanism or internationalism.</li>
					<li>Science versus religion.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>However, the philosophy that the whole world is one family (vasudhaiva kuṭumbakam) as taught and practised by our great sages who were the real socio-religious and cultural leaders, has practically eliminated such conflicts in our country.</p>
				<p>Records of ancient and medieval history of our country as given by the foreign travellers and other foreigners<aside>Megasthanes (302-288 B. C.); Abul Fazal (A. D. 1551-1602; <em>Ain-i-Akbari</em>); William Jones (A. D. 1746-1794); James Mill (A. D. 1773-1836; <em>History of India</em>); Max Muller (A. D. 1823-1900; <em>India: What can it teach us?</em>); Monier Willams (A. D. 1819-1899; <em>Modern India and the Indians</em>); Col. James Tod (A. D. 1782-1835; <em>Annals and Antiquities of Rajasthan</em>).</aside> bespeak not only of a high degree of civilization but also of culture as revealed in their accounts of appreciation of our people&#x2019;s deep devotion to truth and ingrained honesty. This had been possible solely because the ancient and the medieval Hindus of India never forgot that dharma (ethical values) and adhyātmavidyā (spirituality) were the centre of gravity of their life. This fact has been further buttressed by the modern saints like Rāmakṛṣṇa, Vivekānanda, Aurobindo and Ramaṇa Maharṣi. Their life and teachings have shown us the moderns, not only the need for and utility of a higher degree of civilization but also its limitations and dangers, thereby showing where to draw the border line. While they have taught us to be rightfully proud of our past history and culture, they have also reminded us very forcefully that we should take only the best from other nations and integrate it with our basic culture.</p>
				<p>Their advice of caution has come not a day too soon. During the last few decades there has been a sickening tendency amongst us—especially the younger generation—to blindly imitate the Western culture, be it in hair-style or dress or language or manners. All the dreadful vices of theirs like consumerism, alcoholism, addiction to drugs and profligate promiscuity are—fast catching us. If we do not wake up immediately to these dangers and try vigorously to tread the path blazed by our religio-spiritual heritage, the future generations—if at all they come into existence—can never forgive us!</p>
				<p>In the light of all that has been said till now, a basic study of Hindu culture—as it was in the past and as it is at present—in order to evolve a balanced combination of the true spirits of both the Western and our cultures, has become an urgent necessity.</p>
				<p>It is rather an uphill task to present such a comprehensive and complicated subject in a capsule form, in an essay such as this. Yet, an earnest attempt is being made in the following pages which, it is hoped, will not be in vain.</p>
				<h3>2. Saṁskṛti or Culture</h3>
				<h2>Definitions</h2>
				<p>Before undertaking a study of Hindu culture, one should understand what exactly we mean by the word &#x2018;culture.&#x2019; Since it is being widely used as the equivalent of the Sanskrit word &#x2018;saṁskṛti,&#x2019; it is better to study this word first, its connotations and implications. The verbal root &#x2018;kṛ&#x2019; (to do) can give rise to several nouns when associated with certain prefixes. Out of these, three words have a direct bearing on our subject: prakṛti (basic matter or condition), saṁskṛti (refined matter or condition) and vikṛti (modified or decayed matter or condition).</p>
				<p>These can be explained further with suitable examples:</p>
				<p>A block of stone is &#x2018;prakṛti,&#x2019; the basic raw material. When it is sculptured into a beautiful image, it becomes &#x2018;saṁskṛti.&#x2019;</p>
				<p>A lump of gold is &#x2018;prakṛti.&#x2019; An elegant ornament made out of it is &#x2018;saṁskṛti.&#x2019;</p>
				<p>Raw food articles like rice and sugar are &#x2018;prakṛti,&#x2019; whereas a delicious pudding prepared out of them is &#x2018;saṁskṛti.&#x2019;</p>
				<p>On the other hand, if the block of stone is broken into chips or the gold lump reduced to powder or the food articles get putrefied, they become &#x2018;vikṛti.&#x2019;</p>
				<p>The English word &#x2018;culture&#x2019; is derived from the Latin term <em>cult</em> or <em>cultus</em>, meaning, &#x2018;tilling, care, refinement and worship&#x2019;. In sum, it means cultivating and refining a thing to such an extent that its end-product evokes our admiration and respect. This is practically the same as &#x2018;saṁskṛti&#x2019; of the Sanskrit language.</p>
				<p>The word &#x2018;cultivation,&#x2019; also derived from the same Latin root, as generally applied to the cultivation of crops from the earth, involves several processes such as tilling and preparing the ground, sowing the seeds, watering and manuring as also removing the weeds and destroying harmful insects. This will ultimately result in reaping a good crop.</p>
				<p>This word also fits in very well with the concept of saṁskṛti.</p>
				<p>Another expression current in the Sanskrit language is &#x2018;saṁskāra.&#x2019; It refers to the process of cultivating, preparing or refining. The abstract quality in the end product is called &#x2018;saṁskṛti.&#x2019; But very often, the two words are used as if they are identical.</p>
				<h2>Culture and Human Beings</h2>
				<p>The culture of a society depends on the culture of the individuals comprising it, as also the relationship they have among themselves. Hence great attention has to be paid to the growing and nurturing of the basic values of culture in an individual.</p>
				<p>Contrary to the vociferous assertions of the materialists or the dry philosophers, a human being is the conglomeration of several parts, apparently different from one another, but acting cohesively for a common purpose, that of the jīvātman or the individual soul (a conscious entity) inhabiting them. They are: the physical body including the sense-organs, the faculty of speech, the mind and the spirit. A proper training in culture has to tackle each one of these singly, but in a way that it does not interfere or overshadow the natural faculties of the others. For instance, the arms should not be developed to such an extent that they become a burden for the feet to carry them or allow the nose to develop at the cost of the eyes and the ears! It is a balanced development and a harmonious combination of all the limbs and faculties that conduces not only to the health of the body but also to the well-being of the personality as a whole.</p>
				<p>Such a training as envisaged by a holistic attitude towards the development of the human personality can be on the following lines:</p>
				<ul class="lower alpha">
					<li>Meticulously observing the rules of health and sanitation. Physical culture including yogāsanas.</li>
					<li>Cultivating the faculty of speech through the study of languages and grammar of those languages.<br />
					Practising the art of speaking the truth at the right time and place, including the knack of presenting even unpleasant truths in a manner that is gracefully accepted.</li>
					<li>Training the mind in developing discretion and discrimination so that the right decision can be taken at the right time within the limitations imposed by the circumstances.<br />
					Exercising the intellect by the study of science, philosophy and logic.<br />
					Fostering a sense of justice.</li>
					<li>Trying to develop a taste or interest in some of the arts such as classical music and dance, good and elevating literature, drawing and painting, drama and other theatrical arts that can rouse our finer sentiments and so on.</li>
					<li>Faith in God and a regular habit of prayer.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>Coming to the social aspect of the training for culture, one should start with greater and more intimate association with one&#x2019;s own family members. Though this suggestion may appear a little strange—since such an association seems to be taken for granted—it has become very necessary to bring about a sense of togetherness and cohesion within a family. Such a cohesion is almost absent now-a-days in most of the families, thanks to the industrialization of the country and a mechanical way of life that it has engendered.</p>
				<p>The royal secret of good human relationship with others is unselfish love and genuine consideration for the needs and feelings of others. This includes a sense of responsibility and duty towards others.</p>
				<p>It goes without saying that this &#x2018;charity that begins at home&#x2019; should gradually be extended to the neighbours, friends and relatives as also other people, leading ultimately to the highest ideal of &#x2018;vasudhaiva kuṭumbakam&#x2019; (&#x2018;the whole world is my family&#x2019;).</p>
				<p>And, it can be assured that a cultured and refined individual will easily succeed in his efforts at being in peace and harmony with the society, for the very reason that he is a cultured and refined individual !</p>
				<h2>Basis of Culture</h2>
				<p>In the Upaniṣads—the canonical texts of Vedānta—we sometimes come across the basic question, &#x2018;What is that by knowing which, everything else is known?&#x2019; In a similar vein, we can ask, &#x2018;What is that by possessing which, culture can be possessed automatically?&#x2019; The answer as given by our ṛṣis, our wise ancestors, is &#x2018;spiritual wisdom.&#x2019; (And it should be remembered that this spiritual wisdom, in the ultimate analysis, evolves out of spiritual experience and <em>not</em> out of book-learning!)</p>
				<p>This question may be asked from another angle too. &#x2018;In what way does advancement of culture (or saṁskṛti) lead to spiritual evolution culminating in mature spiritual wisdom?&#x2019;</p>
				<p>A corollary that arises from this question is: &#x2018;What is the basic norm referring to which the evolution of cultural values is estimated?&#x2019;</p>
				<p>The answer is &#x2018;mokṣa&#x2019; or emancipation through &#x2018;ātmajñāna&#x2019; or Self-realization. This itself is adhyātmavidyā or the science of the Self within.</p>
				<p>This is the norm for evaluation, nay, the final goal of life itself.</p>
				<p>And, this point of view of our ancient leaders, the ṛṣis of yore, has stood the test of time for several millennia!</p>
				<h2>Training in Culture</h2>
				<p>They have advised us to follow the path of satya (truth that brings about the welfare of all) and dharma (righteousness) which are eternal values. For this, they have given us two parallel paths: pravṛtti (activism) and nivṛtti (restraint). The ultimate goal of life can be reached by starting with the first and passing through the second, they being two phases and faces of life here. It is also possible to have a balanced combination of these two and reach the same (final) goal.</p>
				<p>If the elite could learn about these truths by getting training in the gurukulas (forest academies) the masses were educated by the wise elders of the society through such popular devices as harikathās (musical discourses with ethico- religious themes), devotional music, folklore, folksongs and folk-dramas, recitation of mythological works and so on.<aside>In the modern context, we can make very good use of the various technical devices like the radio, the television and the films to propagate the eternal values taught by our sages, much more, effectively, instead of abusing them and degrading the entire society.</aside></p>
				<p>That an ideal civilization-cum-culture can throw up an ideal person has been proved by the sage Vālmīki in his celebrated work, the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em>. Apart from Śrī Rāma,<aside>Modern Indian research scholars, basing their calculations on the astronomical data given in the two epics (<em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> and <em>Mahābhārata</em>) have tried to prove the historicity of these epics and their heroes. See <em>Indian CHronology</em> by Dr. D. S. Triveda, Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan, 1963.</aside> the principal hero, we come across a galaxy of great persons such as Lakṣmaṇa, Bharata, Hanumān, Vibhīṣaṇa, Sītā, Sumitrā and Maṇḍodarī, as also the sages like Vasiṣṭha, Agastya and Atri.</p>
				<p>Though adhyātmavidyā—or, to put it in the modern language, religion and philosophy—has been the primary basis of Hindu culture, all other aspects of life here and now, that contribute to the attainment of peace and joy, have also been given their due place. For instance: social values; political institutions including the judiciary; economic ideas; educational system; physical, chemical, biological and health sciences; engineering sciences, arts like music, dance, drama, drawing, painting and sculpture, and so on.</p>
				<p>It will be not only interesting and fascinating, but also rewarding, to undertake a panoramic study of all these facets of Hindu culture. Such an attempt on the one hand can boost our self-confidence and public image; and on the other, further inspire us to do even better, surpassing the other nations in the process, as we had done in an earlier age.</p>
				<h3>3. Religion and Philosophy</h3>
				<h2>Religion is Adhyātmavidyā</h2>
				<p>Religion, in its truest sense of adhyātmavidyā, has been the basis of Hindu culture. Vivekānanda has an interesting description of the Hindu:<aside><em>The Complete Works of Swami Vivekananda</em>, Vol. 8, Mayavati, Advaita Ashrama, Sixth Edition, 1977, p. 205</aside></p>
				<p>&#x2018;He does everything in a religious manner. He eats religiously; he sleeps religiously, he rises in the morning religiously, he does good things religiously; and he also does bad things religiously!&#x2019;</p>
				<p>According to him, religion is not just belief in certain dogmas or observing some rituals but realizing the divinity that is already there in everyone of us. Whatever helps us to manifest this latent divinity is also religion. As already pointed out, it is this that has been termed &#x2018;adhyātma-vidyā&#x2019; or the science of the Self within.</p>
				<h2>Its Two Aspects—The Darśanas and the Yogas</h2>
				<p>This adhyātmavidyā has two aspects: theory and practice. Theoretical speculations have led to the evolution of several schools of philosophy. The practical application of their findings has led to the formation of several systems of sādhanās or spiritual exercises, generally called &#x2018;yogas&#x2019;.</p>
				<p>The well-known schools of Hindu philosophy are six. Hence the name &#x2018;ṣaḍ-darśanas&#x2019; (ṣaḍ = six; darśana = philo- sophy). They are: Nyāya of Gautama, Vaiśeṣika of Kaṇāda, Sāṅkhya of Kapila, Yoga of Patañjali, Mīmāṁsā of Jaimini and Vedānta of Bādarāyaṇa.</p>
				<p>The Nyāya system of Gautama and the Vaiśeṣika system of Kaṇāda envisage creation by Paramātman (God) out of aṇus (atoms) which are eternal. The shape of things is directly related to the adṛṣṭa (unseen deserts) of the jīvas (individual souls) left over unredeemed, from the previous cycle of creation. Combination of these atoms causes creation and their disintegration results in the dissolution of this universe. The jīva has got into the bondage of transmigration due to ignorance of its real nature as an eternal entity different from the body, the senses and the mind. He attains mokṣa or liberation (a state of absolute negation of all pain and suffering) through tattvajñāna (knowledge of the realities) by listening (śravaṇa) to the truths mentioned in the scriptures, by reflecting on the same (manana) and by meditation on his true nature (nididhyāsana).</p>
				<p>The Sāṅkhya system of Kapila and the Yoga system of Patañjali are complementary to each other. They advance the theory that prakṛti (the fundamental matrix of matter) evolves into this universe in the presence of the puruṣas (the individual souls) who act as catalytic agents. In fact, the whole process of creation is for the benefit of the puruṣas, for their spiritual upliftment, resulting finally in their emancipation. The pañcabhūtas (the five elements like earth, water and fire) are evolutes of this prakṛti. The universe is a permutation and combination of these. Though essentially detached from prakṛti, the puruṣa involves himself in bondage by getting attached to it and its products. This leads to repeated transmigration. Detachment from it through vivekakhyāti (discriminaion and wisdom) aided by the eight steps of Yoga leads him finally to emancipation.</p>
				<p>The Mīmāṁsā system of Jaimini advocates the theory that prakṛti or insentient nature evolves by itself into this universe, impelled by the prārabdha karma (actions done by the individual souls in the previous lives and about to be fructified) of the jīvas. Their liberation (described as total cessation of pain and suffering) is achieved by strictly following all the directions given in the Mīmāṁsā works with regard to karmas (Vedic rituals and other actions).</p>
				<p>According to the Vedānta system of Bādarāyaṇa (also known as Vyāsa), Brahman the Absolute, projects this universe out of Itself, sustains it and withdraws it into Itself in each cycle of creation. It is something akin to a web coming out of a spider&#x2019;s mouth or sparks emitted out of fire. Hence, everything that exists is really Brahman and there is nothing that is not Brahman. The jīva gets liberated through jñāna (knowledge of his real naure) and bhakti (devotion to Brahman) regaining his original state of infinite bliss.</p>
				<p>Coming to Yoga, the practical aspect, there are four of them: Karmayoga, Bhaktiyoga, Jñānayoga and Rājayoga. All these yogas cleanse the mind and make it so pure that the ātman within (Self or God) is automatically revealed. If Karmayoga advocates the performance of all ordained actions with a desireless and selfless attitude, Bhaktiyoga teaches devotion to God and attaining him through his grace. Jñānayoga advises constant reflection and meditation on the true nature of oneself as the ātman, ultimately resulting in its experience. Rājayoga (based mainly on Patañjali&#x2019;s Yoga system) prescribes an eightfold path leading finally to samādhi or superconscious experience of the Self within.</p>
				<p>It should be specially stressed here that all these philosophical speculations and practical spiritual disciplines are based almost entirely on the basic scriptures of Hinduism, viz., the Vedas, the Upaniṣads, the <em>Bhagavadgītā</em> and allied works.</p>
				<h2>Sāmānya Dharmas or Basic Moral Values</h2>
				<p>These works, while dealing with philosophical principles or modes of spiritual practice, have also vigorously stressed the need for inculcating sāmānya-dharmas or certain basic moral and ethical values in one&#x2019;s life, to refine oneself and to create social harmony. Both of these conduce to quick spiritual progress. They are: ahiṁsā (nonviolence), satya (truth), asteya (nonstealing), dāna (giving gifts to deserving persons), kṣānti (forbearance), dama (control of passions), śama (inner peace), akārpaṇya (not demeaning oneself), śauca (purity) and tapas (austerity).</p>
				<h2>The Four Puruṣārthas</h2>
				<p>While stressing mokṣa as the ultimate goal of human life, the scriptures advocating adhyātmavidyā have not forgotten the legitimate desires and aspirations of the average human beings. They are: artha (wealth) and kāma (instinctive desires of the flesh). However, these can be earned and enjoyed only when they are in conformity with dharma (righteousness) and do not transgress it. What dharma is and what it is not, can be known only through the holy books and the holy persons. Of course, mokṣa as the final goal of life is never omitted from such lists. These four together—dharma, artha, kāma and mokṣa—are called puruṣārthas (the four ends of life desired by all human beings).</p>
				<h2>The Guru</h2>
				<p>One of the most important things repeatedly stressed in our religio-philosophical works is that no progress is ever possible in any field of life—much less in the field of adhyātmavidyā—without the active help and guidance of the guru or teacher. A thorough knowledge of the religious works, practical experience, a sinless life and a loving concern for the welfare of the disciple are the qualifications expected of a guru. Humility, eagerness and earnestness to learn and devoted service to the guru are the desired qualities in a śiṣya or a disciple. When the disciple advances to great heights in religio-spiritual life, he is required to pass on that knowledge to worthy disciples thus keeping alive a great tradition for the benefit of humankind.</p>
				<p>From all this we can easily understand that the basic scriptures of Hinduism—of all hues and views—never ignored the social aspects of life even while constantly stressing the ultimate spiritual goal.</p>
				<p>And, this is a very significant contri- bution to the development of our culture.</p>
				<h3>4. Hindu Society</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>It is the culture of a country that converts a denizen into a citizen and a citizen into a national. Again, it is the individual human being that is called a denizen or a citizen or a national. A society comprises of families and, families, of individuals. Hence, a study of the culture of the Hindu society has to embrace all aspects of the individual and the social life.</p>
				<p>The puruṣārtha principle, the varṇa system and the āśrama scheme of life are the three legs of the tripod that gave stability and vigour to the Hindu society—whenever they were understood properly and implemented rightly—during the ancient and medieval periods. If the puruṣārtha principle (as explained on p. 33) has fulfilled the aspirations of an individual and given him a goal and a direction to his life, the āśrama scheme of life has given it a concrete and practical shape. And, the varṇa system has given him an organizational structure to work out the same. Therefore it is necessary to describe briefly these two facets of Hindu social life: the varṇa system and the āśrama scheme.</p>
				<h2>The Varṇa System</h2>
				<p>The fourfold varṇa system goes back to the <em>Ṛgvedasaṁhitā</em> (vide 8.35.16.7; 1.10.8.7) itself. To make a living by choosing a profession as per one&#x2019;s desire and aptitude is a common phenomenon seen in all civilized societies. It is the duty of the society to provide suitable opportunities for its members to choose and pursue those vocations that agree with their nature. This is the philosophy behind the varṇa system. The Vedas, including the <em>Puruṣasūkta</em> (wherein this fourfold division of the society has been enunciated very clearly) have only recognized its existence and <em>not</em> created it.</p>
				<p>As a society grows in size and civilization, there has got to be a division of labour, since all persons cannot do all things. In the early Vedic period, this division of labour might have taken place on a voluntary basis, even as the members of a family do so on any important occasion affecting the whole family. Some chose the occupation of acquiring knowledge, wisdom and culture, and training the younger generation in them. They became the brāhmaṇas. Those who were physically sturdy and strong, took to arms to protect the society from external aggression as also maintain internal law and order. They were the kṣattriyas. A great majority of the rest devoted themselves to the production and distribution of wealth and goods through agriculture, dairy farming, trade and commerce. They were called the vaiśyas. The others who could not fit into any of these vocations made a living by supplying manual labour and serving others. They became the śūdras. In course of time, each of these varṇas—from the brāhmaṇas to the śūdras—acquired hierarchical superiority over the succeeding ones.</p>
				<p>Though this was a natural process based on guṇa (aptitude) and karma (vocation chosen as per that aptitude), it was more a general rule and an ideal one at that. Hence, birth in a varṇa became an easier and a more practicable principle to fix up the varṇa of that individual. This was the beginning of the jāti or the caste system wherein the varṇa got automatically fixed by birth (jāti = birth).</p>
				<p>India is a continent of different races. But the people of these races have been welded together into an integrated, though federal, society by the varṇa-jāti system. Even the foreign invaders like the Śakas and Hūṇas never tried to destroy it but gracefully accepted it. The system has protected the Hindu society by preserving the various professions, by preventing unhealthy competitions and by democratizing institutions. It has thus preserved the unity of the country in spite of the diversities.</p>
				<p>As for the caste-conflicts, they are mostly of the post-British era. The problem has sometimes been compounded by selfish and narrow-minded political and social leaders, ever eager to fish in troubled waters.</p>
				<p>Some interesting sidelights of the varṇa-caste-system may now be stated here which give us an idea of the society of the ancient and medieval days:</p>
				<p>Performing Vedic sacrifices was an integral part of a brāhmaṇa&#x2019;s professional life. He could not refuse to eat, when invited, at the houses of sac-chūdras (good śūdras who followed the sāmānya dharmas or the basic moral code in their life) especially if they were his employees or family friends. During national emergencies or calamities he could take to the vocations of other castes. He was relegated to the group of caṇḍālas (lowest among the śūdras) if he gave up the brāhminical way of life without valid reasons.</p>
				<p>Evidence is not wanting to show that many brāhmaṇas went to foreign countries such as Egypt, Greece, Rome, Mexico as also the South-East Asian countries to preach religion, philosophy and various aspects of Hindu culture.</p>
				<p>As for the kṣattriyas, many of them were not only good kings but also experts in the field of Vedic lore and saintly in their personal life.</p>
				<p>Indian kṣattriya soldiers are said to have participated in the Marathon and Plataea battles (in Greece) in 490 B.C.</p>
				<p>The kings had built huge armies and navies. The armies included the use of horses and elephants.</p>
				<p>The vaiśyas were generally divided into two groups: the gṛhapatis and the śreṣṭhīs. The former lived by agriculture and dairy-farming. The latter were devoted to trade and commerce. They had successfully built huge corporations and had also established trade links with foreign countries such as China and Jāva in the east, and, Egypt, Greece and Rome in the West.</p>
				<p>The śūdras were divided into two classes: the sacchūdras (the good) and the asacchūdras (the not-so-good). The former who led a good life—honouring the general moral principles—had been permitted even to undergo the upanayana ceremony and perform certain kinds of yajñas or sacrifices. They could learn and teach religious truths except the Vedas. They could adopt various professions such as fighting, agriculture, mat-making, fishing, laundry, haircutting and so on.</p>
				<p>Aspṛśyatā or untouchability, though unknown during the Vedic days, might have gradually started during the 8th century B. C. Certain vocations considered as unclean and a health hazard, committing of heinous sins, people of certain countries whose ways of life radically differed from those of the people here, certain cults considered as heretical and hence dangerous—these seem to be the various reasons for the origin and spread of the idea of untouchability over the centuries. But even they were given enough scope for moral and spiritual development by exhorting them to follow the sāmānya dharmas as also the worship of gods like Viṣṇu or Bhairava (an aspect of Śiva).</p>
				<p>Work for their emancipation, especially by the religious teachers of devotional schools, has gone on for centuries, though the results achieved are not commensurate with the efforts put in.</p>
				<h2>The Āśrama Scheme</h2>
				<p>The āśrama scheme of life, designed to sublimate the basic instincts of a human being, may now be described briefly. According to this, the life of an individual was divided into four āśramas or stages of life. They are: brahmacarya (student-hood), gārhasthya (married state), vānaprastha (the state of forest recluse) and saṁnyāsa (monkhood).</p>
				<p>Brahmacarya, the first stage of life, was usually of twelve years&#x2019; duration (from the seventh or eighth to the nineteenth or the twentieth year). It was mainly devoted to study and discipline. The student was required to stay in the gurukula or the house of his teacher and learn the sciences—sacred as well as secular—and the arts.</p>
				<p>These teachers in ancient India usually lived in hermitages not far from the towns. The children under their care lived under the same roof without any distinction of wealth and status, all leading a hard, austere life. Serving the teacher and actively participating in the household duties were as much part of their life as learning the Vedas and mastering secular sciences. Begging the food, eschewing the pleasures of life (in which brahmacarya or celibacy was the most important) and abstaining from the affairs of the world were a prominent part of their training.</p>
				<p>After returning home, the student, now a young man, was expected to marry and raise a family. Since marriage was considered as a saṁskāra or a sacrament, and the wife as a life-mate in righteous living, it was not considered as an obstacle to spiritual evolution. The gṛhastha or the householder was expected to earn well by righteous means and live a happy and decent life which had to be socially useful. Among his principal duties were the pañcayajñas or the five daily sacrifices: devayajña (offering oblations to Indra and other deities into the duly consecrated Vedic fires), ṛṣiyajña (appeasing the ṛṣis or the sages by study and teaching of the Vedas), pitṛyajña (obsequial offerings to the departed manes), nṛyajña (feeding guests and hungry persons) and bhūta- yajña (feeding the domestic animals).</p>
				<p>At the approach of old-age, the householder was to hand over the responsi-bilities of the family to his children and retire to the forest along with his wife if she was willing, or alone, if she was not. In this stage known as vānaprastha (vana = forest; prasthāna = going) he was to lead a contemplative life, in spiritual pursuits. It was actually a life preparatory to the final stage, saṁnyāsa.</p>
				<p>When this vanaprasthin or the forest recluse felt enough inner strength to totally renounce all possessions and lead the life of an itinerant monk, he could embrace saṁnyāsa or the monastic life, after sending his wife to be taken care of, by the children. In this stage of life, he had to move about constantly from place to place, begging his food and spending his entire time in contemplation on God. He was to practise self-control, freedom from desires and attachments, and, universal love.</p>
				<p>Though these four āśramas were intended to be adopted successively, excep- tions were allowed in special cases, so that one could take saṁnyāsa even from the first or the second stage.</p>
				<p>It appears that only the brāhmaṇas were considered competent or eligible to adopt saṁnyāsa.</p>
				<p>Some additional—but useful—information about the four āśramas may now be given here:</p>
				<p>A brahmacārin, living in the house of his guru, as a celibate, could, if he so desired, continue specialization in Vedic studies for 24 or even 48 years.</p>
				<p>Eight types of marriage have been mentioned out of which only four were considered as pure and legal. They are: brāhma (the gift of a daughter by the father to a man learned in the Vedas and of good conduct), daiva (the gift of daughter to the presiding priest of a Vedic sacrifice), ārṣa (giving away one&#x2019;s daughter after receiving from the bridegroom [for the fulfilment of the sacred law] a cow and a bull) and prājāpatya (gifting of the daughter by the father, stipulating the condition that the bridegroom remain monogamous and be faithful to her).</p>
				<p>Tying of the maṅgalasūtra (or maṅgalapratisara) (the thread with an amulet, signifying auspiciousness to the bride) by the bridegroom seems to be a later social custom, not mentioned in the dharmaśāstras.</p>
				<h2>Status of Women</h2>
				<p>Here, we can dilate a little, on the status and condition of women in India. During the Vedic age they were given a high place in the society. The mention of women sages like Vāc, Ambhṛṇī, Romaśā and Gārgī in the Vedic lore corroborates this view. Women could undergo the upanayana sacrament and pursue Vedic studies. Those who chose this path were called &#x2018;brahmavādinīs.&#x2019; The others who did not pursue this path but chose to enter into the married life straight-away, were called &#x2018;sadyovadhūs.&#x2019; Co-education seems to have existed in the earlier period. Kṣattriya ladies got training in the use of arms and other martial arts. Both kanyāvivāha (marriage of a pre-puberty girl arranged by her parents) and prauḍhavivāha (marriage after attaining puberty) were prevalent. Under certain circumstances, the girl had the freedom to choose her husband.</p>
				<p>The wife known as &#x2018;gṛhiṇī&#x2019; was considered as &#x2018;half&#x2019; of the husband and constituted the real &#x2018;gṛha&#x2019; or home. She was called &#x2018;sāmrājñī&#x2019; (the queen or the mistress of the home) and had an equal share in the performance of religious rites.</p>
				<p>Divorce and remarriage of women were allowed under very special conditions.</p>
				<p>Shaving of the hair and wearing red saries by the widows or their committing sahagamana (dying on the funeral pyre of their dead husbands) was <em>never</em> compulsory. The former custom seems to have been confined to a small section of the brāhmaṇas, that too in South India. The idea, perhaps, was that their life should be similar to that of the saṁnyāsins.</p>
				<p>It is interesting to note that veśyās (prostitutes) were allowed to make a living, in the society, but were regulated by a code of conduct specially made for them!</p>
				<p>The devadāsī-system (devadāsī = a girl or a woman &#x2018;married&#x2019; to the God in a temple and expected to spend her life as his servant-maid) seems to be a later development.</p>
				<h2>Some More Aspects of Social Life</h2>
				<p>Now, a few more aspects of Hindu social life, may be described:</p>
				<p>Though ātmahatyā or suicide was severely condemned as a sinful act, it was allowed as a ritual under very special conditions such as old-age decrepitude, incurable diseases causing much suffering to oneself and to others, as a prāyaścitta or expiation for heinous sins, for protecting one&#x2019;s religion and honour and so on. As far as possible, such ritual suicides were to be committed in tīrthakṣetras (holy places, places of pilgrimage).</p>
				<p>Formal conversions into Hinduism from alien religions do not seem to have existed. Foreigners just adopted the Hindu way of life and were absorbed into the society.</p>
				<p>However, patitasaṁskāra and śuddhi (expiations and purification for those fallen from the Hindu way of life) (patita = one who is fallen) were very much prevalent and appropriate rites had been prescribed for the same.</p>
				<p>Many taboos existed with regard to food since it was believed that food affected the mind also. Pure food was conducive to purity of mind. Hence, rules and regulations were set out about food and eating—what to eat and what not to eat; how to eat and how not to eat and so on.</p>
				<p>Māṁsabhojana (eating of flesh) was common during the Vedic period. However, it was later on discouraged—though tolerated—due to the influence of Jainism and Buddhism.</p>
				<p>Though surāpāna (drinking of wine) existed, it was severely condemned as a heinous sin.<aside>Somapāna (drinking of the soma juice during sacrifices) was highly eulohized. However, the soma juice was <em>not</em> an intoxicating drink as some seem to misunderstand.</aside></p>
				<p>Pākaśāstra (the culinary art) was well-developed, Nala and Bhīma being the legendary experts in this field.</p>
				<p>Dhūmapāna (smoking of fragrant substances) and use of snuff (special medicinal powders, only for curing certain diseases) have been mentioned. Smoking and taking snuff, as we know them today, did not exist.<aside>Tobacco was intorduced into India by the Westerners in the 15th century.</aside></p>
				<p>Cotton, woollen and silk cloths were in use since several centuries before the Christian era. Unstitched clothes were preferred. Though dhoti and cādar (or chaddar or uttarīya, upper wearing cloth) were common, long shirts, pyjamas and coats were not unknown. Several types of head-dresses, saris and bodices for women were in use.</p>
				<p>Several attractive styles of dressing hair and wearing of ornaments (by both men and women) existed, reflecting the zest for life.</p>
				<p>Wrestling, polo, playing of cards had their origin in India and were quite popular. There were many other games—simple but exciting and exhilarating—inculcating and embellishing good sportsmanship.</p>
				<p>From the foregoing portrayal of the Hindu society one thing stands out as supreme: Life is <em>not</em> a curse but a great gift of God. It must therefore be lived well. Though mokṣa is the ultimate goal of life, <em>all</em> aspects of life should be taken into consideration, each being given its due place, but always in harmony with all the other aspects.</p>
				<p>It is this understanding and conviction of the Hindu religious and social leaders that has imparted stability as well as resilience to the society over the millennia.</p>
				<h3> 5.	Hindu Educational System</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>The Upaniṣads aver that whatever good is done with full knowledge and awareness becomes forceful and fruitful in life. Bhartṛhari, a well-known Sanskrit poet, compares a man without any education to a brute. Albert Einstein (A. D. 1879-1955) seems to concur with him when he likens a man with a specialized knowledge, but lacking in values, to a well-trained dog!</p>
				<p>Vivekānanda, the great patriot-prophet of Modern India, who could feel the pulse of the Indian nation, states that:</p>
				<ul class="loweralpha">
					<li>Education is the panacea for all our ills.</li>
					<li>It is the manifestation of the perfection already in man.</li>
					<li>It is the training by which the current and expression of will are brought under control and become fruitful in life.</li>
					<li>It is life-building, man-making, character-making assimilation of ideas.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>It is rather astonishing that many Western savants<aside>See - Tyron Edwards (Ed.), <em>The New Dictionary of Thoughts</em>, U. S. A., Standard Book Company, 1961.</aside> have practically echoed Vivekānanda&#x2019;s ideas though in different words.</p>
				<p>These can be briefly summarized as follows:</p>
				<ul class="lower alpha">
					<li>Education should teach our children self-control, the art of holding one&#x2019;s passions and prejudices.</li>
					<li>It should instil true and worthy motives, a profound religious feeling and inspire the formation of a great character.</li>
					<li>It should help us to understand the laws of God in nature and to shape our lives to be in consonance with those laws.</li>
					<li>It should pay much greater attention to the development of the powers of the mind than mere learning of facts.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>The ancient and medieval systems of education recognized all these aspects while formulating the policies guiding them. Accordingly all fields of vidyā or knowledge were divided into two broad streams: the parāvidyā (the higher knowledge, the spiritual wisdom) and the aparāvidyā (the lower knowledge, the secular sciences). The latter is needed to live a comfortable life here. The former helps one to be fully prepared for the hereafter. Hence a balanced combination of both, is advocated so that both civilization and culture are imparted.</p>
				<p>It is very interesting to note that even an ancient Upaniṣad—the <em>Chāndogya Upaniṣad</em>—assigned to the period 4000 B. C. to 2500 B. C., mentions as many as fifteen branches of knowledge apart from the four Vedas! Some of them are: Vyākaraṇa (grammar), Pitrya (science of obsequial rites), Gaṇita (mathematics), Daiva (knowledge of the portents), Tarka (logic), Ekāyana (ethics), Bhūtavidyā (science of the spirits), Dhanurveda (martial arts and sciences), Jyautiṣa (astronomy) and Devajanavidyā (the art of preparing perfumes, music, dancing and sculpture).</p>
				<h2>Constituents of an Educational System</h2>
				<p>The three constituents of an educational system are: the teacher, the student and the content as also the methods of education.</p>
				<p>A spiritual teacher—generally called &#x2018;guru&#x2019; or &#x2018;ācārya&#x2019; <aside>Upādhyāta&#x2019; is another term that is sometimes used for a teacher. He is generally described as one who charges fees for his teaching whereas the guru and the ācārya do not.</aside>—was expected to be a &#x2018;śrotriya&#x2019; (learned in the Vedas and allied scriptures) and a &#x2018;brahmaniṣṭha&#x2019; (well- established in Brahman or God). As applied to other fields of knowledge it could mean that he should be an expert both in theory and in practice. An impeccable character, earnestness to teach and a genuine love towards the student were the additional qualities expected in him.</p>
				<p>Eagerness to learn, humility, obedience to the teacher, self-control, absence of laziness in the pursuit of knowledge and willingness to do personal service to the teacher—these were the essential traits a student must possess, to qualify for admission.</p>
				<h2>Gurukulas</h2>
				<p>The teachers kept their students in their own houses. When the number of students became large, these houses would grow into institutions called &#x2018;gurukulas,&#x2019; established by the society, the kings and the rich endowing them with sufficient property and funds so that they could provide quality education, free of cost, to all the students.</p>
				<p>As a result, these gurukulas or educational academies grew to enormous dimensions—both in quality and quantity—thus fulfilling the significance of their very names: guru = enormous, kula = institution. It was not uncommon to find as many as ten thousand students in some of these bigger institutions. Not only out of necessity, but also as a good practice, the senior and better qualified students were made to teach the novices and also supervise over their life and discipline. Though punishments for transgressions existed they were not very severe. Incorrigible students were expelled to save the discipline and reputation of the institution.</p>
				<p>For imparting parāvidyā or spiritual wisdom, an earnest desire to learn and a willingness to undergo tapas or austerity were the only requirements. Neither varṇa nor āśrama nor age seems to have mattered.</p>
				<p>However, for the study of the Vedas and allied sciences like the Vedāṅgas,<aside>Literally, the &#x2018;limbs of the Vedas&#x2019; They are six: Śikṣā (phonetics); Chandas (prosody); Vyākaraṇa (grammer); Nirukta (etymology); Kalpa (liturgics); Jyautiṣa (astronomy).</aside> some restrictions had been imposed. It was open only to the dvijas (the &#x2018;twice-born,&#x2019; the members of the first three castes) and that too after the boys had undergone the upanayana<aside>An important sacrament signifying a birth in a spiritual sense. Wearing a tuft of hair (śikhā) and the sacred thread called yajñopavīta, and the receiving of the holy Gāyatrīmantra are the primary aspects of this sacrament.</aside> ceremony.</p>
				<p>Now, some additional, but miscellaneous, information can be given to get a more complete picture of the system over the centuries:</p>
				<p>Scholarly disputations and philosophical discussions used to take place even in the Vedic period, in meetings generally known as &#x2018;samiti&#x2019; or &#x2018;samāja&#x2019; or &#x2018;pariṣad&#x2019;.</p>
				<p>Vārāṇasī or Kāśī and Takṣaśilā were well-known as great centres of learning even from the 8th century B. C. Some cities like Pāṭalīputra, Vidiśā and Kāñcīpuram were called &#x2018;ghaṭikāsthānas,&#x2019; centres capable of measuring the scholarship of the savants. In such centres there was provision to get training in 14 to 18 branches of learning.<aside>These included subjects useful to all the castes from which the students could choose.</aside> Students were free to acquire a deep knowledge of their religion without any hindrance from the followers of other religions.</p>
				<p>The universities of Takṣaśilā (400 B. C.), Vikramaśilā (A. D. 800) and Nālandā (A. D. 600) had attained phenomenal growth and fame. These universities had several mahāpāṭhaśālās (colleges) and each of these again comprised several lecture halls. There were three huge buildings housing big libraries of invaluable manuscripts.</p>
				<p>Admission tests were very strict and only 20% of the aspirants could succeed in getting admission!</p>
				<p>In the Nālandā University alone there were 8500 students, taught by 1500 teachers with at least 100 lectures delivered per day! Professors like Nāgārjuna, Vasubandhu and Diṅnāga were internationally reputed scholars attracting a large number of students from many foreign countries like China, Japan, Korea, Turkestan, Burma, Gāndhāra (Afghanisthan), Sumātra and Persia. Though education was mostly residential and free, students who could afford to pay, did so.</p>
				<p>Among the residential students Buddhist nuns were also there. However, according to Hiuen Tsang (A. D. 600-664) and I-Tsing (A. D. 635-713), not even a single instance of misconduct had been noticed or discovered, thanks to the high degree of moral discipline kept up by the teachers and the administrators.</p>
				<p>Apart from these Buddhist univer- sities, we learn from Kauṭilya (300 B. C.) and others that there were industrial and vocational training institutions too, imparting specialized training in those branches.</p>
				<p>From all these accounts we find that the education system of the ancient and medieval India was not only highly developed but also capable of delivering to us a lesson or two even now.</p>
				<h2>Script, Language and Literature</h2>
				<p>A passing reference may now be made to some allied topics like the evolution of the script, language and literature. The art of writing was known even during the Vedic age though memorization was preferred and encouraged. The two scripts—Brāhmī and Kharoṣṭhī are known to have existed even in 600 B. C. Both the Devanāgarī and some of the South Indian scripts are its evolutes. Tālapatra (palm-leaf), Bhūrjapatra (birch-bark), wooden plates, cloth (of cotton or silk), leather, stone and bricks were used for writing.</p>
				<p>Evidence is not lacking to conclude that Sanskrit works existed even as early as 600 to 100 B. C. Apart from the Vedas, the epics—the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> and the <em>Mahābhārata</em>—stand out as monuments of exquisitely beautiful literature of a very high standard. The ease and facility with which the Sanskrit language has been used even in the composition of technical subjects bearing on liturgy, medical and health sciences, ethics or linguistics, is astounding.</p>
				<p>The Prākṛt language—a popular derivative of Sanskrit—also had been fairly well-developed even by 500 B. C.</p>
				<p>The following table gives the approximate periods of the evolution of the earliest literary works in other Indian languages:</p>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<td>Assamese</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1300</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Bengali</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1100</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Gujarati</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1000</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Hindi</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1000</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Kannada</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 100</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Kashmiri</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1200</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Malayalam</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 900</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Marathi</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1000</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Oriya</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 700</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Punjabi</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1000</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Sindhi</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1000</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Tamil</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>600 B. C.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Telugu</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>200 B. C.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Urdu</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td>A. D. 1300</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<p>A few important literary works in these languages composed during the early and the medieval periods may now be cited:</p>
				<p>Works of Hemasarasvatī, Harihara Vipra and Śaṅkara Deva in Assamese; the Maṅgala and the Vijaya literature in Bengali; works of Narasī Mehtā and Rāmānanda in Gujarati; compositions of Tulasīdas, Mīrā, Vidyāpati and Kabīr in Hindi; grammar and mythological literature of Keśirāja, Pampa, Ranna and Harihara as also the religious literature of the Śivaśaraṇas and Haridāsas of Kannada; works of Jñāneśvar, Eknāth, Tukārām and others in Marathi; Pañca-sakhās&#x2019; works in Oriya; the <em>Guru-Granth Sāhīb</em> in Punjabi; the <em>Kuraḷ</em> of Tiruvaḷḷuvar, the <em>Tevārams</em> and the <em>Divyaprabandhams</em> of Tamil saints in Tamil; the poetical works of Śrīnātha, Potana, Vemana and Aṇṇamācārya in Telugu.</p>
				<p>From all these, we can conclude that the Indian languages and literature had attained considerable growth and refinement even by the middle ages.</p>
				<h3>6. Hindu Political Institutions</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>Politics in the modern period seems to have become the science of exigencies, mainly because politicians have perfected the art of circumventing God himself !</p>
				<p>But, look at how Atri, one of the seven great sages of the saptarṣi-group, defines the duties of the ruler of a country:</p>
				<p>&#x2018;The five duties of a king are: punishing the wicked, honouring the good, filling up the treasury by right means, meting out justice impartially and protecting the kingdom by all means at his disposal.&#x2019; (<em>Atrisaṁhitā</em> 1.28).</p>
				<p>The Hindu tradition divides the śāstras—authoritative texts of religion and culture—into four broad groups: trayī (the Vedas), ānvīkṣikī (logic), vārtā (economics and politics) and daṇḍanīti (statecraft). However, the <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya (assigned to the period 300 B. C.) deals with the last two topics together and is easily the best work on this subject. Hence any study of the Hindu political system or its institutions will be on a safe track if it follows this ideal text.</p>
				<h2>Generalities</h2>
				<p>Before dealing with the rājyāṅgas or the constituents of the State as detailed by Kauṭilya, a few generalities may now be described. The ancient and medieval writers on statecraft and political science had recognized the absolute need for the authority of the State without which &#x2018;matsya-nyāya&#x2019; (the jungle-law) would prevail. They had also solved the problem of individual freedom versus social order and discipline, by applying, the fundamental principles of the dharma-śāstras.<aside>i.e., the gretest good of the greatest number.</aside> While it was conceded that a system was meant to bring about the general good of the individuals comprising it, no individual or coterie was allowed to usurp the power, boss over or harass the others.</p>
				<p>Democracy was not at all an unknown system in ancient and medieval India. The various public institutions such as the grāmapañcāyats, sabhās and samitis, pariṣads and mahānāḍus practised it fairly extensively. Detailed instructions regarding elections to such institutions are to be found in some works and stone edicts.</p>
				<p>In the Vedic age, the kings were actually social leaders elected by the people. The office of the king as a hereditary institution seems to be a later development. Even then, peoples&#x2019; consent was taken before the appointment of the Yuvarāja (the crown prince, successor to the throne).</p>
				<p>The kingdom was <em>not</em> the personal property of the king. However, he could own lands, buildings and other property from his earnings.</p>
				<p>Republics too were known to have existed even as early as the time of the <em>Aitareya Brāhmaṇa</em> (3000 B. C.). The rulers were expected to be devoted to truth and righteousness. They were always obliged to obey the dictates of the cabinet, called &#x2018;mantripariṣad&#x2019;. Instances are not wanting where the evil rulers were dethroned or even killed!</p>
				<h2>The Rājyāṅgas or the Constituents of a State</h2>
				<p>A brief study of the rājyāṅgas or the constituents of a State may now be taken up. They are: svāmin (king), mantripariṣad (council of ministers), janapada (people), durga and bala (fort and armed forces), kośa (treasury), and mitra (allies).</p>
				<h2>SVĀMIN (The King)</h2>
				<p>The ancient and medieval works on political science recognized the great necessity for the office of the king or the supreme Head of the State. Since everything concerning the State ultimately depended upon him, he was expected to possess some basic qualities and proficiency in some specified fields. They were: physical strength and stamina, expertise in the use of astras (missiles) and śastras (weapons) and a good knowledge of the four branches of learning. To understand the basic principles of dharma and act according to them he must have been properly educated, refined and cultured. Needless to say that self-control was an essential part of this training.</p>
				<p>Since the stability of the society depended on the strict maintenance of dharma by all concerned, and since the varṇa-āśrama-system was considered pivo-tal to it, the king was expected to enforce it strictly. In the process he was obliged to deal with the transgressors very sternly.</p>
				<p>Contrary to the Western concept that the king was the owner of all the land over which he ruled, the Hindu dharma-śāstras ordained that the land <em>did not</em> belong to him as he was only its trustee. However he could have a private property built up from the funds allotted to him in the management of the State. Consequently he could give gifts only from this!</p>
				<p>The king had a fixed, but strenuous, daily routine. Sufficient time was allotted for all legitimate activities such as these: examining the income and expenditure position, preparing a balanced budget, tax-collections, planning welfare schemes for the people, consultations with the ministers, secret meeting with the spies bringing information, inspection of the armed forces and consultation with its officers, spending some time with the family members and personal prayers.</p>
				<p>It goes without saying that elaborate and strict arrangements were made for the personal safety of the king.</p>
				<p>Kings who aspired to become emperors cherished a great desire to perform sacrifices like the Rājasūya or Aśvamedha.</p>
				<h2>MANTRIPARIṢAD (Council of Ministers)</h2>
				<p>The ministry was usually in two tiers—the inner or core group and the outer, larger, council. The inner, the core, group comprised the crown-prince, the prime minister, the royal preceptor (rājaguru) and the commander-in-chief. All policy decisions and framing of laws were done by this inner group. The outer circle could consist of 8 to 23, or even more, persons. They were important officers and heads of departments. This outer circle was mainly concerned with the implementation of the decisions taken by the inner circle.</p>
				<p>The king was advised not to go against the majority decisions.</p>
				<h2>JANAPADA (People)</h2>
				<p>Since the kingdom, the entire governmental system, is meant for the welfare of the people, they must be kept happy and contented. For this they need security and all opportunities for development. The primary means of achieving this is by giving them food, clothing, shelter, health-care, education and avenues for employment. Hence, the king and his government must support and encourage all organizations of public service such as trade guilds, labour unions, educational institutions and self-government agencies like the pañcāyats. As far as possible, all welfare activities must be undertaken through them or with their cooperation.</p>
				<h2>DURGA AND BALA (Forts and Armed Forces)</h2>
				<p>During those days, forts were extremely important for the defence system. They used to be built in important places, including the inaccessible ones, for emergencies. Vantage points were always preferred. They would have outer and inner structures, secret tunnels, proper places for the soldiers, weapons, treasury, food and other essential commodities, and even secret places for hiding. Food and essential commodities were always kept in stock.</p>
				<p>The espionage system was well- organized.</p>
				<p>There were proper provisions and methods for the raising and training of the armed forces which consisted of four divisions: infantry, cavalry, chariot-force and elephant-force.</p>
				<p>Since ship-building was well-known even in the early period, powerful navies formed part of the armed forces.</p>
				<p>During wars and invasions, very strict rules were followed. A few of these are:</p>
				<p>The soldiers should not fight with unarmed persons. Weak persons, women and children, sick people and refugees must never be harmed. No damage should be caused to agricultural fields and civilian industries. There should be no looting or molestation in the conquered territory. Local religions and customs must be honoured and never interfered with. Closest relative of the conquered king, if found fit, may be installed as the new king. He was to be a sāmanta (feudatory chief) paying tributes and supplying the army when the conquering king needs it. He had complete autonomy in all other respects.</p>
				<p>People of the conquered country had to be befriended by proper means.</p>
				<h2>KOŚA (Treasury)</h2>
				<p>No activity of the State can be undertaken unless there is enough money and wealth to back it up. Hence, collection of taxes was a primary duty of the State.</p>
				<p>The taxes levied were generally light or moderate, and never heavy. Land revenue was the main tax. Irrigation tax was also collected wherever irrigation had been provided. The tax was generally one-sixth or one-fifth of the produce. Arts, crafts and trades were also taxed. Religious and educational institutions, disabled persons, unemployed people, sādhus (recluses and monks) and brāhmaṇas (devoted to Vedic learning and an austere life) were exempted. During droughts, famines and other national emergencies taxes were either abolished or deferred.</p>
				<p>Emergency funds were built up in a separate treasury and were never touched except in grave and critical situations.<aside>The sage Vidyāraṇya (A. D. 1350), the chief architect of the Vijayanagar Empire, is said to have built up an emergency treasury worth 920 million varahas (gold coins) and instructed the princes Harihara and Bukka never to touch it except in extreme emergencies.</aside></p>
				<p>There was a constant and strict supervision of accounts. Tax-collectors were expected to behave humanely and invited severe punishments for cruelty.</p>
				<p>The tax money was apportioned to various public purposes by proper budgetary procedures.</p>
				<h2>MITRA (Ally)</h2>
				<p>For the consolidation of the State and help in emergencies, friends and allies were considered absolutely necessary. The first two of the four upāyas or means, viz., sāma (a spirit of reconciliation) and dāna (the spirit of give and take), come in handy in this regard. (The other two—bheda [splitting the enemy ranks] and daṇḍa [violent means including war]—were meant to be used against enemies and that too as a last resort.)</p>
				<p>Potential enemies, when not amenable to sāma and dāna, were to be neutralized.</p>
				<p>Friendly countries were to be helped in their hour of need. Pacts signed were strictly honoured. There was to be no invasion on a king who was virtuous and was ruling according to dharma!</p>
				<h2>Some Salient Features</h2>
				<p>It will be interesting to note some more salient features of the Hindu political system here.</p>
				<p>Though the king generally appointed all the important officers of the State, local officers in the villages and towns were elected by the people, the process of election being described in detail in the concerned works. The central government never interfered in the local affairs. The local customs and traditions were honoured.</p>
				<p>The system of census, not only of people but also of domesticated animals, existed.</p>
				<p>Administration of justice was in the hands of upright and important officers. The varṇa-āśrama-dharmas and the duties of the various castes were enforced as strictly as possible. However there was also the freedom to choose one&#x2019;s profession.</p>
				<p>Punishments of various types for the transgression of the laws—both civil and criminal—existed. They ranged from fines and confiscation of property up to banishment and even death.</p>
				<p>All efforts were made to maintain peace in the society since it was conducive to the development of culture.</p>
				<p>Temples and places of worship were looked upon with respect and jealously guarded.</p>
				<p>It is thus seen that the political system of Hindu India was never inferior to any other similar system in the world.</p>
				<h3>7. Hindu Economics</h3>
				<h2>Importance of Artha or Wealth</h2>
				<p>&#x2018;A sound mind in a sound body&#x2019; is a sound saying. We can perhaps adopt it to describe a welfare State as: &#x2018;A sound State in a sound economy!&#x2019; And, what is economy but the art of spending less than what is earned? Does it not prove to be the philosopher&#x2019;s stone ultimately?</p>
				<p>The proverbial wealth of ancient and early medieval India as eloquently described by many a foreign traveller was not a little due to the wholesome economic policies of the State as well as the industriousness of its people. The basis of this was the philosophy of the four puruṣārthas—ends or goals of human life—which gave artha or wealth also a decent place in life, though subservient to dharma or righteousness.</p>
				<p>Wealth, called &#x2018;artha&#x2019;, is material in form. It can be acquired and consumed. Since it can become scarce unlike air or water, is attractive!</p>
				<p>Goddess Lakṣmī is the presiding deity of wealth. Allegorically speaking, material wealth, professions that bring wealth and persons practising those professions are the three legs of the tripod upon which the goddess rests. Hindu works dealing with the artha-śāstra (the science of wealth) cover all these aspects.</p>
				<h2>Characteristics of Hindu Economics</h2>
				<p>The general characteristics of Hindu economics may be stated as follows:</p>
				<p>The entire State or the society is more important than the individual. Hence, the individual good may have to be, sometimes, sacrificed for the good of the society as a whole.</p>
				<p>Economic polices should not generally go against the principles of dharma though it may not always be possible to follow all of them strictly.</p>
				<p>There are quite a few special characteristics too. They are, according to the <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya (300 B. C.):—</p>
				<p>Though the State as a whole should be given supreme importance vis-a-vis the subjects, it was obligatory on its part to:</p>
				<ol>
					<li> treat the subjects as its children and devise welfare schemes for them;</li>
					<li> help them in periods of crises like war and natural calamities like famine, floods, earthquake etc.;</li>
					<li> moderate the prices of commodities so that people are not exploited;</li>
					<li> control the quality of goods;</li>
					<li> help trade and commerce by providing means of transport, communication, security, tax-concessions in foreign trade and so on;</li>
					<li> protect agriculture in all its aspects;</li>
					<li> create job-opportunities for the people.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>We thus see that all the important economic aspects of a modern welfare State are covered by this scheme.</p>
				<h2>Planning and Budgeting</h2>
				<p>Planning a properly balanced budget was a very important aspect of administration. Revenue from various sources had to be estimated and allotment of funds for essential expenditure made by the State officials, personally supervised by the king himself. Daily checking of accounts by competent authorities was recommended.</p>
				<p>Land revenue seems to have been the major source of income. Generally, one-sixth of the produce was collected in kind. Excellent irrigation system is known to have existed even during Candragupta Maurya&#x2019;s time (325 B. C.). Hence irrigation cess was also laid where it had been provided.</p>
				<p>Other sources of income were trade, commerce, industry and mines. The rate of taxation used to be around one-tenth. Sometimes, a few mines and industries were also run directly by the governments to augment their income. Defence industries were directly under the State. Forest wealth also was tapped by the government itself. The concept of nationalisation was not unknown.</p>
				<p>Apart from fines levied for the transgressions of the laws of the land, special cesses collected during emergencies like war or victory expeditions were also a source of income.</p>
				<p>Before levying a tax, the king was expected to study the time, place and circumstances connected with it. The level of taxation had to be bearable and not hurt the people too much. Though enough income had to be generated for the State, means and methods employed were to be fair and just.</p>
				<p>Details regarding expenditure given in the Hindu works on political science and economics are, comparatively speaking, less than those concerning income. Major part of the income—sometimes as high as 50%—was apportioned for defence, including internal law and order. Unsettled conditions in the country due to frequent foreign invasions as also ambitions of the rulers for conquests might have been responsible for this. A lot of money was therefore spent on building up and the training of the five limbs of the armed forces, the stores, secret services, armoury and so on.</p>
				<p>A reserve fund for emergencies had to be built up by saving one-sixth or one-fourth of the income. A part had also to be given as privy-purse to the king for his personal expenses.</p>
				<p>Other items of expenditure were almost the same as we have today: general administration, department of justice, roads and bridges as also navigation, grants to local self-governments, religious and cultural institutions, hospitals, maintenance of orphans and other helpless persons.</p>
				<p>Banking system was well-organized. Loans usually carried an interest of 15% or even more.</p>
				<h2>Trade and Commerce</h2>
				<p>Trade and commerce—both internal and external—were very flourishing even in the pre-Christian era. Contacts had been established with China, Mongolia, Japan, Korea, Egypt, Troy, Babylonia, Assiria, Greece, Crete, Rome, Mexico and other countries.</p>
				<p>Trade by sea was thriving well. Several seaports have been mentioned in the ancient works including the Buddhist Jātaka tales and travellers&#x2019; accounts. The Vijayanagar empire itself had 300 ports!</p>
				<p>Great encouragement was given to foreign trade by providing tax-concessions and other facilities. The passport-visa system existed. Foreigners coming for trade were given sufficient protection.</p>
				<p>The transport and communication system kept pace with trade.</p>
				<h2>Merchant Organizations</h2>
				<p>There were trade-guilds and merchant-organizations of several types known by different nomenclatures such as: śreṇī, mahānāḍu, maṇimaṅgala, saṅgha, pūga and gaṇa. They had their special constitutions to control their professions in all aspects. They were even permitted to have their own private armies. They were quite powerful in national life. The rulers rarely interfered with their working.</p>
				<h2>Arts and Crafts</h2>
				<p>A large number of arts and crafts have been mentioned in the ancient and medieval works thereby signifying a high degree of industrial development. Some of them, for instance, are: weaving, laundry, tailoring, carpentry, oil-extraction, goldsmithy, blacksmithy, flower-garland making, mat-making, leather industry, potmaking and so on. These crafts were generally assigned to or undertaken by the castes known for them. In bigger towns and cities there were separate streets for each craft and its products. Finished goods were examined by experts and seals were put on them for certifying the quality. If and when necessary, prices were also controlled.</p>
				<p>Partnerships in general, and also between the capitalists and workmen, existed. They were well-regulated by appropriate laws and rules.</p>
				<h2>Units of Money and Measurements</h2>
				<p>Coins made of gold, silver and copper did exist even by 600 B. C., and were used as money, though the barter system too existed, perhaps, side by side. Known by such names as hiraṇyapiṇḍa, niṣka, suvarṇa, śatamāna, pāda, purāṇa, kārṣāpaṇa and paṇa, they were of various shapes—square, rectangular and circular. Certain signs and symbols were embossed on these coins, some of which resemble the Harappan seals. Tables of values of these coins have been given in some books like the <em>Līlāvatī</em> of Bhāskara (12th cent.)</p>
				<p>Units of measurement whether of length (like aṅgula, hasta or yojana), or of weight (like guñja, pala and droṇa) or of time (like nimeṣa, kṣaṇa or ghaṭikā) had also been well-developed. It is interesting to note that the unit of length (or scale) shown by the sculptor of the image of Gomaṭeśvara at Śravaṇabeḷagoḷa (Karna-taka) is almost the same as the French meter!</p>
				<h2>Epilogue</h2>
				<p>At a time when the average Indian&#x2019;s admiration for the West is growing at an alarming pace, that too at the cost of one&#x2019;s national pride and self-respect, an earnest study of our ancient and medieval history can be of great help to boost it.</p>
				<p>A sound economic philosophy, expansive trade and commerce, well-organized trade-guilds, a good coinage system, sensi-ble taxation laws, building up reserves for emergencies—which have characterised our political and social administration, should instil righteous pride in the mind and heart of every true Indian.</p>
				<h3> 8.	The Hindu Judicial System</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>No society can survive for long, despite immense wealth and military might, if it does not have a proper system of jurisprudence that can give justice impartially to all its members. Impartiality is the life of justice, and justice, of good government. There can never be any justice without mature wisdom which alone knows how to strike a balance between individual liberty and social good. This is exactly what the sources of Hindu law have done, right from the Vedas upto the smṛtis and dharmaśāstras, as also the various nibandhas (digests).</p>
				<p>However, the <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya (300 B. C.) being the oldest among the best organized works on secular codes of law, can throw a lot of light on Hindu jurisprudence. It refers to more than 12 authors of the earlier period. It may hence be safely relied upon while discussing or presenting this subject.</p>
				<h2>Origin of the Hindu Judicial System</h2>
				<p>&#x2018;Sabhās&#x2019; were known to have existed even from the Vedic times. They were judicial assemblies consisting of good people—called Vṛddhas or the wise ones—who were experts in the observance of satya (truth) and dharma (righteous conduct).</p>
				<p>Four kinds of courts of justice are sometimes described in the ancient works: pratiṣṭhitā (one established in a place), apratiṣṭhitā (a mobile court), mudritā (the court of a judge appointed by the king who is authorised to use the royal seal) and śāsitā or śāstritā (the court in which the king himself presides).</p>
				<h2>Independence of the Judiciary</h2>
				<p>The outstanding feature of the judiciary in any civilized society is its independence from the control of the executive. This has jealously been guarded by the Hindu works on political science. According to them even the prince is equal to a private citizen before law. This is because dharma is considered supreme and inviolable!</p>
				<p>As at present, the judges used to be appointed from among the lawyers. Generally brāhmaṇas of learning and character were selected, though members of other castes also could be appointed if qualified. The qualifications generally insisted upon were: self-control, reputation of the family (from which he comes) for satya and dharma, impartiality, absence of excitement, steadfastness and energy in the performance of duties.</p>
				<h2>The Court</h2>
				<p>The court generally comprised of a judge who presided and an odd number of juries (3 or 5 or 7). Persons well-versed in law were often invited to attend the Sabhā (or meeting) and were expected to speak if called upon to do so. However, there was to be no public participation.</p>
				<p>Though the king might be present he would not decide the cases directly. His council would include the Chief Justice. He would of course see that the sentence, once pronounced, is carried out faithfully.</p>
				<p>Full records of the proceedings were kept. Justice was administered openly. Earlier judgements were given due weightage before new ones were delivered.</p>
				<h2>System of Judiciary and Judicial Administration</h2>
				<p>The Chief Justice (called prāḍvivāka) and Minister of Justice (known as dharmādhikaraṇa) formed the core of the judicial system and of the judicial administration. The Chief Justice presided over the Supreme Court at the capital. The Minister of Justice prescribed the law and the procedure after consulting the jury.</p>
				<p>Before finally deciding a case, all material connected with pratyakṣa (direct evidence), anumāna (inference) and upamāna (analogy) were to be gathered and thoroughly examined.</p>
				<p>Justice was meted out at several levels with a provision for appeal to the next higher authority. They were:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>The <em>Kula Courts</em>: They consisted of kinsmen only and were confined to personal and family laws and customs.</li>
					<li>The <em>Śreṇī Courts:</em> They comprised representatives of traders and artisans belonging to different tribes but practising the same profession.</li>
					<li>The <em>Pūga Courts:</em> They were an assemblage of townsmen or meetings of persons belonging to various tribes and professions, but inhabiting the same place.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>The decisions of the Kula courts could be revised by the Śreṇī courts and of the Śreṇī courts by the Pūga courts. The court of the prāḍvivāka was the next higher authority, the court of the monarch or the sovereign being the highest.</p>
				<p>There were also the Gaṇa courts, courts administering the laws of the Hindu republics which have been praised highly by the Greek writers on India. The laws framed by these courts were called &#x2018;samaya&#x2019; (decision taken together in an assembly).</p>
				<h2>Judicial Procedure</h2>
				<p>No civil action could be started without a complaint, which again, could be lodged only by the aggrieved person. A regular petition to the court was necessary. This was taken down by a &#x2018;lekhaka&#x2019; or a writer, well-versed in the legal terms. He could put questions to the plaintiff for clarifications if necessary. Then summons were issued to the concerned person. Obedience to the summons was enforced, by sanctions or legal restraint, called &#x2018;āsedha&#x2019;.</p>
				<p>This restraint could be of four kinds, as to: sthāna or place; pravāsa or journey; time or period; and, certain actions. In other words, till the dispute was settled, the defendant (or respondent) should not go out of his house or place of residence, should not undertake any journey, should present himself at the court on the day and at the time fixed for it and should not do certain actions connected with the dispute.</p>
				<p>The plaintiff was required to repeat the charges in detail in the presence of the defendant. This was taken down again by the lekhaka. Any discrepancy between the earlier and later versions of the complaint could lead to the dismissal of the case.</p>
				<p>Pleading had to be precise, comprehensive, unequivocal, consistent and susceptible of proof.</p>
				<p>Defence had to be confined only to the points raised, answers being unhesitating, clear and consistent.</p>
				<p>The defence could take any one of these four forms: 1) Confession; 2) Denial; 3) Special exception; 4) Plea of a former judgement.</p>
				<p>The judicial proceedings were generally in four stages: the plaint, the reply, the trial and the deliberations followed by a decree.</p>
				<p>There were rules guiding the trial. A surety had to be given by both the parties before the trial. The plaintiff had the right to begin the arguments but had to give enough evidence in support of his cause. Counter claims by the defendant were not entertained until the original case was disposed off.</p>
				<p>Once a litigation was started, the parties involved could not evolve any compromise formula between themselves without the consent of the court.</p>
				<p>There were rules concerning evidence. Generally three types of evidence were recognised: 1) documents; 2) witnesses; 3) conduct.</p>
				<p>Of conduct, possession was always taken as evidence giving rise to a presumption of title.</p>
				<p>Persons coming from respectable families, deeply religious by temperament and hence devoted to truth, who were straightforward were considered as reliable witnesses.</p>
				<p>Interesting descriptions of an untruthful witness are given. Some of them are: shifting the position constantly; licking the corner of one&#x2019;s own lips; sweat on the forehead; change of colour of the countenance; faltering speech; contradictory statements.</p>
				<h2>Judgement</h2>
				<p>The judgement—called vidhāna or jayapatra—was given at the end of the trial. Enough time was taken for considering all the aspects of the case. But unnecessary delays were also avoided.</p>
				<p>A typical judgement was expected to contain:</p>
				<ul class="lower alpha">
					<li>a summary of the proceedings;</li>
					<li>evidence of all the concerned parties;</li>
					<li>deliberations thereon, by the court;</li>
					<li>the law applicable in the case; and</li>
					<li>the signature of the judge with the royal seal.</li>
				</ul>
				<h2>Punishment</h2>
				<p>Equality of all, before the law of the land, was not only stressed, but also vigorously implemented. Even the king was not exempted. In fact, for the same offence, persons with higher social status were given more severe punishments. The principle was: greater the position and authority, greater were the responsibility and the standard of behaviour expected.</p>
				<p>Punishment meted out was of various kinds and types: public censure and rebuke; fines and confiscation of property; banishment; corporal punishment including branding or severing limbs or even death.</p>
				<p>The primary object of punishment was always the protection of the law- abiding people. If the evil-doers were kept under check by the fear of punishment, the chances of social security and order would be much more.</p>
				<h2>Conclusion</h2>
				<p>The Hindu judicial system, many of whose features are found even in the modern days, offers a good field of research. Its findings can certainly enrich our field of jurisprudence helping us further towards the goal of ideal justice through human agencies.</p>
				<h3>9. Contribution of the 	Hindus to Science</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>The contribution of Hindu India to the field of science is no less significant than its contribution to the field of spiritual wisdom. The sages of India never considered religion and science as two conflicting areas of knowledge. To them both were equally important, one being the quest for the truth within and the other, without. They were actually two facets of the same vidyā or science. That is why they were called parāvidyā (higher knowledge) and aparāvidyā (lower knowledge).</p>
				<p>The word &#x2018;ṛṣi&#x2019;—generally translated as a &#x2018;sage&#x2019;—just signifies a man of knowledge, in <em>any field</em> for that matter, since it is derived from the root verb &#x2018;ṛṣ&#x2019; (&#x2018;to know&#x2019;). Thus, if Vasiṣṭha and Vyāsa were ṛṣis in the field of spiritual wisdom, Dhanvantari, Varāhamihira and Bhāskara were ṛṣis in the fields of medicine, astronomy and mathematics.</p>
				<p>One thing which was basic to all these ṛṣis was that their jñāna or knowledge was always meant to be used within the perimeters of dharma, for the universal good of mankind.</p>
				<p>It is necessary to stress one more point here. The discovery by these sages that Brahman, the basis of the external universe and Ātman, the basis of the internal world, are ultimately one and are pure consciousness, has obliterated the walls between these two fields of knowledge.</p>
				<p>A brief account of the various sciences as developed in this country during the ancient and medieval ages may now be given, arranging them in the English alphabetical order for easy reference.</p>
				<h2>Architecture and Town Planning</h2>
				<p>The Harappa and Mohenjadāro excavations (3000 B. C.) and the ancient temples (A. D. 325)—including the cave temples—have shown the highly developed state of Hindu architecture and town planning. There is a lot of advanced scientific literature on these subjects such as: <em>Mānasāra</em>, <em>Mayamata</em>, <em>Mānasollāsa</em>, <em>Sanatkumāra Vāstuśāstra</em> and so on. Some of the purāṇas like <em>Viṣṇudharmottara</em> also deal with these subjects.</p>
				<p>The word &#x2018;Vāstuśilpa&#x2019; used to indicate this science is comprehensive in scope and includes all types of building construction, forts and other military structures as also town planning. The burnt bricks, wood-work, houses, wells, public tanks, sewerage system, swimming pools and granaries discovered at the Harappan sites bespeak of the highly developed state of this science.</p>
				<p>Megasthanes (300 B. C.) has given an interesting account of Candragupta&#x2019;s palace, fort and other structures. The stūpas and pillars <aside>These pillars, 9 to 12 meters (30 to 40 ft.) in height, sometimes weighing as much as 50 tonnes and highly polished, are a marvel of the Mauryan period of architecture</aside> of Aśoka, the various images of Buddha and the cave architecture belonging to the Mauryan Period (3rd century B. C.) stand as monumental proof of the development of architecture of that period.</p>
				<p>Apart from buildings like palaces or defence structures like the forts, temples have always been a source of strength and inspiration for the rulers of Hindu India. Hence there was a steady growth of temples—both in quality and in artistry—over the centuries. The temples of the Gupta period (4th to 7th centuries A. D.), the temples of Bhubaneshwar and Puri as also Konarak in Orissa (8th to 13th centuries A. D.) are cases to the point. The huge temples of South India built by the various dynasties like the Pallavas (7th to 10th centuries A. D.), the Coḷas (10th to 12th centuries A. D.), by the Vijayanagara kings (14th to 16th centuries A. D.) and by the Nāyaks of Madurai (17th century A. D.) are monuments of marvel. Mention should also be made of the cave temples of Bādāmi (in Karnataka) belonging to the 6th century A. D., the Gomaṭeśvara image cut out of a single rock of granite (nearly 20 metres or 57 ft. in height) in 983 A. D. and the famous temples at Belur, Halebid and Somanathpur (all in Karnataka) known for their exquisite carvings in stone (12th century A. D.) built by the Hoysaḷas.</p>
				<h2>Astronomy</h2>
				<p>At a time when Vedic sacrifices were all important, there was a great need to determine the correct times for performing them. This gave rise to a new branch of knowledge called &#x2018;Jyotiṣa&#x2019; or &#x2018;Jyautiṣa&#x2019; which was deemed as a Vedāṅga, a subsidiary science of Veda. This was the origin of Hindu astronomy and dates back to 1400 B. C. The Vedic sages were fully aware of the following astronomical facts and phenomena:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>The earth is round, rotates on its own axis and also round the sun.</li>
					<li>Sunlight has seven colours, allegorically described as seven horses.</li>
					<li>The twelve signs of the zodiac.</li>
					<li>There are 366 days in a year.</li>
					<li>The number of days per month is $29 \dfrac{16}{21}$ or 29.762.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>The <em>Sūryasiddhānta</em>, considered as a revealed work, is the earliest of the available works on Hindu astronomy. It was thoroughly revised by Varāhamihira (6th century A. D.). The works attributed to him are: <em>Bṛhajjātaka</em>, <em>Laghujātaka</em>, <em>Pañcasiddhāntikā</em> and <em>Bṛhatsaṁhitā</em>. Other great names in the field are: Āryabhaṭa I (b. A. D. 476), Brahmagupta (7th century A. D.) and Bhāskara (12th century A. D.)</p>
				<h2>Botany</h2>
				<p>A fairly good knowledge of the botanical sciences existed in the Hindu India not only in the post-Vedic period, but also in the Vedic. The Vedic Āryans were aware of what is now termed &#x2018;photosynthesis.&#x2019; The <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya (300 B. C.) refers to gulma- vṛkṣa-āyurveda (science of bushy plants and trees). A lot of information regarding soils, seed selection, sowing, germination, grafting and cutting, rotation of crops, plant classification and so on, is found in some purāṇas like the <em>Agnipurāṇa</em> (A. D. 800).</p>
				<p>An account of the different parts of a plant body like the roots and shoots, stem and branches, leaves, flowers and fruits are found in the <em>Ṛgveda</em>, <em>Atharva-veda</em>, <em>Taittirīya Saṁhitā </em>and <em>Vājasaneyī Saṁhitā</em>.</p>
				<p>Indian literature of the post-Vedic period (600 B. C.—A. D. 600) bears ample evidence to a knowledge of morphology, physiology, ecology and taxonomy of plants. The famous Sanskrit lexicon, the <em>Amarakoṣa</em> of Amarasiṁha (A. D. 400), has enumerated more than three hundred species of plants. Medicinal herbs and plants naturally received great attention due to their being closely associated with Āyurveda, the science of medicine and surgery. All the methods of propagation now known to us were common knowledge. To mention a few: propagation by seeds, roots, cuttings, graftings and leaves. Treatises such as <em>Arthaśāstra</em>, <em>Bṛhatsaṁhitā</em> and <em>Manusaṁhitā</em> refer to all of them.</p>
				<p>Plants had been regarded, even from the Vedic times, as living organisms.</p>
				<p>In the naming of plants, a rational and scientific procedure was followed, which was in no way inferior to the modern methods.</p>
				<p>During the medieval period (A. D. 600 to 1500) botanical research—including the possibilities of developing new species—got further fillip, as evidenced in the <em>Śārṅgadhara Paddhati</em> of Śārṅgadhara (14th century).</p>
				<h2>Chemistry</h2>
				<p>The beginnings of the science of chemistry in India may be traced to the philosophical speculations of certain schools like the Nyāya-Vaiśeṣika and development of certain practical arts like decorated earthenware and porcelain, burnt bricks, glass beads, alloys and medicines, which presuppose a practical knowledge of the chemical processes involved.</p>
				<p>The Nyāya-Vaiśeṣika schools put forth the atomic theory of matter, the permutation and combination of which atomic particles ultimately lead to the whole creation.</p>
				<p>The people of the Indus Valley Civilization (2500 B. C.) were skilled in employing a wide range of chemical processes. Materials recovered from the excavation sites at Harappa and Mohenjodāro such as water-pots, vessels, earthenware, pottery (ordinary and glazed), jewellery and seals, confirm this conclusion.</p>
				<p>References to tanning of hides, dyeing of garments with certain natural vegetable colouring materials and to preparation of fermented drinks found in the Vedic texts bespeak of a knowledge of chemistry, however elementary that may be.</p>
				<p>There was a phenomenal growth of Āyurveda, the science of medicine and surgery, during the period 600 B. C.—A. D. 800. This automatically led to the develop-ment of the science of chemistry too.</p>
				<p>The fact that chemical reactions generated heat and <em>vice versa</em> was known even by A. D. 400.</p>
				<p>The <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya (300 B. C.) and the <em>Saṁhitās</em> of Caraka (A. D. 300) and Suśruta (A. D. 500) contain a wealth of information regarding chemistry also, along with that of metallurgy and medicine. Procedures for extracting and purifying metals like gold, silver, copper and lead, preparation of various kinds of fermented liquors and anhydrous alcohol by distillation, formation of sulphides, preparation and properties of alkali carbonates and caustic alkali as well as of neutralization of the alkali by an acid—these and many more things have been described in these works. Other subjects referred to are: processes of calcination, distillation, sublimation, and steaming; grouping of organic substances; vegetable as well as animal oils; poisons of several varieties and so on.</p>
				<p>An elaborate discussion about the chemistry of digestion of food in human beings is found in the <em>Carakasaṁhitā</em> and <em>Aṣṭāṅgahṛdaya-saṁhitā</em> of Vāgbhaṭa II (A. D. 650).</p>
				<p>The process of melting, refining, and colouring glass was known even as early as the sixth century B. C. as borne out by the discovery of the earliest specimen of glass at the Bhirmound in Takṣaśilā or Taxila (now in Pakistan). The art of making painted, decorated and glazed pottery was current even by 300 B. C. So also the use of indigo, lac, turmeric, resin and red ochre.</p>
				<p>In medieval India, the rise of Tāntric cults interested in alchemy gave a further push to the development of the chemical sciences and engineering. Preparation of an elixir of life and conversion of base metals into gold were the twofold objectives of the alchemists.</p>
				<p>The <em>Rasārṇava</em> (12th cent.), the <em>Dhātuvāda</em> (8th cent.), the <em>Rasendra-cūḍāmaṇi</em> (13th cent.) were some of the treatises composed during the middle-ages which dealt with subjects like extraction of copper, purification of mercury by distillation, making of cuprous sulphide and sulphuric acid.</p>
				<p>Though chemistry was developed more as a handmaid of other streams of knowledge like the health sciences or mining and metallurgy, the contribution of ancient and medieval India to it is significant.</p>
				<h2>Mathematics</h2>
				<p>The Vedic Hindus were deeply devoted to yāgas or sacrifices. Performance of these sacrifices needed a fair degree of knowledge in two fields of science: geometry and astronomy. The former was needed in designing and building suitable Vedis or altars, generally with bricks. The latter became necessary while fixing the correct time or period for the performance of the sacrifice itself. The Śulbasūtras developed the former and the Jyautiṣa, the latter. Signs for numbers, counting up to very huge quantities like parārdha (10<sup>14</sup>), the decimal and the duodecimal systems, the concept of zero and infinity, quadratic equations, surds and indeterminate analysis were all familiar subjects to the ancient and medieval Hindus.</p>
				<p>Another unique development in India has been the use of word-numerals such as kha, ākāśa (the sky or space) or śūnya (void) to represent zero, kṣiti, dharā and pṛthvī (the earth) to represent the figure 1 and so on. This system has enabled the authors of mathematical treatises to versify their ideas and express them concisely.</p>
				<p>The methods of extracting the square and the cube roots of integral numbers can be traced to Āryabhaṭa I (A. D. 499) and Brahmagupta (7th cent. A. D.).</p>
				<p>So far about arithmetic.</p>
				<p>Let us now turn to algebra.</p>
				<p>The construction of sacrificial altars and the arrangements for laying bricks for them posed serious problems to the Vedic Āryans. While attempting to solve them, they discovered geometrical methods of algebra. The <em>Śulbasūtras</em> of Āpastamba (400 B. C.), Baudhāyana (600 B. C.), Kātyā-yana (A. D. 400) and others give the solutions of linear, quadratic, simultaneous or even indeterminate equations.</p>
				<p>Algebra was called &#x2018;Kuṭṭakagaṇita&#x2019; first. The term &#x2018;Bījagaṇita&#x2019; used in the modern period was given by one Pṛthūdaka Svāmin (A. D. 860).</p>
				<p>In the <em>Sthānāṅgasūtras</em> (100 B. C.) simple, quadratic and cubic equations are given.</p>
				<p>Coming to geometry as such, it had its origin in the building of Vedic sacrificial altars. The so-called Pythagoras theorem had already been enunciated by Baudhā-yana (600 B. C.). Problems like the area of a quadrilateral or the diagonals of a cyclic quadrilateral have been successfully solved by Brahmagupta in his Brahmasphuṭa-siddhānta.</p>
				<p>Trigonometry evolved as an integral part of Astronomy. The functions of sine and cosine were called &#x2018;jyā&#x2019; and &#x2018;kojyā&#x2019;. A number of elementary formulae—such as sin (90-𝜃) = cos 𝜃 ; sin 2𝜃 = z sin cos 𝜃—as also trigonometrical series had also been developed.</p>
				<p>Rudimentary ideas of Integral and Differential calculus are found in the works of Brahmagupta and Bhāskara II (A. D. 1150).</p>
				<p>It is thus seen that the Hindus of ancient and medieval India were familiar with almost all branches of mathematical sciences to a greater or lesser extent.</p>
				<h2>Medicine and Surgery</h2>
				<p>A sound body is fit to house a sound mind. A balanced combination of these two is in a far better position to manifest the spirit within—the ātman—which is always sound! Realizing this, a great and useful science of health in <em>all</em> its aspects, called &#x2018;Āyurveda&#x2019; or the Science of Longevity, was handed over to us by Brahmā the Creator, through the twin deities Aśvins and then the sages like Bharadvāja. This is how Hindu tradition traces the origin of the medical sciences.</p>
				<p>Though the elements of Āyurveda are found even in the <em>Ṛgveda</em>, it is in the <em>Atharvaveda</em> that a more detailed and a systematic account is found. Treatment of diseases like leucoderma, leprosy, tuberculosis, jaundice as also the sciences of dentistry, making and fixing of artificial limbs, means of virilification and treatment of the diseases of the eye were known to exist. A fairly good practical knowledge of human physiology was possessed by the vaidyas or the doctors. Even transplantation of eye-ball has been mentioned in some works!</p>
				<p>Among the best known classical texts of Āyurveda are the <em>Saṁhitās</em> of Caraka (A. D. 200) and Suśruta (A. D. 400). The <em>Aṣṭāṅgahṛdaya</em> of Vāgbhaṭa II (early 8th century) is another well-known and authoritative treatise.</p>
				<p>The standard texts generally deal with aṣṭāṅgas or eight subjects. They are: Kāyacikitsā (therapeutics), Śalyatantra (major surgery), Śālākyatantra (minor surgery including E.N.T.), Bhūtavidyā (psychiatry), Kaumārabhṛtya-tantra (paediatrics), Agadatantra (toxicology), Rasāyana-tantra (geriatrics) and Vājī-karaṇa-tantra (virilification).</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>Some additional information given in these texts as also the <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya may now be listed: details of the various bones and nālās or nāḍīs (blood-vessels and nerves) in the human body; duties of the toxicologists and nurses; rules and regulations for the surgeons; certain modes and methods of treatment like the application of oils and ointments; bandaging techniques; surgical instruments and how to use them and so on.</p>
				<p>Foreign travellers like Megasthanes (302-288 B. C.) and Strabo (54-24 B. C.) have declared that:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>the Hindus of India attained longevity due to good food, pure air and good habits;</li>
					<li>the Hindu physicians and surgeons were greater experts in their field than their contemporary Greeks;</li>
					<li>even Alexander preferred to employ the Hindu physicians to look after his army-men;</li>
					<li>Aśoka had established hospitals not only for human beings but also for animals.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>It is interesting to note that a very strict code of conduct has been laid down in these medical works for the doctor. They are:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>He should treat his patients to the best of his ability since they trust him for their lives.</li>
					<li>He should refuse to treat morally depraved persons since they are a scourge to the society.</li>
					<li>He should not take up terminal cases where he is sure that death is imminent, as also refuse to treat persons suffering from incurable diseases.</li>
					<li>Once he agrees to treat a patient, he should provide him with proper medical and nursing facilities and also treat him kindly.</li>
					<li>He should never attend to a woman patient in the absence of her husband or guardians.</li>
					<li>All professional information should be kept strictly confidential.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>Many of these Indian medical treatises were translated into the Arabic language and their practices introduced into Europe by the Arab physicians.</p>
				<h2>Military Science</h2>
				<p>Even from the most ancient times the Hindu soldiers of the various armies of the Indian kings were wellknown for their valour as well as the use of weapons. The weapons in use were bows and arrows, swords and shields, lances, javelins and tridents, armours and similar objects specially designed for combats and battles.</p>
				<p>Chariots were greatly in use. Driving chariots during battles had been developed into a special art. So also the use of horses and elephants. The latter were employed like the modern tanks.</p>
				<p>The use of words like śataghnī (that which kills one hundred persons at a time) and sammohanāstra (a weapon that makes people unconscious) have induced some scholars to presume that the use of cannons and poison gases was also known.</p>
				<p>The weapons were generally classified into three groups:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>Yantramukta—those discharged from a machine or mechanical device;</li>
					<li>Hastamukta—those discharged by hand;</li>
					<li>Muktāmukta—those used by hand or discharged from hand.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>The names of some weapons like vajra and āgneyāstra give rise to the surmise that fire-arms might have been in use. However, it is difficult to come to any definite conclusion.</p>
				<p>The detailed descriptions of the vyūhas or formations of the armed forces given in our epics, also help us to appreciate the degree of perfection that our ancient and medieval military science had achieved.</p>
				<h2>Mining and Metallurgy</h2>
				<p>Mining for precious metals and precious stones have been described by Megasthanes as wellknown to the Hindus.</p>
				<p>The archaeological excavations at Baragunda (Singhbhum), Mosabani (Singhbhum), Agniguṇḍala (Andhra Pradesh) and Wynad (Kerala) have revealed extensive, abandoned, copper and gold mines.</p>
				<p>Even the Vedic Āryans were familiar with the use of several metals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, tin, bronze and iron. This presupposes that they had a fair knowledge of mining and metallurgy.</p>
				<p>The wrought-iron pillar at Delhi, near the Qutb Minar, assigned to the period, early 4th century A. D., is considered as a marvel even today. Not only its dimensions<aside>It is 7.2 metres (24 ft.) in height, 40 centimeters (16 inches) in diameter and weighs 6 tonnes!</aside> but also its rustless shining surface, speak volumes about its quality and the technical perfection attained by its makers. The copper image of Buddha<aside>It is cast in pure copper. It is $2 \dfrac{1}{4}$ metres (7.5 ft.) in height and weighs 1 tonne. It belongs to the 5th cent. A. D.</aside> found at Sultangunj (Bihar) is another marvel. Huen Tsang (A. D. 600-664) refers to a colossal 24 metres (80 ft.) copper statue of Buddha established by the king Pūrṇavarman near the Nālandā University in Bihar.</p>
				<p>There is enough evidence to show that embossed or cast copper coins were issued by the Mauryan and other kings.</p>
				<p>Silver and gold jewellery with granulation and filigree work made on copper and bronze moulds have been found at the Takṣaśilā site (circa 3rd century B. C.).</p>
				<p>Thus, we can say that smelting of copper and other metals on an extensive scale was known to the Hindus even about two thousand years ago.</p>
				<p>Specimens of iron implements and a large variety of weapons discovered at Tirunelveli or Tinnevelly (Tamil Nadu) have been assigned to the period 4th century B. C. Radio-carbon dating of some of the samples of iron objects obtained in the archaeological excavations in parts of North India near Delhi varies from 1025 to 537 B. C.</p>
				<p>The king Porus is said to have gifted a piece of steel weighing 13.6 kgs. (30 lbs.) to Alexander. The <em>Suśruta Saṁhitā</em> refers to many surgical instruments made of steel. Indian steel used to be exported to Western countries even at the beginning of the Christian era and was used for preparing the famous Damascus blades. Varāhamihira (6th cent. A. D.) in his <em>Bṛhatsaṁhitā</em> mentions about the tempering of steel.</p>
				<p>It can therefore be safely concluded that not only smelting of ores but also preparation of various metallic objects were well-known to the Hindus of ancient and medieval times.</p>
				<h2>Veterinary Sciences</h2>
				<p>Being an agro-centered society, the Hindus depended heavily on cows, bulls and other animals of the bovine species. The rulers of the land needed horses and elephants for their armed forces. Hence these three animals attracted great attention of the society and a veterinary science centred round them developed in course of time. They are: Gavāyurveda (āyurveda pertaining to the cows or bovine species of animals), Aśvāyurveda (āyurveda pertaining to the horses) and Hastyāyurveda (āyurveda pertaining to the elephants).</p>
				<p>The <em>Gavāyurveda</em> attributed to the sage Gotama, was the standard work current until the middle ages. Apart from diseases and their treatment, the text contained information about diet, breeding, calving, lactation and milk.</p>
				<p>The principal work on Aśvāyurveda is the <em>Śālihotra-saṁhitā</em> of uncertain date. Extracts from it are found in the <em>Agnipurāṇa</em>. The <em>Śālihotra-samuccaya</em> of Kalhaṇa (12th century A. D.) is believed to be a redaction of the <em>Saṁhitā</em>. It is a voluminous work throwing light on different aspects of the horse like anatomy, physiology and pathological conditions requiring medical and surgical treatment. It also contains information relating to breed, sex, age and so on.</p>
				<p>The <em>Pālākapya-saṁhitā</em> attributed to the sage Pālākapya, is an exhaustive treatise on Hastyāyurveda. It is a work in the form of questions and answers between the sage and his disciple Romapāda. It deals with anatomy, physiology, pathology, major and minor diseases with medical and surgical treatments, drugs and diet. Another work on the same subject is the <em>Mātaṅgalīlā</em> of Nīlakaṇṭhācārya. The dates of both these works are not known.</p>
				<p>It may be of interest to mention here, though in passing, that there was a regular veterinary hospital in the campus of the Nālandā university.</p>
				<h2>Zoology</h2>
				<p>Zoology in ancient India was confined to a very general classification of animals as gleaned from Vedic literature.</p>
				<p>The <em>Saṁhitās</em> of Caraka and Suśruta give some information about carnivorous and non-carnivorous land quadrupeds and birds such as lions, tigers, bears, camels, elephants, dogs, wolves, asses, vultures, ospreys, hawks and so on. The other animals mentioned are: frogs, lizards, various kinds of reptiles, water birds like swans, ducks, cranes, flamingos and pelicans, other birds such as pigeons and kingfishers, as also different kinds of insects.</p>
				<p>The <em>Arthaśāstra</em> of Kauṭilya (300 B. C.) has several references to fish and fisheries, to rearing of animals such as cows, buffaloes, goat, sheep, horses and elephants.</p>
				<p>If the <em>Garuḍapurāṇa</em> (A. D. 900) treats of certain diseases of animals, particularly of horses and elephants, the <em>Nibandha-saṅgraha</em> of Ḍallaṇa (10th century A. D.) gives a detailed and astonishingly precise description of several animals, birds and insects.</p>
				<p>Being in constant communion with nature, the Hindus of ancient and medieval India had keenly observed the flora and the fauna around them. The literature that has come down to us in this regard is definitely useful.</p>
				<h3>10. Hindu Fine Arts and Music</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>The goddess Sarasvatī of the Hindu pantheon—the goddess of learning and wisdom—is generally pictured as having four arms. With one, she is holding a book. With two, she is playing on a vīṇā (lute). With the last she is holding the akṣamālā (rosary).</p>
				<p>This representation of her form, has a great symbolical significance. The book stands for all secular knowledge, the lute for fine arts and the rosary for spiritual wisdom. Secular knowledge helps a human being to earn his livelihood. Fine arts enrich his life, giving aesthetic pleasure and emotional satisfaction. Spiritual wisdom fulfils the ultimate purpose of life.</p>
				<p>By thus depicting the goddess of learning and wisdom, Hinduism has elevated all fields of knowledge to divine levels.</p>
				<p>For a Hindu, his art has originated from God himself. And, his art is also the best means of worshipping God!</p>
				<p>Hindu art has several facets: drawing and painting; sculpture; dance and drama; music.</p>
				<p>Actually these arts are sometimes enumerated as 64! Some of them, for instance, are: floral designs, preparing various kinds of beds, magic, culinary arts, reading from books, carpentry, goat-fighting, composing poems, physical exercises, hair dressing and so on.</p>
				<p>But, the five streams mentioned above are highly developed and hence deserve a more detailed treatment.</p>
				<h2>Drawing and Painting</h2>
				<p>Hindu tradition always attributes a divine origin to all the sciences and arts. The original propagators may be gods like the four-faced Brahmā or sages like Bharata. Citrakalā or drawing and painting, is said to have originated from the sage Nārāyaṇa, the eternal companion of the sage Nara. He is said to have created Ūrvaśī, the best of heavenly nymphs, by drawing a picture on the urvī or earth and then infilling it with life. His work, the <em>Citrasūtras</em>, which he taught to Viśvakarma, is not available now.</p>
				<p>According to the standard works on this art, a good drawing or painting, must have several features like form, proportion, expression of emotion, grace, and colours. These works are: <em>Kuṭṭanīmata</em> of Dāmodara Gupta, <em>Viṣṇudharmottara</em> <em>Purāṇa</em> (A. D. 500), <em>Mārkaṇḍeya Purāṇa</em> (A. D. 300). <em>Abhilaṣitārtha-cintāmaṇi</em> (of Someśvara, A. D. 1129) and <em>Śilparatna</em>.</p>
				<p>There are four stages involved in the preparation of a painting: a) preparing the basic surface like a white cloth; b) making it stiff by smearing with a paste of rice or similar material; c) drawing the outlines with charcoal or a black pencil; d) finishing with appropriate colours.</p>
				<p>Several varieties of drawing and painting are described in these works. Though paintings can be prepared depicting all the nine sentiments (navarasas<aside>They are: amour (śṛṅgāra), humour (hāsya), heroism (vīra), compassion (karuṇa), wonder (adbhuta), fear (bhayānaka), horror (rudra), aversion (bībhatsa) and peace (śānta)</aside>) one can keep in one&#x2019;s home only those that depict humour, amour and peace and <em>not</em> the others. However, in public places, pictures depicting all the nine can be exhibited.</p>
				<p>These works also give detailed instructions regarding painting, whether they are objects of nature like uneven surfaces of earth, waves of ocean, fire, smoke and clouds or living beings including every limb of the human beings.</p>
				<p>Let us now turn our attention to the ancient pictures and paintings discovered till now in various parts of India.</p>
				<p>The oldest pictures so far discovered are located in the caves of Kaimur and Vindhya hills as also Raigarh and Mirzapur, all in Madhya Pradesh. They belong to the prehistoric age and were drawn using crude implements of stone. They mostly depict hunting scenes.</p>
				<p>The paintings in the Jogimara caves of the Ramgadh hills (Surguja district, Madhya Pradesh) (200 B. C.) and the ones at Ajantā (Maharashtra) (100 B. C.) are the earliest ones discovered so far.</p>
				<p>The Ajantā paintings are the creation of expert artists and must have been done during the period 100 B. C. to A. D. 700. Their influence seems to have spread to other parts of Asia like Tibet, Afghanistan, China, Korea and even Japan. These paintings are outstanding due to their perfection in the shape of the lines, proportion and combination of colours, variety and expression of emotions. Various aspects of nature like trees, flowers, animals, human beings including kings and queens, gods of the heavenly regions, Buddhas and Bodhisattvas are the themes of these paintings.</p>
				<p>Another variety of paintings has been discovered in the Bāgh Caves (Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh) and they too resemble the Ajantā paintings. The other well-known art-works are: in the Bādāmi caves of Karnataka (A. D. 700); in Sittanivāsal of Pudukoṭe (Tamil Nadu; A. D. 750); in Ellora (Kailāsa Temple; A. D. 800) of Maharashtra; in the Bṛhadīśvara temple of Tanjavur (A. D. 1100); in some of the temples of Kerala belonging to the erstwhile States of Travancore and Cochin (A. D. 1100-1700).</p>
				<p>The period A. D. 800 to 1200 seems to have been a dark one since no paintings of significance have been unearthed. Historians feel that the Muslim invaders of this period might have destroyed such paintings.</p>
				<p>The next phase of development in the Hindu art is the evolution of the Rajasthan school, known as Rājaputra or Rajput style of art. This school of art has earned for itself a unique place in the panorama of Hindu culture. It has successfully achieved a balanced combination of the secular and the sacred side of life. Jaipur was the nerve-centre of this art. The period of development was from the 15th to the 18th centuries.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>While depicting the various aspects of human emotions, due place has been given to natural sense-attractions as also to the struggle against them to achieve self control. Scenes from the epics—the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> and the <em>Mahābhārata</em>—various incidents culled from the Rādhā-Kṛṣṇa episodes, traditions of the worshippers of Kṛṣṇa as also of Śiva, form the basic themes of these paintings.</p>
				<p>Another speciality of this school is the pictorial representation of the various tunes of Hindu music—the Rāgas and the Rāgiṇīs—basing them probably on the description of these tunes as given in the standard works on music.</p>
				<p>The Rajput art gradually extended to Punjab and some sub-Himalayan regions like Nūrpur, Cambā, Jammu and Kāṅgra. It gradually acquired a new name—the Pahāḍī school. It reached the summit of its glory during the reign of the Kāṭoch rulers (15th to 17th centuries).</p>
				<h2>Sculpture</h2>
				<p>Allied with the art of drawing and painting is that of sculpturing. Since there are references to the images of gods in all the four Vedas, it can safely be concluded that the art of sculpturing was current even around 3000 B. C. The <em>Baudhāyana Gṛhyasūtras</em> (600 B. C.) clearly mentions not only about the images of Viṣṇu, Gaṇeśa and Yama, but also gives the details regarding their establishment and worship. Bronze images have been unearthed at the Harappan site of excavation (3000 B. C.).</p>
				<p>During the Vedic age, images were being fashioned out of wood, stone, metal, clay and precious stones.</p>
				<p>Images for private worship at home and temples for public worship had already made their appearance even during the Mauryan period (300 B. C.)</p>
				<p>With the growth of images, mūrtiśilpa or sculpturing, developed into a regular science. Some of the standard treatises on this are: <em>Śukranītisāra</em>, <em>Mayamata</em>, <em>Mānasāra</em>, <em>Bṛhatsaṁhitā</em>, <em> Śilparatna</em>, <em>Śilpasāra</em>, <em>Suprabhedāgama</em> and <em>Kāraṇā-gama</em>.</p>
				<p>They give all the relevant details needed in the process of preparing the images.</p>
				<p>Images of gods and goddesses are broadly divided into two groups: Śaiva and Vaiṣṇava. Each of these, again, can be subdivided into three groups: 1) calaprati-mās or movable images; 2) acalapratimās or immovable images; 3) calācalapratimās or movable and fixed images.</p>
				<p>The calapratimās are made of metal and are used during utsavas (festivals). They are hence called &#x2018;utsavamūrtis&#x2019; (processional images). The acalapratimās also called &#x2018;dhruvaberas&#x2019; or &#x2018;mūlavigrahas&#x2019;—are generally prepared out of stone and fixed to the ground in temples. If the same image is kept in the temple for worship and also taken out in procession it is called &#x2018;calācala&#x2019;. The wooden images in the Jagannātha temple at Purī (in Orissa) belong to this category.</p>
				<p>The images may also be in three postures: sthānaka (standing), āsana (sitting) and śayāna (reclining or resting). Only the images of Viṣṇu are shown in the third posture.</p>
				<p>Images may also be ugra (terrible) and śānta (benign).</p>
				<p>The particular aspects of the deities represented by the images can be recognized by observing the mudrā (position of the hand and the fingers), āsana (posture of legs and feet), cihna (symbol), vasana (dress) and ābharaṇa (ornaments). Among the mudrās and āsanas, abhayamudrā (assuring protection) and varadamudrā (granting boons), padmāsana (lotus posture) and yogāsana (meditation posture) are most common. Śaiva and Śākta images (images of Śiva and Devī) have ḍamaru (drum), triśūla (trident), pāśa (noose), aṅkuśa (goad), bāṇa (arrow), khaḍga (sword) and so on, as their symbols. Cakra (discus), śaṅkha (conch), gadā (mace) and padma (lotus) are most common for Vaiṣṇava (Viṣṇu and related deities) images.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>There are elaborate rules guiding the sculpturing of images. The height or the length, width, girth as also the proportion of the various limbs—each one of these is fixed according to the tālamāna system. A &#x2018;tāla&#x2019; is the measurement of the palm of the hand (from the tip of the middle finger to the wrist) and is equal to the length of the face. The navatāla system wherein the total length or height of the image is nine times (nava = nine) the length of the face, is recommended for the images of gods.</p>
				<p>In course of time, four distinct styles of sculpturing evolved. They are: the Madurai style; the Kāñcī style; the Cālukya-Hoysaḷa style; the Bengali style (current in Bengal, Assam and Orissa).</p>
				<p>Though all of them follow the general rules of iconography as given in the standard works, they also exhibit their special features.</p>
				<h2>Music</h2>
				<p>If drawing and painting can strike the eyes, music has the power to rouse the heart. It has the potential to express the moral and spiritual sentiments to the highest degree. It is not only the medicine that can cure an aching heart but also help a spiritual aspirant to raise his soul to God. That is why the Hindu sages have sometimes christened it as &#x2018;nādayoga&#x2019; and God as &#x2018;Nādabrahma&#x2019;. And, music has almost always allied itself with religion and spiritual values.</p>
				<p>The three basic notes of Vedic chanting—udātta, anudātta and svarita—are the fundamental notes of Indian music. These three notes developed later into seven in the <em>Sāmaveda</em>. They are: kruṣṭa, prathama, dvitīya, tṛtīya, caturtha, mandra and atisvāra. They correspond to the notes pañcama (pa), madhyama (ma), gāndhāra (ga), ṛṣabha (ri), ṣaḍja (sa), daivata (da) and niṣāda (ni), in modern Indian music. Hence, the <em>Sāmaveda</em> has been considered to be the origin of Indian music.</p>
				<p>During the earliest period, saṅgīta or music was considered to be an integral part of nṛtya or nāṭya or dancing. Dancing, music and drama (nāṭaka) were treated as one unit—Nāṭyaśāstra or the science of dramaturgy. And, Bharata&#x2019;s <em>Nāṭya-śāstra</em> (A. D. 100) is considered to be the original systematic treatise on this subject. The other standard works often referred to are:</p>
				<p><em>Saṅgītaratnamālā</em> by Mammaṭa (A. D. 1100) <em>Saṅgītaratnākara</em> by    Śārṅgadhara (A. D. 1260) <em>Saṅgītasāra</em> by Vidyāraṇya (A. D. 1380) <em>Saṅgītadarpaṇa</em> by Dāmodara (A. D. 1380) <em>Svarameḷakaḷānidhi </em>by Rāmayāmātya Todaramalla (A.D. 1600)</p>
				<p>In Indian music the two invariable basic notes are sa and pa. The others—ri, ga, ma, da and ni—are of two varieties each, making a total of 12 notes. Sometimes 16 notes are described, though, for all practical purposes 12 are enough.</p>
				<p>A permutation and combination of these notes produce a variety of rāgas or tunes. Those tunes in which all the seven notes are present are called &#x2018;melakartā&#x2019; or &#x2018;janaka&#x2019; rāgas. The derivatives are known as &#x2018;janya&#x2019; rāgas.</p>
				<p>Veṅkaṭamakhi (A. D. 1600) in his <em>magnum opus</em>, the <em>Caturdaṇḍiprakāśikā</em> (written in Sanskrit verses) has grouped the 72 janaka-rāgas into two groups of 36 each. He has also dealt with many other fundamental aspects of music in this great work which has remained as an invaluable guide to all musicians.</p>
				<p>As far as the janya or the derived rāgas are concerned, they can be limitless. Even now, talented musicians are inventing new rāgas.</p>
				<p>The various rāgas or tunes are capable of expressing a variety of feelings and sentiments such as love, anger, tenderness, sorrow, disappointment, pity, joy and so on.</p>
				<p>Another speciality of Indian music is that specific rāgas are assigned to specific periods of the day or night. If certain rāgas like Māyāmāḷava-gauḷa (or Bhairav) are to be sung early in the morning, Kalyāṇī (or Yaman) is to be sung in the night. The very atmosphere at that time is said to enhance its power to rouse the particular sentiment to which it is tuned.</p>
				<p>If symphony is the heart of Western music, śruti (drone or basic musical sound as the one produced by the tānpūra), rāga (tune), tāla (fixed number of beats for each unit) and laya (uniform speed for the beats) are the basics for Indian music. Thirty-five varieties of tālas have been evolved.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>Though Indian music had been one for several centuries, due to the Persian influence exerted during the Mughal period, there was a gradual branching into two schools: the uttarādi or the North Indian and the dakṣiṇādi or the South Indian (also called Carnāṭic). There are many similarities as also notable distinctions between the two schools. The uttarādi school further got subdivided into gharāṇās or traditions which are alive and active even today.</p>
				<p>A music performance is generally centred round the vocalist. In the South Indian classical music the vocalist is accompanied by the violinist and another who plays on the mṛdaṅgam (a percussion instrument). Of course, the tānpūra should always be there as the basic instrument. Sometimes other percussion instruments like ghaṭam (a mud pot), khañjīra (a disc-like percussion instrument) and morsing (a small stringed instrument played by mouth) are also added.</p>
				<p>In the North Indian classical music performances, the vocalist is generally accompanied by the harmonium and the tabalā (a percussion instrument in two pieces) players. Occasionally stringed instruments (similar to the violin) like the sāraṅgī or the dilrūbā are also used. Tānpūra is, however, a must.</p>
				<p>Apart from vocal music, Indian music system is rich in instruments too. Even in the Vedic and allied literature there are references to vīṇā (lute), vāṇa (an instrument with 100 strings), dhanurvīṇā, dundubhi (drum), āḍambara and so on. The dhanurvīṇā is said to be the precursor of the violin now imported from the West. Many other instruments like bānsurī, flute, sitār, sarod, goṭuvādyam, pakhvāj, khol, clarionet, nādasvaram and shehanai have also come into use over the years.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<h2>Dance</h2>
				<p>Dance, like music, has always been a means by which human beings have tried to express their inner feelings. For instance, the rustic villagers express their gratitude to the deities of nature even now, through their folk-dances during the harvest season. In most of the societies there are dances for every important social occasion.</p>
				<p>Indian dance is said to have originated from Śiva and Pārvatī, the divine couple, the parents of the world. Gods like Gaṇapati and Kṛṣṇa, minor deities like Nandi and Bhṛṅgi, goddess Sarasvatī—all of them are fond of dancing.</p>
				<p>The <em>Saṅgītaratnākara</em> of Śārṅgadeva (A. D. 1260) calls the art of dancing as <em>Nāṭyaveda</em> and declares that the four faced Brahmā, the creator, taught it to Bharata who exhibited it before Śiva himself in Kailāsa. Then Śiva, who had taught the tāṇḍava dance to the sage Taṇḍu, asked him to teach that also to Bharata. Then Pārvatī, Śiva&#x2019;s spouse, taught the lāsya dance (specially suited to women) to Uṣā, the daughter of Bāṇa. This is how the science and art of dancing was spread in this world.</p>
				<p>Vedas refer to dancing as also to several musical instruments. Figurines in the dancing pose have been found in the Indus valley excavations (3000 B. C.). The two epics also speak of dancing as a flourishing art.</p>
				<p>Encouragement given to dancing right from the times of the Mauryan emperors helped it to grow to phenomenal proportions. The devadāsī custom, whatever might have been its evil effects, also helped in the development of the dancing arts.</p>
				<p>The standard works dealing with the art of dancing are:</p>
				<p><em>Nāṭyaśāstra</em> of Bharata; <em>Bharatārṇava</em> of Nandikeśvara; <em>Abhinayadarpaṇa</em>, also of Nandikeśvara.</p>
				<p>Both the authors seem to be legendary figures. The extant <em>Nāṭyaśāstra</em> may not be the original. A commentary <em>Abhinayabhāratī</em> on it by Abhinavagupta has been discovered, but only in fragments.</p>
				<p>Outward expression of inner emotions is the heart of the dancing art. It is done by abhinaya or rhythmic movements of limbs, various types of stances and mudrās or poses of hands. Dresses suitable to the occasion and music with all the accompaniments enhance the total effect. The themes are generally chosen from the epics and the purāṇas.</p>
				<p>The major dance traditions that are still very much in vogue are:</p>
				<ul class="unlist">
					<li>Bharata-nāṭya</li>
					<li>Kathak</li>
					<li>Kathakkaḷī</li>
					<li>Kūcipuḍi</li>
					<li>Maṇipurī</li>
					<li>Oḍissī-nāṭya</li>
					<li>Sattriya-nāṭya</li>
					<li>Yakṣagāna</li>
				</ul>
				<h2>BHARATA-NĀṬYA</h2>
				<p>Bharata-nāṭya is the science and art of dance as taught by the sage Bharata. It is much more common in South India and has been preserved over the centuries. After the fall of the Vijayanagar empire, the artists of this school migrated to Tañjāvūr (Tanjore) and developed it further.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>The word &#x2018;bharata&#x2019; is sometimes treated as an abbreviation of bha (= bhāva, abstract idea), ra (= rasa, emotion) and ta (= tāla, musical time or measure).</p>
				<p>It has branched off into three traditions: the Sadir-nāṭya, the Bhāgavatameḷā and Kuruvañji.</p>
				<p>The Sadir-nāṭya was generally done by the devadāsīs (temple dancers) to the background of Carnāṭic music, comprising amorous songs with a greater stress on foot-work, Sanskrit hymns and songs depicting scenes from Kṛṣṇa&#x2019;s life to embellish the acting part and conclusion with tillānas (musical compositions with words imitating the sounds of percussion instruments).</p>
				<p>The Bhāgavata-meḷās are actually dance dramas with religious themes and are enacted in temples.</p>
				<p>In the Kuruvañji, the dancer represents the individual soul in search of the divine who is the deity of the temple. This is always a religious dance performed in temples.</p>
				<h2>KATHAK</h2>
				<p>The Kathak dance tradition had its origin in the devotional dances current in Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh. Devotees of Kṛṣṇa used to dance, to the accompaniment of bhajans (devotional songs), trying to express the sentiments contained therein. The themes were also connected with Kṛṣṇa.</p>
				<p>The Kathak branched off into two traditions: the Jaipur (Rajasthan) and the Lucknow (Uttar Pradesh) traditions. Subtlety and speed are the characteristics of the former while the latter is marked by acting and grace.</p>
				<h2>KATHAKKAḶĪ</h2>
				<p>This is a speciality of the Kerala State and Malayāḷam culture. It seems to have originated from folk-dances with paurāṇic themes.</p>
				<p>It has three varieties: Kūttu, Rāmanāṭṭam and Kṛṣṇanāṭṭam.</p>
				<p>The Kūttu dance was the privileged possession of the Cākyār community of Kerala. It used to be exhibited in temples during festival days, the themes being chosen from paurāṇic legends or even famous incidents culled from history.</p>
				<p>The other two are identical in form and pattern except that the former has Rāma episodes and the latter Kṛṣṇa episodes for their themes.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>In the Kathakkaḷī, the dancers do not speak or sing but express all the sentiments through acting. The themes are invariably from Hindu mythology. Colours of the dress and ornaments are apportioned as per the nature of the character, viz., whether it is sāttvik, rājasik or tāmasik.</p>
				<p>The Kathakkaḷī dances are usually held in the open fields and that too in moonlight.</p>
				<p>Announcing about the Kathakkaḷī programme, invocatory verses from behind the screens, beating of drums, entry of the first dancer, narration of the story from the background, dance and acting by the persons playing the various roles, their conversations being recited in the background—these are the various aspects of the programme.</p>
				<h2>KŪCIPUḌĪ</h2>
				<p>This is a typical dance of Andhra Pradesh. It got prominence during the days when the Vijayanagar Empire flourished.</p>
				<p>It is known for its sāttvik sentiments and acting.</p>
				<p>The themes selected are mostly from the 17th century works—the <em>Brahma- kalpam</em> and <em>Pārijātam</em> of Siddhāndhra Yogi—and others such as <em>Gollakalpam</em>, containing Vedāntic conversations between a cowherdess and a brāhmaṇa.</p>
				<p>Daśāvatāras are another popular theme.</p>
				<h2>MAṆIPURĪ</h2>
				<p>The promoters of the Maṇipurī dance claim that the tradition was started by Śiva himself, at the suggestion of his spouse Pārvatī. Citrāṅgadā of <em>Mahā-bhārata</em> fame whom the Pāṇḍava hero Arjuna married, was a princess of the Maṇipurī royal family and was an accomplished dancer.</p>
				<p>Originally, the Maṇipurī dances centred round the Śiva-Pārvatī themes. However, as Vaiṣṇavism spread in that area, Kṛṣṇa became the hero and central figure.</p>
				<p>Bhāgyacandra, the king of Maṇipur (18th century) introduced the Rāsalīlā dance after building a temple for Kṛṣṇa (called Govinda-svāmin). In course of time, six modes of dancing, suitable for six ṛtus or seasons, evolved. They are: Vasantarāsa, Kuñjarāsa, Kartārāsa, Nartarāsa, Divārāsa and Mahārāsa.</p>
				<p>Another style called Lāy-haraubā is also current. This is deemed to be very ancient and considered as the original of the Maṇipurī dances. It includes enactment of the various stages of creation by God and is generally spread over a month.</p>
				<p>Rāsalīlā, the dance of Kṛṣṇa with the gopīs of Vṛndāvana, is another aspect of the Maṇipurī school. It also depicts the various incidents from the life of Kṛṣṇa and hence the performance is spread over the whole night.</p>
				<h2>OḌISSI-NĀṬYA</h2>
				<p>It is an ancient tradition of dancing based on Bharata&#x2019;s Nāṭyaśāstra. Being influenced by the Oriya style of music, it developed its own characteristic features. It was actually a dance by the devadāsīs before the Lord Jagannātha in the famous temple at Purī, generally assigned to the 12th century A. D. By the 14th century, the tradition of &#x2018;nartaka-bālakas&#x2019; (boy-dancers) was also developed.</p>
				<p>The Oḍissi tradition of dancing as resurrected now, has integrated into itself both the North Indian and the South Indian styles. The background music is mainly North Indian. Some characteristic features of Bharatanāṭya, Kathakkaḷī and Kathak are also found in it. Story of Kṛṣṇa and themes as found in Jayadeva&#x2019;s (A. D. 1200) <em>Aṣṭapadī</em> are the backbone of the present-day Oḍissi dances.</p>
				<h2>SATTRIYA-NĀṬYA</h2>
				<p>Śaṅkara Deva (A. D. 1486-1568), the great Vaiṣṇava teacher of Assam, established a number of Vaiṣṇava Maṭhas (centres of a religious denomination or cult) to propagate his cult. These Maṭhas in course of time started &#x2018;sattras,&#x2019; centres of religious instructions. These sattras introduced devotional dances called &#x2018;Sattriya-nāṭya&#x2019; which have protected their religious and devotional tradition.</p>
				<p>These dances have two branches: Jumurśāli and Rās. The former is connected with Kṛṣṇa&#x2019;s life and the latter with the Rāsalīlā or Kṛṣṇa&#x2019;s dance with the gopīs.</p>
				<p>The Jumurśāli dance is a kind of religious exercise specially practised and enacted by young men of the sattras who have dedicated their lives for this purpose. The old teachers who train them support the dance with background music.</p>
				<h2>YAKṢAGĀNA</h2>
				<p>Prevalent in parts of Karnataka, the Yakṣagāna (also called Bayalāṭa) is a dance-drama and is similar in form to the Kathakkaḷī of the Kerala State. Though based on the techniques given in Bharata&#x2019;s <em>Nāṭyaśāstra</em> it has attained a strong local colour. The artists not only dance but also sing and talk according to the roles they have to play. The themes are invariably taken from the epics and the purāṇas.</p>
				<h2>FOLK-DANCES</h2>
				<p>Whatever has been described so far, applies to the refined and cultured systems of dancing developed as an art. However there are several varieties of folk-dances spread all over the country which have become an inalienable part of the daily life of the masses. On all joyous occasions of life like marriage, birth in a family, festivals and sacred days, good harvest and so on, the common people—men and women, young and old—dance in their own way. However, over the centuries, these dances too have assumed some set patterns. Some of them may be mentioned here:</p>
				<table class="table table-striped">
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td>Bhāṅgrā</td>
							<td>(Punjab)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Gārbā</td>
							<td>(Gujarat)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Ghamar</td>
							<td>(Rajasthan)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Hoḷi</td>
							<td>(Manipur)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Kolāṭa</td>
							<td>(Karnataka)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Lūḍi</td>
							<td>(Punjab)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Paṅgi</td>
							<td>(Himachal Pradesh)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Suggi-kuṇita</td>
							<td>(Karnataka)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Tabal Coṅgbi</td>
							<td>(Manipur)</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Tiyān-bāghi</td>
							<td>(Punjab)</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</table>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>There is no gainsaying the fact that dances have not only enriched our national culture but have also added a new dimension of joy and pleasure to the life of our masses.</p>
				<h2>Drama</h2>
				<p>According to the <em>Nāṭyaśāstra</em> of Bharata, music and dancing are an integral—but subsidiary—part of nāṭaka or drama. However, both of them gradually developed into independent streams of art. Drama, on the other hand, continued to retain them also as its parts.</p>
				<p>Drama, as an item of social education and entertainment, must have originated at a very early period. The Ṛgvedic mantras wherein a ṛṣi, under the exciting influence of soma juice, challenges Indra to fight with him, or, another one pathetically describes his fate brought about by his weakness for gambling, point to the histrionic talents inherent in many human beings.</p>
				<p>The basic theme of a drama is expressed through conversations and music with appropriate acting. The total effect will be enhanced by proper dress, ornaments and equipment. All these are dealt with in the <em>Nāṭyaśāstra</em> of Bharata.</p>
				<p>For the enactment of a drama, a suitable place, called &#x2018;raṅgasthala,&#x2019; was necessary. It could be triangular, square, circular or semicircular in shape depending on the availability of space. It was generally divided into two parts: the raṅgabhūmi (stage) and the prekṣāgṛha (auditorium). During the earlier period, these two parts used to be of equal dimensions.</p>
				<p>The stage had a green-room, a back stage and a front stage as also a rest room at the side. Screens were very much in use.</p>
				<p>Dresses and ornament as also different hair-styles appropriate for the roles played have been described in detail in the works of nāṭyaśāstra. Masks also were in use.</p>
				<p>The themes of the dramas in ancient days might have been chosen from the mythological literature. With the advent of classical Sanskrit literature, social themes too might have become popular as evidenced by the dramas of Kālidāsa, Bhavabhūti (8th cent.), Śūdraka (3rd cent.) and others.</p>
				<p>There is reason to believe that the dramatic art might have branched off into two streams—the refined type for kings, courtiers and the elite of the society; the folk-type meant for the masses.</p>
				<p>It may safely be assumed that dramatics was a well-developed art in India even during the beginning of the christian era.</p>
				<h3> 11. Hindu Culture Outside India</h3>
				<h2>Introduction</h2>
				<p>The desire for conquest is inherent in human beings. Conquest, however, can be of two types: physical conquest through war and violence; cultural conquest through the head and the heart. Histories of nations over the centuries have proved that it is the latter that survives whereas even the traces of the former may be thrown out when the conquered nation rebels and reasserts itself, regaining its lost freedom.</p>
				<p>The cultural conquest has another, a tremendous, advantage. The heart can mellow the head when the latter displays arrogance. And, the head can harden the former if it leads to debilitating sentimentalism.</p>
				<p>The way Hindu culture, based on the multifaceted Hindu religion, has quietly spread far beyond the geographical boundaries of India, proves this theory. It is the sages and savants, sans the Sword and sans the Book, that went out of this country to other regions of the globe to spread the message of universal love and brotherhood. They were least interested in political colonization or accumulating wealth through trade and commerce. India had plenty of military power and wealth. In fact it is the latter that tempted the foreigners from the Middle-East and the West to set off a series of savage invasions against this country. That neither the Hindus nor their religion and culture were wiped out of this land—on the other hand, they are still going strong—is proof enough of the wonderful religio-cultural resilience of the Hindus.</p>
				<p>Right from the beginning of the Christian era, if not earlier, Hindu religion and culture have spread to all parts of Asia, and some parts of the Middle-East as also Siberia and the Americas. It will be interesting to study this phenomenon to enrich our own knowledge of the same.</p>
				<p>For the sake of easy comprehension the presentation can be made according to the countries, arranged in the alphabetical order.</p>
				<h2>Afghanisthan</h2>
				<p>The Gāndhāra Deśa of the epic period has been identified with the present-day Afghanisthan. The name of the Kandahar city seems to confirm this.</p>
				<p>Two images of Gaṇeśa have been found in this country:</p>
				<ol>
					<li> One at Gardez (belonging to the 6th century A. D.);</li>
					<li> Another at Sakar Dhar near Kabul (belonging to the 4th century A. D.). Here, images of Sūrya and Śiva (7th century A. D.) also have been discovered.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>The colossal image of Buddha near Bamiyan, measuring 53 meters (177 ft.) is another standing monument of Indian culture.<aside>This was demolished by the fanatical Muslims of the Taliban during March 2001.</aside></p>
				<h2>America</h2>
				<p>Christopher Columbus (A. D. 1451-1506) is said to have discovered America. But, did he, really? May be, but only for Europe! He discovered a few small islands between the two huge American continents and a small part of the Honduran coast!</p>
				<p>But, millennia before that, the Americas had not only been discovered but had also been covered with large settlements of Indian (Hindu) population. The Aztecs of Central Mexico, the Incas of Peru and Mayas of Yucatan (South-East Mexico) were all Hindu settlers from India.<aside>See Chaman, Lal, <em>Hindu America</em>, Bombay, New Book Co., 1940; Preface and Chapter I.</aside> They believed in the four Yugas, had adopted the gurukula system of education, the pañcāyat system of village administration and the bazaar economy, performed Soma sacrifices, worshipped Indra, Gaṇeśa and other Hindu deities, were well-versed in Hindu religious dances, practised the rituals usually associated with child-birth, marriage and death, and had the priestly hierarchy too.</p>
				<h2>Arabia</h2>
				<p>Hewitt, in his monumental work <em>Ruling Races of Prehistoric Times</em><aside>Quoted from: Chaman Lal, <em>Hindu America</em>, BOmbay, New Book Co., 1940; p. 54</aside> (Vol. II), gives an elaborate account of Hindu rule in Arabia and Mesapotamia.</p>
				<p>Will Durant, in his well-known book, <em>The Story</em> <em>of</em> <em>Civilization</em> (Vol. IV, <em>The Age of Faith</em>, New York, Simon and Schuster, pp. 161-171) writes that within the Kaaba, in the pre-Moslem days, there were several idols and that one was called &#x2018;Allah,&#x2019; which was probably the tribal god of the Quraish. Three other female images were probably Allah&#x2019;s daughters. Prof. Shustery confirms this, adding however, that there were 360 images of the gods!<aside>A. M. A. Shustery, <em>Islamic Culture</em>, Bangalore, BAPPCO, 1992; p. 4.</aside></p>
				<p>During the festival and pilgrimage seasons, &#x2018;kanyās&#x2019; or unmarried girls, took part in dancing.</p>
				<p>Even now, the Haj pilgrims are expected to wear two unstitched cloths<aside>This is called <em>ahram</em> and signifies the beginning of the vows of pilgrimage.</aside>, similar to dhoti and uttarīya (or aṅga- vastra).</p>
				<p>It is now a well-recognized fact that the Arabs were responsible in propagating in Europe, the literature and knowledge they had acquired from India, like the <em>Pañcatantra</em> and several treatises on subjects such as mathematics, astronomy, medicine and surgery and so on.</p>
				<h2>Bali and Jāva</h2>
				<p>Hindu religion and culture started spreading to the various islands of South East Asia even from the first century A. D. Some of the kings of South India who were defeated by their rivals, migrated to the islands like Jāva and established their own kingdoms there.</p>
				<p>Known as Yavadvīpa, probably from the 10th cent. A. D., Jāva was the home of well-known dynasties of kings like Śrīvijaya Rāja.</p>
				<p>The work <em>Ajiśaka</em> states that during the first century A. D., twenty thousand people from Kaliṅga (Orissa, India) came and settled down in the island of Jāva.</p>
				<p>A very large number of Hindu scriptural works in Sanskrit (excepting the Vedas) written in the Kawi script have been discovered. The following list can give an idea of the same:</p>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<td>Purāṇas (Mythology)</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td><em>Brahmāṇḍa-purāṇa</em>, <em>Viṣṇu-purāṇa</em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Mantraśāstra (Rituals and Worship)</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td><em>Sūryasevana</em> (pūjā of Śiva and Āditya); several mantras connected with ritualistic worship; Mṛtyuñjaya and Gāyatrī mantras; some hymns like <em>Viṣṇustava</em>.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Nītiśāstra (Ethics)</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td><em>Sārasamuccaya</em> of Vararuci <em>Ādipurāṇa</em>; <em>Kāmandaka Nītiśāstra</em>.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Dharmaśāstra (Social Science)</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td><em>Śivaśāsana</em>; <em>Kuṭāra Mānavāgama</em>; <em>Devāgama</em>; <em>Svarajambu</em></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Vyākaraṇa (Grammar)</td>
						<td>:</td>
						<td><em>Ādisvara</em>; <em>Amaramālā</em>; <em>Vṛttasañcaya</em>.</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
				<p>Apart from these there is the famous <em>Rāmāyaṇa Kakawin</em> in old Javanese. Works on medicines, astrology, stories and literary classics and history works have also been found. The <em>Rāmakavaca</em> (22 verses in Sanskrit) appears to be quite popular even now.</p>
				<p>Śaivism made its first appearance in Jāva around 4th century A. D. The oldest image of Gaṇeśa has been found on the Dieng plateau. Another image found near Borobudur is considered to be the finest.</p>
				<p>The residents of the island of Bali are all Hindus even today. They follow the varṇa-āśrama system. Upanayana ceremony and sandhyā ritual are being observed even now.</p>
				<p>Shadow-plays, puppet-shows and Bharatanāṭya with Hindu mythological themes are still in vogue.</p>
				<h2>Borneo (Indonesia)</h2>
				<p>Around the 5th century A. D. Hinduism had already penetrated into Borneo. An epigraphical record discovered at Kotei describes the performance of some Hindu rites there. Most of the images discovered in Borneo are either Śaivite (including a Gaṇeśa image) or Buddhist. A Sanskrit inscription on a yūpastambha (pillar of sacrifice used in Vedic rituals) has also been found and has been attributed to Mūlavarma (A. D. 480).</p>
				<h2>Burma (Myanmar)</h2>
				<p>Even during Aśoka&#x2019;s time (272-232 B. C.) Buddhism had spread to Burma. The first Hindu kingdom had been established in the Arakan province by A. D. 162. The Vikramarāja dynasty and the Sukhodaya kingdom came into existence in the 8th and the 9th centuries.</p>
				<p>King Poonnareeka (Puṇḍarīka?) who ascended the throne of the Pegu dominion in 746 A. D. was considered as a lover of brāhmaṇas. It was he who built the city of Ramanago (City of Rāma). The Rangoon City of today stands on the same site.</p>
				<p>The people of Pegu were known as the Mons and also as Talaiṅgs, thereby suggesting their migration from the Telengana region of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
				<p>With their knowledge of astrology and other sciences, the brāhmaṇas among the Talaiṅgs held important positions even in the courts of the Buddhist kings. While performing religious ceremonies on special occasions such as coronation of a king or laying the foundation for a new building, they had introduced the worship of Nārāyaṇa.</p>
				<p>There are good reasons to believe in the existence of a Viṣṇu temple at Pagan, from an inscription engraved on sand-stone, containing a Sanskrit verse from the famous <em>Mukundamālā Stotra</em> of Kula-śekhara, but in the Grantha script.</p>
				<p>The Burmese law-books, called <em>Dhammathats</em>, are based on the <em>Manu-smṛti</em>. They are still recognised as valid legal authority regulating inheritance and other domestic disputes.</p>
				<h2>Cambodia (Kampuchia)</h2>
				<p>Known as Kambuja-deśa in our paurāṇic literature, the first kingdom of Cambodia is said to have been established by one Kauṇḍinya, a disciple of Aśvatthāma. He married a Nāga princess, Somā by name, built a capital Bhavapura and started the Somavaṁśa line of Hindu rulers there.</p>
				<p>The great sage Agastya from South India, is reputed to have spread the Hindu religion and culture in the entire South East Asia and is highly revered in Cambodia even now.</p>
				<p>Numerous inscriptions—most of them in faultless Sanskrit—have been found in Cambodia, confirming the spread of Hindu religion and culture.</p>
				<p>Both the Bhāgavata (Vaiṣṇava) and the Śaiva cults were popular. Temples of Śiva and Gaṇapati exist even now. There was very good understanding between the Buddhists and the Hindus. Even by the 6th century A. D., study of the Vedas, recitation of <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em>, <em>Mahābhārata</em> and<em> </em>some purāṇas, was quite common. Tantras<em> </em>like<em> Jayadrathayāmala</em> and <em>Niśśvāsa-saṁhitā</em> were in vogue. Princes of the royal families were educated in the Sanskrit grammar of Pāṇini, Siddhāntas (Śaiva?), dharmaśāstras and the darśanas also, apart from all secular fields of knowledge needed by them.</p>
				<p>Among the Hindu temples, the Angkor Vat, near the city of Angkor Thom<aside>Situated near the town Siemreap, almost on the Thai broder, the ruins were discovered in the 19th century.</aside> (built by the King Sūryavarman II, A. D. 1112-1152) is the most famous.</p>
				<p>The Bayon Vat, also in Angkor Thom, is a Buddhist temple of colossal dimensions built by Jayavarman VII (A. D. 1120-1215). The large towers exhibit gigantic masks of Bodhisattva Lokeśvara on the four sides of each and everyone of the towers.</p>
				<h2>Campā (South Annam, part of Vietnam)</h2>
				<p>Known as Campādeśa in the various Sanskrit inscriptions of that country, it is now a part of Vietnam, its South Annam region. The impact of Hindu culture must have started as early as the 2nd century A. D. The important centres of the ancient kingdom of Indo-China were: Amarāvatī (Quangnam), Vijaya (Bin-dinh); Kauthara (Nhatrang); Pāṇḍuraṅga (Phan-rang).</p>
				<p>A bronze image of Buddha found at Dong-Duong (known earlier as Indrapura) is in the Amaravati style of sculpture. It is 1.08 metres (43 inches) in height and is assigned to the period A. D. 350.</p>
				<p>The oldest king, according to an inscription discovered at Vo-Canh, belonged to the Śrīmāra dynasty (3rd cent. A. D.). A new dynasty was established by Rudravarman (A. D. 530-572) belonging to a &#x2018;brahma-kṣattriya&#x2019; family.</p>
				<p>Another monarch, Bhadravarman by name (early 5th cent. A. D.), is said to have built a temple for Śiva (&#x2018;Bhadreśvara-svāmin&#x2019; ) at the site now identified with Mison. The temple site of Mison contains ruins of over seventy small and big buildings constructed from time to time by the kings of Campā.</p>
				<p>Pṛthvīndra Varman (A. D. 758-773) and Harivarman (A. D. 800-820) were the other kings who were famous for their benign rule.</p>
				<p>A four-armed standing image of Gaṇeśa has also been discovered in the same site, near a Śivaliṅga. Skanda (Kumāra or Subrahmaṇya) was also a popular deity, not only with the masses but also with the rulers.</p>
				<p>A number of Hindu temples, belonging mostly to the 10th century A.D., are found in the same area. Some of them are still in a good condition.</p>
				<h2>Cīnā (China)</h2>
				<p>Unlike the influence of Hindu religion and culture on the countries of South East Asia, Indian influence on Cīnā or China has been confined almost entirely to the spread of Buddhism. According to one view, images of Buddha made in India, were found even during the early period of the Hān dynasty (121 B. C.). Buddhism is said to have been introduced into China during the rule of Emperor Ming in A. D. 67. History of the Liyang dynasty mentions the arrival of ambassadors from India during the years A. D. 85 to 167.</p>
				<p>A galaxy of scholarly Buddhist monks started visiting China right from A. D. 64. To mention a few: Kaśyapa Mātaṅga, Dharmaratna, Mahābala and Dharma-phala. They settled in the Lo-yang province and spent most of their time in translating many Buddhist works<aside>The number is sometimes put at 434!</aside> into the Chinese language.</p>
				<p>The greatest of such scholars was Kumārajīva (A. D. 344-413). He arrived in Chang-an during A. D. 401 and before his death in 413, had translated several Buddhist works including the more famous ones like the <em>Prajñāpāramitā-sūtras</em> and <em>Saddharma-puṇḍarīka</em>.</p>
				<p>The other Indian scholars who did notable work of translation are: Paramārtha (A. D. 499-569); Śubhākara-siṁha (A. D. 637-735); Vajrabodhi (A. D. 671-741) and Amoghavajra (A. D. 705-774).</p>
				<p>That a large number of Chinese travellers visited India from time to time for higher studies in Buddhism is now a well-recognised fact of history. Among them the following were more well-known for their life and work: Fahien (A. D. 399-410); Hiuen Tsang (A. D. 600-664); Itsing (A. D. 635-713).</p>
				<p>It is interesting to note that Gaṇeśa pictures have been discovered on wooden panels and frescoes in Khotan in West China, suggesting the spread of Hinduism at an early period.</p>
				<h2>Iran (Eastern part)</h2>
				<p>Iran—known earlier as Persia—was the home of Zoroaster (6th cent. B. C.) and his religion, Zoroastrianism or the Pārsi religion, which has a great affinity to the early Vedic Hinduism.</p>
				<p>According to the account of some Chinese travellers, the Hīnayāna Buddhism was prevalent in Persia and that the vessel which Buddha was using to beg his food, had been preserved in the store-house of the king.<aside>See Dr. S. Srikantha Sastri, <em>Bhāratīya Saṁskṛti (In Kannada), Mysore, Prasārāṅga, University of Mysore, 1975, p. 377.</em></aside></p>
				<p>Al-Beruni (A. D. 973-1039) has stated that in former times Khorasan, Persia, Iraq, Mosul and the country up to the frontier of Syria were Buddhistic.</p>
				<p>During the 7th century A. D., there was a regular exchange of envoys between the King Khusru of Persia and Pulakeśin II in South India.</p>
				<p>The late king of Iran, the Shah, who was dethroned and forced to leave the country, belonged to a ruling dynasty called &#x2018;Pahlavas&#x2019;. The Pahlavas are a race of kṣattriyas mentioned in Vedic legends.<aside>See <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> of Vālmīki, Bālakāṇḍa, 54.18.</aside> It is also interesting to note that his royal title, &#x2018;Ārya-mihir&#x2019; (&#x2018;the Sun of the Aryan race&#x2019;) is a pure Sanskrit word!</p>
				<p>The well-known story of the descent of the Gaṅgā river from heaven has found an important place in the <em>Zend Avesta</em>, the scripture of Zoroastrianism, in the pre-Islamic Iran.</p>
				<p>The Yazidis—also spelt as Yezdis—are a confederation of tribes and have a religion based on Zoroastrianism. Kurdish, Turkish and Arab tribes are included in this group. They have the caste system (4 castes, similar to the 4 varṇas), practise monogamy, believe in the transmigration of souls and revere fire.<aside>Taken from the report in the Daily, <em>Times of India</em>, December 9, 1982. See also P. N. Oak, <em>World Vedic Heritage</em>, New Delhi, Institute for Rewriting Indian History, 1984 (p. 597).</aside></p>
				<h2>Japan</h2>
				<p>Buddhism entered Japan via China and Korea. It gradually replaced Shintoism the native religion of Japan.</p>
				<p>The word &#x2018;Zen,&#x2019; in &#x2018;Zen-Buddhism,&#x2019; which became extremely popular in Japan is a corrupt form of the Sanskrit word &#x2018;dhyāna&#x2019;. Being a combination of Buddhist teachings and Taoist mysticism, it teaches meditation on the Śūnya or the Great Void, reminiscent of the Nirguṇa Brahman of Advaita Vedānta.</p>
				<p>The Buddhist temple complex Horyūji, near Nara (South Honshu, Japan) is the oldest in Japan. It contains mural paintings of Buddhas and lesser figures, all in the Ajantā style.</p>
				<p>Contacts Japan had with ancient India are also confirmed by the Japanese beliefs and stories such as a hare living on the moon, the story of the crocodile, the monkey and his liver, and, the Ṛṣyaśṛṅga legend that was developed as an opera, <em>The Story of Monoceros</em>.</p>
				<p>Huge icons of Buddha prepared during the period A. D. 747 to A. D. 1252 also bespeak of the spread and popularity of Buddhism.</p>
				<h2>Korea</h2>
				<p>Korea had contact with India right from the 4th century A. D. Buddhism was brought to Korea from China by a bhikṣu, Soondo by name, in A. D. 372, during the reign of king Sosoorimwang.</p>
				<p>The first Indian teacher—whose Korean name was Ahdo<aside>It has not been possible to know his original Indian name due to lack of sufficient evidence.</aside>—arrived in A. D. 374 and two temples were built in A. D. 375 at Pyongyang. Ten years later, the second Indian teacher, Mallānanda, came to Korea. The third one—Mookhoja by name—is said to have visited Korea during A. D. 417.</p>
				<p>Gradually different sects were established. Both the king and the people started constructing temples and vihāras (Buddhist monasteries) with images and painting of Buddha and other divinities.</p>
				<p>The manufacture of sacred utensils used in worship and other works of art contributed to the development of various fine-arts.</p>
				<p>In course of time, the Korean scholars introduced not only Buddhism, but also certain arts, crafts and literature into Japan.</p>
				<p>Kymik was probably the first priest of Korea to visit India and bring several Buddhist scriptures of the Vinaya school. Six more visited India later.</p>
				<p>Kwanrenk of Paikje was an eminent scholar who went to Japan and established the famous Horyūji temples there.</p>
				<p>Wunchenk (A. D. 613-696) of Silla was a great Sanskrit scholar responsible for establishing a special school of Buddhism.</p>
				<p>Around the 8th century A. D. the Dhyāna (Zen) cult was introduced into Korea.</p>
				<p>Construction of caves and stūpas like those in India, some musical instruments in use like the flute and mohtahk (ghaṇṭā or bell) as also temple bells bespeak of Indian influence on Korean art and architecture.</p>
				<p>The Koryuh dynasty (A. D. 936 to 1391) built and restored temples, stūpas and monasteries. The greatest achievement of these kings is the production of the <em>Mahādharmakoṣa</em> (A. D. 1070), an encyclopaedia of Buddhism, through scholars in their court. When it was destroyed by the invading Mongols, another edition was produced in A. D. 1236.</p>
				<p>The Hanguel script of Korea was developed, based on the phonetic system of Sanskrit in A. D. 1443.</p>
				<p>Indian culture has had a great influence on many aspects of Korean culture, whether art or architecture, literature, music or dance.</p>
				<h2>Laos</h2>
				<p>Originally known as &#x2018;Lava,&#x2019; Laos is one of the countries of South East Asia, deeply influenced by India. As per archaeological evidence and Chinese records, the Hindus colonised and established their kingdoms not only in Burma but also in the upper valleys of Chindwin river (in Burma or Myanmar), the Irawadi and the Salween rivers (also in Burma) as also the Mekong and the Red River areas (in South East Asia). There is evidence that a Hindu kingdom existed in Laos also. The earliest known historical king was Śrutavarman and then his son Śreṣṭhavarman.<aside>Their period is not known. However, it was much earlier than 8th century A. D.</aside> The capital of the kingdom, the Śreṣṭhapura was located around Vat Phu Hill near Bassac (in Laos).</p>
				<p>The earliest material evidence of ancient Hindu influence goes back to the 6th century A. D. The Vat Phu Hill near Bassac was then called Liṅgaparvata. A temple of Bhadreśvara Śiva is said to have existed there.</p>
				<p>In Laos, there are many figures of Buddha with certain Indian traits like the hair on the head being treated in small curls or the nāsāgradṛṣṭi (gaze being fixed on the tip of the nose).</p>
				<p>The scriptural art as also architecture of Laos also shows Indian influence as seen in the Vat Pa Ruok and Vat Ban Tan temples. They contain Gupta-Cālukyan features. The monastery Ban Peng Thai exhibits certain traits prevalent in medieval Kerala. Window frames of big buildings clearly show Hindu influence. The Vat Pra temple (17th cent A. D.) is adorned by an image of Lakṣmī standing on a lotus, over its dome!</p>
				<p>The Pālī language was common till the 16th century.</p>
				<p>The Indian gurukula system exists in Laos even now.</p>
				<h2>Malaya (Malaysia)</h2>
				<p>India&#x2019;s ties with Malaysia are closer and older than is generally recognised. By the similarities between the glass beads discovered in the Malay peninsula and those at the Hallur site of Dharawad in Karnataka, the contact between the two peoples must have been from 1000 B. C.</p>
				<p>The <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> of Vālmīki, the <em>Niddesa</em> (a Pālī canonical text belonging to a late B. C. era), the <em>Jātakas, </em>the <em>Milindapanha</em>, the <em>Śilappadikāram</em> (in Tamil), the <em>Raghuvaṁśa</em> of Kālidāsa and a host of other ancient literary works contain reference to India&#x2019;s association with South East Asia including Malaya.</p>
				<p>A Hindu king of Śrīvijaya (a maritime kingdom in Indonesia that lasted from the 7th to the 13th centuries) had already established his supremacy over parts of Malaya even by A. D. 775.</p>
				<p>Several bronze images of Buddha (Hīnayāna type) have been unearthed in the mining areas of Perak and Kinta Valley at Tanjong Rambutan.</p>
				<p>Archaeologists have found strong evidence of Tāntric Śaivism in the Kedah and Province Wellesley in Malaya where female figurines with triśūla (trident) have been unearthed. The head of a granite Nandi, the relief of a Durgā image and that of Gaṇeśa as also a liṅga too, have been unearthed, all belonging to the 7th century A. D.</p>
				<p>Tablets with Buddhist texts written in a script that resembles old Tamil have been found at Kedah of Malaya.</p>
				<p>The hilt patterns of Malay dagger, the Keris, often have figures of Hanumān and Garuḍa, for their superhuman qualities. Large water-bottle-stands, pedestals etc., carry figures from the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em>. Kitchen vessels of bronze, popular in India, have been in use in old Malay households.</p>
				<p>Hindu epics, the <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em> and the <em>Mahābhārata</em>, provide favourite themes to the Malayan theatre.</p>
				<p>The late Brāhmī script, was the script of ancient Malaysia.</p>
				<p>A very large number of words of Indian origin are used in the Malay language. Some of these are: shurga (svarga, heaven); budi (buddhi, understanding); rasa (taste, feeling); guna (guṇa, profit); denda (daṇḍa, punishment); sāksi (sākṣi, witness); lakṣa (ten thousand); menteri (mantri, minister); dipati (adhipati, king).</p>
				<h2>Mongolia</h2>
				<p>Buddhism spread to Mongolia through Tibet, by the Tibetan monk Hphags-pa, in the 13th century. He is said to have converted even the emperor Kublai Khan.<aside>M. K. Dhavalikar, <em>Gaṇeśa Beyond the Indian Borders</em>, p. 6, Quoted from; <em>India&#x2019;s Contribution to World Thought and Culture</em>, Madras, Vivekananda Rock Memorial Committee, 1970.</aside></p>
				<p>Images of Mahākāla Śiva and Nṛtta-Gaṇapati have also been found in Mongolia.</p>
				<h2>Mexico</h2>
				<p>The migration of Hindus and Buddhists from India to the Americas (from Alaska to the Andes), their establishing colonies there and spreading their religion and culture millennia before Columbus is now a well-recognized fact. The Americanist Congress held in the Mexico City in 1962, where a number of learned papers supporting this theory were presented, is the proof of this.</p>
				<p>The material concerning the religions and cultural &#x2018;invasion&#x2019; of the Americas, especially of Mexico and Peru, is so abundant that we can give only a very brief outline of the same here:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>The Aztec calendar followed by the ancient inhabitants was based entirely on the four Yuga-system of the Hindus.</li>
					<li>The people followed the varṇa-āśrama system, especially under the Inca rulers. The extent of the empire was 1.5 lakh square kilometers and the population 20 millions.</li>
					<li>The ceremonial dances of the natives as discovered by the Spaniards in A. D. 1844, were closely related to and resembled Hindu dances.</li>
					<li>The process of cremation of the dead, closely resembled that of the Hindus.</li>
					<li> Temples of Mexico—as for instance, the one at Tajin—were typically Hindu. The remains or ruins bear testimony to the same.</li>
					<li>Archaelogical monuments of Mexico bear unmistakable resemblance to Hindu temples or Buddhist stūpas.</li>
					<li>Hindu images of gods like Śiva, Gaṇeśa, Indra, Vāmana and Narasiṁha, Vānara (monkey) heroes and Ādiśeṣa, traditional temple motifs like lotus and lions, as also Buddhist images and wheels have been found in many places. Worship of some of these gods too existed.</li>
					<li>The gurukula system of education was very much in vogue.</li>
					<li>Monogamy and arranged marriages were common. Astrologers were consulted before marriage. Marriage ceremonies were simple and similar to the Hindu customs. Seeing the pole-star (by the couple) was a must.</li>
					<li>The devadāsī system was prevalent. Girls dedicated to the temple deity were expected to tend the sacred fires in the temples which were never extinguished.</li>
					<li>Belief in a life after death and transmigration of souls was a part of their philosophy.</li>
					<li>Widows of kings often practised sahagamana or satī.</li>
					<li>Coronation ceremonies of kings were elaborate religious rites, very similar to those of the ancient Hindu kings.</li>
					<li>Dasara festival was celebrated in commemoration of Rāma&#x2019;s victory!</li>
					<li>Other signs of Hindu culture are: the family system including joint-families, āyurvedic doctors and their herbal remedies, the bazaar system, the cooperative system during social and religious ceremonies, sun- worship and so on.</li>
				</ol>
				<h2>Nepal</h2>
				<p>Nepal is the only Hindu kingdom of the world existing today. Culturally it has been connected with the Indo-Gangetic plains for over 2500 years. Lumbiṇī, the birthplace of Buddha, is in Nepal.</p>
				<p>The Kirātas ruled Nepal from the 3rd century B. C. to the 5th century A. D. The Licchavis ruled from A. D. 500 to A. D. 700. Then it was the turn of the Mallavi race. All of them were Hindu rulers.</p>
				<p>Temples and stūpas of Nepal derived their inspiration from India and Tibet.</p>
				<p>The temple of Paśupatinātha on the bank of the Bāgmatī river, to the east of Kathmandu is a famous place of pilgrimage even now, for the Hindus of India. There are numerous other shrines in its vicinity.</p>
				<p>The Rādhākṛṣṇa temple at Patana is known for its grandeur.</p>
				<p>The Gaṇeśa temple at Zimpi Tandu, assigned to the period A. D. 800, is also famous.</p>
				<p>An image of Virūpākṣa-Śiva of the pre-Christian era has also been found.</p>
				<p>A beautiful wooden image of a deity with twelve hands at a temple in Bhakta-pura exhibits the special features of Nepali sculpture.</p>
				<p>Inscriptions are available from the 5th century A. D., right up to the 12th century. The script is similar to the one used in the Gupta period (4th to 6th centuries A. D.). Coins issued by the Licchavi kings are similar in format and ornamentation to the Gupta coins of India.</p>
				<p>The Nepali language written even now in the Devanāgarī script is a metamorphosed form of Sanskrit. It is much nearer to Hindī, Gujarātī and Sindhī.</p>
				<h2>Peru</h2>
				<p>It is Peru in South America—as Mexico was in the North—that has had the maximum impact of Hindu religion and culture even from the most ancient days. The Incas of Peru were none other than the Hindus who had migrated by land and sea from India.</p>
				<p>The temple of Sun at Kushko (Cuzco)—since converted into a church—built of immense blocks of stone, is a marvel of engineering and architecture. When the Spanish invaders plundered the temple they found immense wealth there.</p>
				<figure><figcaption /></figure>
				<p>The Incas—who were Sūryavaṁśis—believed in the four Yugas. Their astronomy was similar to that of the Hindus. Their almanacs were known as &#x2018;<em>Panchacta Unnanchae</em> (c.f. with the word &#x2018;pañcāṅga&#x2019;).</p>
				<p>The Incas were great builders of temples, roads, rest-houses and other public structures. Their transport system was very good. Their textiles were unequalled during their days.</p>
				<p>Hindu paurāṇic beliefs and images of gods like Sūrya, Ādikūrma, Anantanāga, goddess Maya (mother of the gods) are found in Peru even now.</p>
				<p>There was a sacrament called &#x2018;Hauracu&#x2019; which every boy at puberty had to undergo. This was remarkably similar to the upanayana ceremony of the Hindus.</p>
				<p>The Quichua (Keśava?) language of the Peruvians has hundreds of words which are analogous to Sanskrit.</p>
				<p>Some of the prayers of the Inca rulers of Peru appear to be, almost, a replica of certain Vedic hymns. They were used during the fire-ceremonies, resembling the Vedic sacrifices.</p>
				<h2>Philippines</h2>
				<p>Indian cultural influences must have arrived in the Philippines through Malaya, Indonesian archipelago and Borneo, any time during the period 200 B. C. to A. D. 300.</p>
				<p>The native language of the Philippines was deeply influenced by Sanskrit through the highly Sanskritised Malay language inscriptions of a monarch of the Śrīvijaya dynasty around the 7th century A. D.</p>
				<p>Archaelogical evidence also supports the influx of Indian influence. The clay medallion of Avalokiteśvara-Padmapāṇi of Southern Luzon, the bronze Lokeśvara image of Cebu, and the golden Garuḍa pendant of Brooke&#x2019;s Point—all assigned to the period 12th to the 14th centuries—confirm this view. Śaiva images too have been found.</p>
				<p>The Cham alphabets of the Philippines have been shown by scholars of Indology to be of South Indian origin, resembling the Pallava scripts.</p>
				<p>The Moros of Southern Philippines were originally Hindus. The hair-style of women resembles that of Kerala in India. Gold ornaments too have an unmistakable stamp of Indian origin.</p>
				<h2>Soviet Russia</h2>
				<p>Startling discoveries of Hindu and Buddhist remnants in Soviet Russia have been disclosed in a recent article by S. K. Malhan in the <em>Indian Express</em> dated Sunday the 27th November, 1983.<aside>Quoted from: P. N. Oak, <em>World Vedic Heritage</em>, New Delhi, published by the author, 1984, pp. 727-731.</aside></p>
				<p>Soviet archaeologists have found the remains of a giant Buddhist cave- monastery inside the Kara-Tepe Hill in Termez (now in Uzbekistan).</p>
				<p>According to the traveller Huoi-Tsao (A. D. 728) who visited the areas near Termez, the king and the nobility of the State, Huo To Lo (or Huttal), believed in the Buddha. There were many Buddhist monasteries there. An ancient manuscript discovered there, mentions the restoration of the Buddhist temples in Samarkhand (in Uzbekistan) in the middle of the 7th century A. D.</p>
				<p>The excavations have revealed not only cave-constructions but also other buildings including shrines, temples, stūpas and cells. The cave-temples contain genre paintings of various deities and scenes from legends.</p>
				<p>Of particular interest is the discovery of inscriptions in different languages including the Brāhmī and the Kharoṣṭhī scripts.</p>
				<p>Frescoes and images of Buddha, several Sanskrit manuscripts, pieces of silk and paper too have been recovered from the place.</p>
				<p>A Vedic fire-temple has been found at Baku on the Capsian Sea (Azerbaijan).</p>
				<p>In the Tajikistan region of Russia, carvings depicting a Vedic chariot and other things have been found.<aside><em>The Evening News</em>, Bombay, dated 30th August 1982.</aside></p>
				<p>The Russian and the Lithuanian languages are very close to Sanskrit.</p>
				<p>A Sanskrit text of Āyurveda as also a bronze idol of a Vedic deity found in Russia have been displayed at the International Academy of Indian Culture in New Delhi.</p>
				<p>Some artifacts recovered from the Adighai people, a Vedic community still surviving in Russia, include bronze axes, idols of Viṣṇu and some decorative figures. They are on display in some Russian museums. The folk-songs and dances of the community as also their oranaments smack of strong Hindu influence.</p>
				<p>The Russian carnival of the burial of Kupalo (= Cupid, Kāmadeva), lighting of a bonfire and performance of Kolo dance is very much reminiscent of the Holi festival of India with its Kāmadahana (burning of the god of lust) ritual.</p>
				<h2>Śrī Laṅkā (Ceylon)</h2>
				<p>Śrī Laṅkā—Siṁhaḷadvīpa or Ceylon—has always had intimate and lasting contact with India, both culturally and politically. The prehistoric cultural remains of Śrī Laṅkā and the ones discovered at the excavation sites of Teri in Tirunelveli of Tamil Nadu are identical.</p>
				<p>As per the epic <em>Rāmāyaṇa</em>, it was the kingdom of Rāvaṇa.</p>
				<p>The Rāma-Sītā episode is very popular in the cultural and social life of the country even now.</p>
				<p>The arrival of Prince Vijaya from the Gujarat area of India in 543 B. C. at Śrī Laṅkā marks the historical beginning of Hindu religion and culture. He established a kingdom of his own. Worship of the Hindu gods which are very common even now—Śiva, Viṣṇu, Skanda and Gaṇeśa—might have been introduced from his times.</p>
				<p>Aśoka&#x2019;s (247-207 B. C.) missionaries brought Buddhism to Śrī Laṅkā.</p>
				<p>Buddhaghoṣa brought the tooth-relic of Buddha during the regime of Mahānāmā (A. D. 401-431). During this period Gupta culture deeply influenced the art and culture of the island.</p>
				<p>During the later period—7th to the 16th centuries A. D.—the Pallava, the Coḷa, the Pāṇḍya and the Vijayanagara empires maintained close links with Śrī Laṅkā.</p>
				<p>Śaivism seems to have been the dominant religion here along with Buddhism. The latter had absorbed Viṣṇu as the protecting deity of its faith! Worship of Skanda (Subrahmaṇya or Kārttikeya) also became quite popular.</p>
				<p>The Siṁhalese script and language were deeply influenced by the Indian impact. The impact has also been considerable on the art and architecture, the Barhut, the Sāñcī and the Amarāvatī styles being more pronounced. Dance and drama too have heavily drawn upon the Bharatanāṭya style.</p>
				<p>The caste system, marriage customs and dress patterns have the South Indian—especially of Tamil Nadu and Kerala—imprint on them.</p>
				<h2>Sumātra</h2>
				<p>The island of Sumātra, is a part of the Indonesian archipelago. Hence it shares the ancient and medieval history of other parts such as Jāva, Bali and Borneo. In Sungve Batu a temple as also images of Śiva, Durgā, Gaṇeśa and Nandi have been found. In Takuvapa, icons of Viṣṇu and some Vaiṣṇava deities have been discovered.</p>
				<p>Even by the 4th century A. D. Sumātra was part of the Śrīvijaya empire. The Laigore inscription speaks of its being a centre of Buddhism too.</p>
				<h2>Thailand (Siam)</h2>
				<p>Thailand, known formerly as Siam, had been having contacts with Hindu India right from the 2nd century A. D. Recent archaeological discoveries at Prah Pathom and Pong Tak include a bronze image of Gaṇapati (of 6th century A. D.), images of Buddha (of Amarāvatī school of sculpture) and other articles of Gupta style of art and architecture. An inscription in Sanskrit belonging to the 4th century A. D., and some images of Vedic gods too have been found in these sites.</p>
				<p>Hindu religion and its scriptures, its language and literature were well-spread during this period. Sage Agastya was highly honoured.</p>
				<p>When the Thais of Yunnan in South China (called Nan-Chao or Gāndhāra) were forced to migrate due to the invasion by the Mongol chief Kublai Khan, one group of people came to Siam (probably in A. D. 1253) and settled down there. They gradually conquered the whole of Siam and Laos.</p>
				<p>The first important kingdom of the Thais was that of Sukhodaya. Indrāditya was the first king and Sajjanālaya was the capital. Some names of this period like Gāndhāra and Mithilā as also Videha indicate the continuing influence of Hindu culture. Other names like Suvarṇagrāma, Unmārga Śilā, Haripuñjaya as well as the use of Pālī language in the inscriptions and, construction of temples of Gupta style of architecture confirm this.</p>
				<p>The Sukhodaya kingdom was succee-ded by Ayodhyā kingdom—also spelt as &#x2018;Ayuthia&#x2019;—in A. D. 1350, the first king assuming the title &#x2018;Rāmādhipati.&#x2019; Its capital was Dvārāvatī. Buddhism was the main religion during the period of this dynasty. However, construction of stūpas and sculpturing of Buddha&#x2019;s icons as also Hindu temples in new styles was encouraged by the rulers.</p>
				<p>The Thai (or Siamese) language has, even now, many Sanskrit words, though in a distorted form.</p>
				<h2>Tibet</h2>
				<p>Tibet was known as Triviṣṭapa in the ancient days. Before the entry of Buddhism through Buddharakṣita, Bon, an animist cult, was the dominant religion of Tibet.</p>
				<p>Buddhism became the main religion by the 7th century A. D. when Thonmi Sambhoṭa, the court minister of the then ruler, was sent to India for higher studies. After many years, he returned to Tibet, innovated the Tibetan script, translated many works into the Tibetan language and was the inspiration behind the two encyclopaedic works—the <em>Kangyur</em> and the <em>Tengyur</em>.</p>
				<p>Guru Padmasambhava, a famous tāntric teacher from India, visited Tibet in the 8th century A. D. and preached the Vajrayāna doctrine.</p>
				<p>During this period, the king being Khri-srom-lde-btsan (A. D. 740-786), Buddh-ism became the State religion. Again, it was during this period that great scholars Śāntarakṣita and Kamalaśīla—apart from Padmasambhava—were brought to Tibet.</p>
				<p>On the advice of Padmasambhava, the king sent a body of monks from Tibet to India. The Sam-ye monastery also was built during this period.</p>
				<p>In course of time, Tibetan Buddhism developed into five major sects or Orders. Several monasteries also grew up with huge libraries and several sublime paintings and images. The now famous mantra <em>Om maṇipadme hum</em> has formed the basis of Tibetan Buddhist practices.</p>
				<p>Tibetan art, comprising many images of Śaiva, Vaiṣṇava, Śākta and Buddhist deities, mostly out of copper and bronze, resembles those of the Nālandā period. The paintings on silk cloth and walls are of the Ajantā style.</p>
				<h2>Conclusion</h2>
				<p>The foregoing brief survey of the spread of Hindu culture in various parts of the world confirms the observations made in the beginning of this chapter, viz., that it spread <em>not</em> by the power of the Sword and the Book of Crusaders, but by the power of life and wisdom of the great men of this country, fired by the missionary zeal of the spirit of &#x2018;vasudhaiva kuṭumbakam&#x2019; (&#x2018;the whole world is your family!&#x2019;). Strangely enough, not even the names of many of these ambassadors of love and peace, are known to us now!</p>
				<p>Though much of this influence has been overshadowed or uprooted by the barbaric invasions of the Semitic races, the traces still surviving are enough to reflect the glory of Hindu culture.</p>
			</description>
		</entry>
	</volume>
</eoh>
